<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: language | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/language/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-02-10T23:10:41+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Effectively Using Anki Flashcards for Language Learning]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2023/01/04/effectively-using-anki-flashcards-for-language-learning/"/>
    <updated>2023-01-04 00:00:00 +0100</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2023/01/04/effectively-using-anki-flashcards-for-language-learning</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve been using Anki to study foreign languages for three years now, and I
consistently spend about an hour a day using Anki to learn something. In this
time, I’ve studied three languages to varying degrees with the help of Anki:
Turkish, Russian, and Italian.</p>

<p>But truthfully, I can’t say that all that time spent doing Anki has always been
effective. In fact, when I look back, I feel that I wasted a lot of time using
Anki.</p>

<p>The goal of this article is to provide tips to use Anki more effectively for
those who have already tried or are currently using it for language learning but
may be using it ineffectively. It assumes background knowledge about how Anki
works without explaining every detail or term for those who may not be familiar
with Anki.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="tips-for-effectively-using-anki">Tips for Effectively Using Anki</h2>

<h3 id="study-target-language-to-native-language">Study target language to native language</h3>
<p>Suppose my native language is English, and I’m studying Russian. This means that
I recommend learning all your cards with the English side on the front, and the
Russian side on the back.</p>

<p>Some people like to learn the “recognition side” (Russian front, English back)
first. I did this for over three thousand words in Russian, and in retrospect, I
regretted it. I would often run into those same words in other contexts and
simply not recognize them. In theory, learning this way should allow you to
recognize many words. In practice, this doesn’t happen.</p>

<p>There are two problems with this approach. The first is that our brain has all
types of ways to cheat remembering the definitions of those cards: “Oh yeah, there’s a card in
this deck that means ‘to believe’, and it sounds/looks vaguely like this word.”
The second is that being able to recognize a word in a foreign language is very,
very far from being able to produce the syllables required to say it.</p>

<p>Having English in the front and Russian on the back forces you to produce the
word so that you might eventually be able to use it in a conversation. You
should also mark the word wrong even if you get one syllable or letter off,
which will happen very frequently. We often remember that a word has certain
letters or starts in a cetrain way, but we can’t always remember the full word.</p>

<p>It may seem strict to punish what seems like such a small mistake in recalling
a word, but I’ve found that even a one letter mistake quite unforgiving. For
example, if I said the word “onforgiving” instead of “unforgiving” to you, it
could definitely be a source of confusion. Or “confasion” instead of
“confusion.” Or “instod” instead of “instead.” You get the point. I can promise
you that I’ve done this in real life with real words, and people did <em>not</em>
understand what I meant to say.</p>

<h3 id="dont-spend-too-much-time-making-your-own-cards">Don’t spend too much time making your own cards.</h3>
<p>Conventional advice states that, supposedly, the most “effective”
learning comes from crafting your own cards. You’ll see comments like this
everywhere about language learning cards. I disagree.</p>

<p>I want to emphasize that in this article, <strong>effectively</strong> means not
only effectively in terms of <em>learning</em> but also in terms of <em>time</em>. It depends
on one’s goals when learning a language, but in my opinion, to start comfortably
having conversations about various topics, one really needs to know <em>thousands</em>
of words.</p>

<p>First, part of being an effective learner is acknowledging the limits of your
discipline. Creating your own cards is a painstaking process, and I don’t think
that most people have the willpower to do this for <em>thousands</em> of words. If you
do, more power to you. I’m talking here not about making cards for fifty
something words, but for, let’s say, the 800 new words or phrases that are
highlighted in the Kindle (this is about how many highlighted words I unload
from my Kindle every time).</p>

<p>But in my perspective, making your own cards is simply not the most
effective use of the limited time we have to learn a language.  Ultimately,
that’s why I wrote <a href="LINK">a script</a> to quickly create high quality cards on
scale.</p>

<h3 id="make-cards-for-phrases-and-include-prepositions">Make cards for phrases and include prepositions</h3>
<p>Even though we’ve been brainwashed to think of things in terms of words, the
truth is that learning words in isolation can cause all types of problems for
language learners.</p>

<p>When I was learning Turkish and partway through learning Russian, this was one
of the biggest mistakes that I made. I would learn a word, but often I would use
it incorrectly because words are not used in isolation, but instead, they’re
often used with mandatory auxiliary parts.</p>

<p>For example, take the English word “believe.” You can say “I believe him”, or “I
believe <strong>in</strong> him”, both of which have completely different meanings. In this
case, if you were learning English, you might want one card for “believe X” and
another card for “believe in X”.</p>

<p>It doesn’t always have to be about prepositions though. In general, I tend now
to make cards for phrases instead of individual words. When I highlight words
in my Kindle while reading, often I highlight phrases where I know all of the
words contained inside of the phrase, but I never would have produced or thought
of that combination myself.</p>

<p>Don’t be scared to edit cards to include prepositions. If I see a card with an
isolated word but I see that the example sentences frequently or always occur with a certain
preposition, I’ll often edit the card so that it tests the usage of the
preposition too.</p>

<p>The above section is slightly abstract, since it’s hard to generalize to every
language. But the point is – think about what you would need to learn to
<strong>utilize</strong> in a sentence, and learn that unit, instead of the single unit of a
word.</p>

<h3 id="make-cards-for-things-you-understand-but-wouldnt-say">Make cards for things you understand but wouldn’t say</h3>
<p>This is related to making cards for phrases. As I mentioned, when I read, I
often highlight phrases (to make Anki cards later) that I <em>completely</em>
understand. I know every word in the phrase. If I read it in a book, I would
understand it instantly. If I heard it, I would understand it.</p>

<p>But after some time, I realized that this doesn’t mean that I could say it in a
conversation.</p>

<p>The essence of this tip is the following: when you hear or read something in any
context, think not only about whether you understood it, but whether you could
or want to say it yourself.</p>

<p>I’ve made cards for very, very simple phrases – phrases that seem like they
would be learned in the first two months of studying a language, but ones that I
realized I had a gap in my knowledge. For every person, these will be different.
In my case, I often find that I have a big gap in saying concrete, real life
things, even though I understand them. When I read, I’m often marking simple
phrases, like “he picked up the X” or “he went around the corner.”</p>

<p>At some point, this habit has extended even to my native language. When I hear
or read something in English, I frequently consider whether or not I would ever
say something in that way as well.</p>

<h3 id="add-audio-when-possible">Add audio when possible</h3>
<p>I’m (now) a huge advocate of adding audio to every card. It was quite common
before for me to be able to read a word but mispronounce it if I spoke it or not recognize it if I heard it. This should rarely happen if a word is properly learned, and having audio on your card prevents that.</p>

<p>For audio, it should be possible on every card using an add-on like AwesomeTTS.
I refrained from using AwesomeTTS from an embarrasingly long time, maybe until
six months ago, because I was too lazy to figure out how to use it. It turns out
it’s not that difficult.</p>

<p>Warning: AwesomeTTS might not always get the pronunciation of a word right
either in some languages, so double check when possible. For example, on more
obscure Russian words, it’ll often place the stress in the wrong place.</p>

<h3 id="require-multiple-intervals-to-recover-failed-cards">Require multiple intervals to recover failed cards</h3>
<p>By default, when you “Again” a graduated card in Anki, you see it again, and
simply have to get it correct once. For a card that has long intervals already
(i.e., you’ve gotten it correct many times in the past), 
oTODO</p>

<p>I recently discovered that you could require more than one interval to bring the
card back into the graduated pool. That is: if I “Again” a card, I have to hit
“Good” twice in a row (once after 15 minutes, once again after 6 hours) before
it goes back in the pool.</p>

<h3 id="catch-and-reset-leeches-fast">Catch and reset leeches fast</h3>
<p>Let’s consider the following scenario. Every card</p>

<h2 id="what-do-my-cards-look-like-now">What do my cards look like now?</h2>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automatically Generating Anki Cloze Cards from Reverso]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2022/11/17/automatically-generating-anki-cloze-cards-from-reverso/"/>
    <updated>2022-11-17 00:00:00 +0100</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2022/11/17/automatically-generating-anki-cloze-cards-from-reverso</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently released a tool that I’ve personally been using (hoarding) for ten
months to generate <a href="https://apps.ankiweb.net/">Anki</a> language cards given only a
list of terms. The <a href="https://github.com/louisrli/anki-reverso-cloze">Anki Reverso Cloze
Generator</a> uses
<a href="https://www.reverso.net/text-translation">Reverso</a> in order to pull example
sentences and create cloze cards.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Here are some examples of cards that can be generated using this script.</p>

<h2 id="example-card-front">Example card front</h2>
<p><img src="https://github.com/louisrli/anki-reverso-cloze/blob/master/assets/front.png?raw=true" alt="Front of card" /></p>

<h2 id="example-card-back">Example card back</h2>
<p><img src="https://github.com/louisrli/anki-reverso-cloze/blob/master/assets/back.png?raw=true" alt="Back of card" /></p>

<p>At the time of writing, I’ve generated about 7000 cards in Russian and 3000
cards in Italian. Using addons like
<a href="https://github.com/AwesomeTTS/awesometts-anki-addon">AwesomeTTS</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/louisrli/anki-faws-image-search">FawsImageSearch</a>, it’s easy
to get some really nice cards with audio and images on them.</p>

<p>More detailed instructions can be found at the <a href="https://github.com/louisrli/anki-reverso-cloze">Github
repository</a>. It requires basic
knowledge of how to run a command in the command line. Feel free to make any
suggestions using a GitHub issue or the comment section below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
