<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-24T12:56:42+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fiilimsi: Turkish Verbal Nouns, Adjectives, and Adverbs]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/04/20/turkish-fiilimsi-verbal-derivatives/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-20T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/04/20/turkish-fiilimsi-verbal-derivatives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<style>
blockquote {
  font-style: unset;
}

blockquote hr {
  margin: 0.3em 0;
}

blockquote p:first-child {
  font-size: 12px;
  border-bottom: 1px solid #ddd;
}

/* In case we want to bold the example headers later. */
blockquote p:first-child strong {
  font-weight: unset;
}

blockquote p {
  margin-top: 0.3em !important;
  margin-bottom: 0.3em !important;
}

</style>

<p>This post talks about the concept of “fiilimsi”, which are nouns, adjectives, or
adverbs derived from verbs. In English, for example, these include gerunds
(“<em>Running</em> is fun”) or participle adjectives (“The dog <em>that I saw</em>”).</p>

<p>This post is not intended to be a comprehensive resource of all fiilimsi.
There are three categories of fiilimsi:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>isim-fiil</strong>: verbal noun</li>
  <li><strong>sıfat-fiil</strong>: verbal adjective</li>
  <li><strong>zarf-fiil</strong>: verbal adverb</li>
</ol>

<p>There’s a noticeable lack of English language resources on the internet about
certain Turkish language topics. There’s a few articles about verbal derivations
but only with minimal details. I hope this post fills that niche.</p>

<p>Almost all of this material was derived from a lesson on the <a href="https://discord.me/turkceogrenelim">Türkçe Öğrenelim
Discord</a>. Feel free to join the community
and support them on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/letslearnturkish">Patreon</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h1 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites</h1>
<p>This post is not intended for complete beginners of Turkish grammar. Fiilimsi
builds on many of the foundations of Turkish grammar. This post assumes
prerequisite familiarity in the following topics,
and as such will not be explaining any of the following in example
sentences:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Possessive</li>
  <li>Buffer letters, consonant mutation, vowel harmony</li>
  <li>Infinitive form</li>
  <li>Subjects and objects in Turkish</li>
</ul>

<p>There are sentence examples and grammar derivations that utilize the following,
though it’s possible to grasp the basic idea without a strong understanding of
these:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Simple present tense, past tense</li>
  <li>Dative, locative, accusative cases</li>
  <li>Future tense</li>
  <li>Reported past tense</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="isim-fiil-verbal-nouns">Isim-fiil: Verbal nouns</h1>

<h2 id="makmek-infinitive-as-a-subject">-mak/mek: Infinitive as a subject</h2>

<p>Infinitives are the “dictionary form” of a verb ending with <strong>-mak/mek</strong>, e.g.,
bakmak (to look).</p>

<h3 id="usage">Usage</h3>
<p>The verbal noun infinitive form:</p>

<ul>
  <li>used as subject</li>
  <li>cannot be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declension">declined</a> – that is, no
suffixes are added to it</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uqIEiUv1bVQ">a line from this song</a>)  </p>

  <p><strong>Eğlenmek</strong> güzel şey.<br />
<strong>To have fun</strong> is a beautiful thing / <strong>having fun</strong> is a beautiful thing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It should be noted that there are many other uses of the infinitive, but here
we’re talking only about its usage as a noun derived from a verb.</p>

<h2 id="mame-gerund-form">-ma/me: Gerund form</h2>

<p>The gerund form is constructed by adding <strong>-ma/-me</strong> to the verb root
(alternatively, one can think of simply removing the <strong>k</strong> from the infinitive).</p>

<ul>
  <li>yap<strong>ma</strong> (doing)</li>
  <li>bak<strong>ma</strong> (looking)</li>
  <li>sor<strong>ma</strong> (sormak)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="usage-1">Usage</h3>
<p>The gerund form:</p>

<ul>
  <li>used as object</li>
  <li>can be declined</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>Kitap <strong>okuma</strong>yı seviyorum.<br />
I love reading books.</p>

  <p>Dans <strong>etme</strong>ye başladım.<br />
I started dancing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: The <em>-ma/-me</em> suffix is also used for the negative conjugation, but do
not confuse it with the gerund construction. They can actually stack, for
example <strong>anla-ma-ma</strong> is the noun “not understanding” (<strong>anlamak</strong> – to
understand).</p>

<h3 id="declension-exception-ablative">Declension exception: ablative</h3>
<p>There is one exception where we use the infinitive instead; for the ablative
form (<strong>-dan/den</strong>), we still use the infinitive form. This also violates the
“no declension infinitive” rule. In the example below, eğlenmekten is the
object.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p><strong>Eğlenmekten</strong> keyif alırım.<br />
I enjoy having fun.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Likely this is because the gerund form causes ambiguity with
<strong>-meden/-madan</strong> (eğlenmeden), which is also a verbal adverb suffix.</p>

<h3 id="declension-exception-locative">Declension exception: locative</h3>

<p>The locative can also be used interchangeably in some contexts. In the example
below, both are valid uses of the verbal noun as an object.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>Böyle yap<strong>mada</strong> sorun yok.<br />
Böyle yap<strong>makta</strong> sorun yok.<br />
There is no problem in doing this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, you cannot use the genitive suffixes with the infinitive, so for the
example sentence below, there is only one valid construction (yap-ma-n-da, with
the n coming from the second-person genitive).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>Böyle yap<strong>manda</strong> sorun yok.<br />
There is no problem in your doing this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To summarize, you cannot use the accusative, dative, or genitive suffixes with
the infinitive, but you can use the ablative and locative.</p>

<h2 id="native-speaking-gerund-and-infinitive">Native speaking: gerund and infinitive</h2>
<p>There’s a tricky exception that’s technically not correct but will be seen in
daily speech. People add (gerund + possessed) suffixes as a way of
creating a verbal noun in lieu of <strong>both the gerund and infinitive forms above</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Subject example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Denizde <strong>yüzmek</strong> eğlenceli. (gramatically correct)<br />
Denizde <strong>yüzmesi</strong> eğlenceli. (seen in daily speech)<br />
<strong>Swimming</strong> in the sea is fun.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this example, we have <strong>yüz-me-si</strong>, which adds the gerund and possessed
suffixes, respectively.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Object example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Denizde <strong>yüzmeyi</strong> seviyorum.<br />
Denizde <strong>yüzmesini</strong> seviyorum.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this example, we have <strong>yüz-me-si-n-i</strong>, which adds the gerund, possessed,
-n- possessed buffer, and accusative suffixes, respectively.</p>

<h2 id="siu-the-way-of">-ıs/iş/uş/üş: “the way of”</h2>

<p><strong>DISCLAIMER</strong>: “the way of” is not always the exact meaning of this suffix; it
can vary phrase by phrase. However, it can give a general idea.</p>

<ul>
  <li>yap<strong>ış</strong> (the way of doing)</li>
  <li>bak<strong>ış</strong> (the way of looking)</li>
  <li>sor<strong>uş</strong> (the way of asking)</li>
</ul>

<p>There are two words derived in this manner that are very common on signs: giriş
and cıkış (entrance and exit).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>Bana <strong>bakışını</strong> sevmiyorum. <br />
I don’t like the way you looked at me.</p>

  <p>Onun <strong>çıkışını</strong> gördün mü? <br />
Did you see how he left? / Did you see the way he left?</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="sfat-fiil-verbal-adjectives">Sıfat-fiil: Verbal adjectives</h1>

<h2 id="yan-en-subject-participles">-(y)an/-en: Subject participles</h2>
<p>In English, you’ll see this grammar concept associated with the terms relative
clause and participle.</p>

<p>We use these to form a verbal adjective that describes a noun.
It is called the subject participle because the described noun is the subject
performing the action.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>evime gel<strong>en</strong> misafir<br />
the guest <strong>who comes / is coming / came</strong> to my house</p>

  <p>uyu<strong>yan</strong> adam <br />
the man <strong>who sleeps / is sleeping / slept</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="negation">Negation</h3>

<p>Negation works as one might expect.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>uyu<strong>mayan</strong> adam<br />
the man <strong>who is not sleeping</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: In practice, the -y- buffer will always be there since <strong>-ma/me</strong> end
with a vowel.</p>

<h3 id="tense">Tense</h3>
<p>The tense is implied by context. It can take the present continuous, simple
past, and simple present (aka wide present) tenses.</p>

<h2 id="dik-and-possessor-suffix-object-participles">-dIk and possessor suffix: Object participles</h2>

<p>Recall that <strong>-dIk notation</strong> indicates it could be <strong>-dık -dik -duk -dük</strong>. The
d also mutates to t when appropriate (consonant mutation).</p>

<p>This adjective is called the object participle, because the noun described by
the verbal adjective is the object of the verb. Because of this, we also need to
specify who is performing the action of the verb; this is done by the possessor
ending.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong>  </p>

  <p>oku<strong>duğum</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that I read / am reading / read (in the past)</strong></p>

  <p>oku<strong>duğun</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that you read (…same tenses)</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: In practice, the <strong>k</strong> in <strong>-dIk</strong> always mutates to a <strong>ğ</strong> since all
of the possessor endings start with a vowel.</p>

<h3 id="negation-1">Negation</h3>
<p>Negation again works as one would expect.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>bak<strong>madığım</strong> adam<br />
the man <strong>who I am not looking at</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="tense-1">Tense</h3>
<p>The tense is implied by context. It can take the present continuous, simple
past, and simple present (aka wide present) tenses.</p>

<h3 id="usage-with-sonra">Usage with sonra</h3>

<p>You will also see this suffix used with the word sonra (“after”), but without the
possessed ending.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>O kahvaltı yap<strong>tıktan sonra</strong> bir sigara içer.<br />
After eating breakfast, he smokes a cigarette.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Notably, it is not symmetrically used with önce, which uses the <strong>-mAdAn</strong>
suffix with verbs with our previously described gerund form.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Uyu<strong>madan önce</strong> kitap okurum.<br />
Before sleeping, I read books.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="future-and-reported-past-participles">Future and reported past participles</h2>
<p>Building upon the two forms we learned above, we can create both object and
subject participles using the suffixes of both the future and reported past tenses. These tenses
won’t be covered here, so this section can be skipped if the reader is not
familiar with them.</p>

<p>Understanding of these derivations follow easily with an understanding of the
<strong>-acak/ecek</strong> future suffixes and the <strong>-mış/miş/muş/müş</strong> reported past
suffixes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (future tense)</strong>  </p>

  <p>konuşacak adam<br />
the man who will speak</p>

  <p>konuşacağı adam<br />
the man he/she will talk to</p>

  <p>adam konuşacak<br />
the man will talk (normal future tense)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (reported past tense)</strong>  </p>

  <p>kitap <strong>okumuş</strong> çocuk<br />
the child <strong>who (apparently) read</strong> books</p>

  <p><strong>boşanmış</strong> kadın<br />
the woman <strong>who (apparently) was divorced</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="other-verbal-adjectives">Other verbal adjectives</h2>
<p>There are a bunch of other verbal adjectives, often with different meaning.
There’s a <a href="https://www.dilbilgisi.net/fiilimsi-konu-anlatimi/">Turkish page</a>
containing some of them here, but they’re less important and often vary in
meaning phrase-by-phrase.</p>

<h1 id="zarf-fiil-verbal-adverbs">Zarf-fiil: Verbal adverbs</h1>
<p>This is not intended to comprehensively cover all zarf-fiil, but it covers a
few of the most common ones.</p>

<h2 id="eliali-since">-eli/ali: Since</h2>
<p>This suffix means “since” in the sense of time passing (not “since” as in the word “because”, which can also be used in English).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Okuldan <strong>geleli</strong> beş saat oldu.<br />
It has been five hours <strong>since I came</strong> from the school.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="subject-of-the-since-clause">Subject of the since-clause</h3>
<p>The subject is optional, but it can be used to clarify the subject of the since-clause when it cannot be derived from context.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (with pronoun)</strong>  </p>

  <p><strong>Sen</strong> okuldan gel<strong>eli</strong> beş saat oldu.<br />
It has been five hours since <strong>you</strong> came from the school.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="madanmeden-before-with-nce--without">-madan/meden: before (with önce) / without</h2>

<h3 id="meaning-without">Meaning “without”</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Maske <strong>takmadan</strong> dışarı çıkmak yasaktır.<br />
It is forbidden to go out <strong>without wearing</strong> a mask.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="meaning-before">Meaning “before”</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Ben polisi aramadan buradan ayrıl.<br />
Leave this place before I call the police.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="with-nce">With önce</h4>
<p>In the section on -dIk, it was explained that “sonra verb + dIktAn” could be used to say something that happened after an action. The -madan/meden suffix serves is often seen with <em>önce</em>. With or without önce is essentially the same (to my understanding).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Çalışmaya başla<strong>madan önce</strong> bir kahve içerim.<br />
Before studying, I drink a coffee.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="madan-meden-modifying-a-negative-verb">-madan/-meden modifying a negative verb</h4>
<p>There is a second construction using -madan/-meden. In this one, if the modified verb is negative, then the adverb happens first in the sequence of events. This is a bit confusing to explain but easily clarified with equivalent examples. Note the negative suffix in the verbs below.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Kitap <strong>okumadan</strong> yat<strong>ma</strong>dı.<br />
Kitap okudu ve yattı. (equivalent)<br />
I read a book before I slept.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A direct English translation can be a bit weird due to the negatives.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Question example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Siz ne <strong>yapmadan</strong> okula gitmiyorsunuz?<br />
What do you <strong>do before</strong> going to school?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The example could literally be translated as, “you don’t go to school before
doing what?”</p>

<p><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=V_bC-hn7cC8">This video</a> (in Turkish, albeit slow
Turkish) is a good explanation of this negative construction. Credit goes to
this video for the examples above.</p>

<h2 id="ar--maz---er--mez-as-soon-as">-ar -maz / -er -mez: as soon as</h2>
<p>Note that the title isn’t precisely correct, the set of suffixes is the same as
those used in the simple present tense, which has a ruleset not within the scope
of this article. One can think of this construction as simply the positive and
negative simple present tense third person forms in succession.</p>

<p>Like -eli/ali, the subject is implied by context, but can optionally be
clarified by a pronoun.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>(Biz) <strong>Dışarıya çıkar çıkmaz</strong> yağmur başladı.<br />
<strong>As soon as we went out,</strong> it started to rain.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example constructions</strong>  </p>

  <p>yapar yapmaz<br />
gelir gelmez<br />
görür görmez</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="yarakerek-by">-(y)arak/erek: “by”</h2>
<p>This adverb indicates that something was achieved in a certain manner.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Türkçe <strong>öğrenerek</strong> ne yapmayı planlıyorsun?<br />
What do you plan to do <strong>by learning</strong> Turkish?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A good way to remember this is the word <strong>bilerek</strong>, which means “on purpose.”
But with the literal translation of the suffix, it would mean “by knowing.”</p>

<h2 id="negation-2">Negation</h2>
<p>Simply add -ma/-me with a y buffer. For example, <strong>istemeyerek</strong>
(unintentionally, reluctantly, “by not wanting”).</p>

<h2 id="pipupp-two-actions-in-succession">-ıp/ip/up/üp: two actions in succession</h2>
<p>Again, notice that the subject is implied in the example sentence below. The
suffixed verb is the one that occurs first.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Konuyu <strong>anlatıp pratik</strong> yapacağız.<br />
We will explain the subject and then do practice.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Usually, there is only one usage of -ip in a sentence.</p>

<h3 id="ip-durmak-idiom">-ip durmak: idiom</h3>
<p><strong>-ip durmak</strong> means to keep doing something all the time.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong>  </p>

  <p>Öksürüp duruyor.<br />
He’s constantly coughing.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="difference-from-sonradan">Difference from sonradan</h3>
<p>Sonradan (“afterwards”) can ostensibly express the same set of sentences, but
the connotation is slightly different. With -ip, the implication is that one
thing happened very quickly after another, while with sonradan, the time gap
could be wider.</p>

<h2 id="further-reference">Further reference</h2>
<p>The end of Unit 10 in <em>The Delights of Learning Turkish</em> is a decent English
language resource for these verbal adverbs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sim Card Price in Turkey in February 2020]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Getting a SIM card in Turkey for short to medium term stays in Turkey is
straightforward. In this article, I describe my experience with prices in
<em>February 2020</em> using Turkcell.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I bought my SIM card in Fatih. I’m actually not sure if what I got was a good
deal. Turkcell offers all types of short-term deals for tourists as well. I
visited three stores in Fatih and they all gave me approximately the same rate
(some trying to squeeze +/- 10 lira) without the option for any smaller plans.</p>

<p>These rates are for foreigners. You’ll see advertisements for cellphone data at
amazing prices, but these require a Turkish bank account.</p>

<h2 id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>My plan was <strong>20 GB data for 120 lira</strong> (around 20 USD at the time of writing). However,
it should be noted that the 20 GB is <strong>for one month only</strong>.</p>

<p>Although the SIM card lasts for multiple months, you do need to top up in future
months. The top-up is at a rate rate that I don’t remember, but it’s much
cheaper than the initial upfront cost.</p>

<p>I didn’t really keep track of the SMS and call time in the plan, though that’s
included. It’s 2020, use WhatsApp :)</p>

<h3 id="long-term-stays">Long-term stays</h3>
<p>It should be noted that the SIM card situation for long-term stays (more than
120 days) gets much more expensive. You have to pay a foreigner registration fee
that’s more than 200 USD. I won’t go much into it here, but you can read about
it <a href="https://toomanyadapters.com/buying-sim-card-turkey/">on this page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="purchasing">Purchasing</h2>
<p>Bring your passport. It took about ten to fifteen minutes for the guy to finish
registering everything.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sahibinden: The Craigslist of Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Sahibinden</strong> (literally, “owners”) is the Craigslist equivalent of Turkey.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="usage">Usage</h2>

<p>In order to respond to listings (at least housing listings, in my experience),
you do need access to a Turkish cellphone number. The site will ask you to enter
a verification code that is texted to the Turkish number before you can respond.</p>

<h2 id="housing">Housing</h2>
<p>Sahibinden’s housing search is top-notch. In addition to the filters that one
would expect such as flat type and price, it also allows filtering by
furnished/unfurnished, renting from owner/broker, building age.</p>

<p><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/sahibinden/example.png" alt="Example map search" /></p>

<p>On a separate topic, finding housing in Istanbul has a number of options. I’d
recommend reading <a href="https://yabangee.com/finding-a-flat-in-istanbul-a-basic-guide-to-accommodation/">this article</a>, particularly on the difference between renting
from a broker and an owner. </p>

<p>Note: I do dispute one part of this article. They say that renting through an
owner usually has higher quality furnishing. At least in Sisli, my experience
was the opposite: broker flats tended to be newer and have better
furnishing. Most importantly, there were way more broker listings than owner
listings, which meant that the options were “better” for my specific needs based
purely on a higher volume of selection.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-shady-housing-deals">Avoiding shady housing deals</h3>
<p>Like Craigslist, Sahibinden actually includes a warning about housing scams,
though it’s in Turkish. This notification is mostly common sense: don’t wire
money to anyone you haven’t actually met.</p>

<p>I also found that some ads seemed to reuse pictures from other ads (e.g., two
flats in different locations with the exact same pictures and different owners).
Usually, one of them (I believe) is a scam. Longer-term accounts have a
small award image for how long they’ve been on Sahibinden (e.g., 11 years); the
shady ones had no such image. I’m not saying all accounts without the award are
scams, but if you run into two ads with the same pictures, the legitimate one is
probably the certified one.</p>

<p>My friend that lives in Istanbul also told me a few other things to watch out
for when using Sahibinden for housing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Renting daily flats through Sahibinden is difficult (even short- to
medium- term can be a bit of a hassle, as many owners want stable tenants.
However, when renting from a broker, they do like short-term tenants because
they usually charge the full broker fee of one month’s rent).</li>
  <li>Posters will often post really nice looking pictures but the apartment
actually looks a lot worse in person.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best ATM (No-Fee) in Istanbul, Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The best ATM in Istanbul, Turkey is a coveted title. There’s a lot of banks that
accept international cards, but some of them will try to extract more money from
you via service fee or dynamic currency conversion (DCC).</p>

<p>The best ATM is <strong>QNB</strong>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-best-atm-qnb">The Best ATM: QNB</h2>
<p>The best ATM is by far QNB. It has no extra fees and serves 100 TL bills. In my
case, I needed to withdraw a lot of money to pay for a housing deposit, so small
bills weren’t an option.</p>

<p>The particular QNB ATM I used did not have English, so when the DCC menu comes
up, make sure to click <strong>Istemiyorum</strong> (it was on the left side), which means:
“I do not want.” Make sure you say no to DCC. DCC is very bad (Google it).</p>

<p>See the table below for a relative comparison.</p>

<h2 id="atm-comparisons">ATM Comparisons</h2>
<p>Credit for this table goes to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Turkey/comments/cute4k/a_guide_to_turkish_atms_if_you_are_using_a_card/">some anonymous user on
Reddit</a>, who I’m actually,
very truly grateful for taking the time to write and do this exploration. As of
February 2020, I can verify that at least some of these were true, as I tried
about five ATMs in central Sisli.</p>

<p>If you have any updates or additions to this table, please add them below.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bank</th>
      <th>Non-DCC Fee</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>QNB Finansbank</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HSBC</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 20 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>AKBANK</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 20 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HalkBank</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 5 TL/10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ZiraatBanksi</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>VakifBank</td>
      <td>Flat 10 lira fee</td>
      <td>I went to one and it was 4%.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Garanti</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Bankamatik</td>
      <td>2.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>YapiKredi</td>
      <td>3%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Denizbank</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="fees-on-the-card-side">Fees on the card side</h2>
<p>This is not really an advertisement, since I don’t really make money
from this blog.</p>

<p>In addition to the fees charged by the owning bank of the ATM, the owning bank
of the card might also have foreign transaction fees. I use Charles Schwab (for
my god-bless USA of bank account), which has no fees. It also waives ATM fees,
but I’ve actually never been sure if that works for international bank fees such as
the ones above.</p>

<p>If for whatever reason this inspires you to sign up for Schwab, I have <a href="http://www.schwab.com/public/schwab/nn/refer-prospect.html?refrid=REFERY23JXD3D">this
referral
link</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Couchsurfing Safe? (and other common questions)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-24T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://couchsurfing.com">Couchsurfing</a> is a site that connects travelers to local hosts in a city.
As long as both the traveler and host agree, the traveler stays with the host free of charge. 
Although the traveler stays for free, experienced couchsurfers don’t view the site as a way to find
free lodging but instead as an opportunity to spend time with a local.</p>

<p>I usually try to Couchsurf when I travel, though it’s not always possible depending on the popularity of the destination. At the time of writing, I’ve stayed with about ten hosts through my travels.</p>

<p>This post is targeted towards people who are curious about using Couchsurfing as a guest but unsure
what to expect from the experience.</p>

<!-- more -->

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S).
Subscribe! -->

<h2 id="is-couchsurfing-safe">Is Couchsurfing safe?</h2>
<p>The most common question is: is Couchsurfing safe?</p>

<p>The answer is yes, but use caution. You’re signing up to stay in a stranger’s home, so you
definitely want to research your host beforehand. A well-reviewed host is a pretty safe bet.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing works on a reference system; both hosts and guests provide references after the
exchange. Personally, I only look for hosts that have a decent number of references (five or more).
By definition, this also increases the chances that they’re willing to accept guests.</p>

<p>However, navigating references can be tricky. Even if a guest had a slightly bad experience,
negative references are rare; guests don’t want to receive a negative reference in return.
This has two implications.</p>

<p>First, even a single negative
reference, for both a host or a guest, is considered a major red flag – something very egregious
must have happened. Second, finding out whether a
host is problematic requires carefully reading reviews. Since guests may tiptoe around directly
negative feedback, it’s important to analyze for any hints of negativity dispersed among
compliments (e.g., host was too controlling, didn’t show up, etc.).</p>

<p>As an unfortunate reality of the world, Couchsurfing can be more difficult for females.  Many
articles describe unwanted solicitation from hosts. My recommendation is to prefer female
couchsurfing hosts, although those are harder to find. Otherwise, carefully read other females’
reviews for a particular host.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do-with-your-hosts">What do you do with your hosts?</h2>
<p>There’s no definitive answer - it completely depends on your host.</p>

<p>Different hosts have different personalities, schedules, budgets, and so on. All of them will talk
to you, but not all will actually hang out. Your host is <em>not</em> obligated to be your tour guide.</p>

<p>A non-exhaustive spectrum of hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hosts that don’t hang out outside of home, often because they host couchsurfers non-stop and
can’t afford time-wise to show every guest around the city</li>
  <li>Hosts that work during the day and want to get dinner in the evening</li>
  <li>Hosts that will spend a whole day to take you somewhere or show you around</li>
</ul>

<p>To illustrate this concretely, here are things I’ve done in the past with my hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hiked at a national park and got stuck (Taiwan)</li>
  <li>Walked around for an hour and had a beer (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Went to a Noel Gallagher concert (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Talked for a few hours, staying only one night (Petah Tiqva)</li>
  <li>Cooked dinner (Venice)</li>
  <li>Ate ramen at home (Seoul)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-are-the-accommodations">What are the accommodations?</h2>
<p>Similarly, your accommodations vary depending on host.</p>

<p>Hosts will be very annoyed if you treat Couchsurfing like a hostel or hotel. Be considerate, clean
up after yourself, and so on: they’re not obligated to provide any services. After all, they’re
letting you crash in their home <em>for free.</em> In this vein, most hosts do not give their guests a key,
rightfully not wanting a stranger to freely have access to their home.</p>

<p>A few examples of my past accommodations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A couch, many times</li>
  <li>Shared a bed with my host, twice (not in any sexual fashion)</li>
  <li>A private room with a bed in a penthouse apartment (super rare, obviously!)</li>
  <li>A guy who had 10+ couchsurfing guests in his apartment at any time with people sleeping
everywhere</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-can-i-do-to-find-a-host-to-stay-with">What can I do to find a host to stay with?</h2>
<p>Couchsurfing is a two-way street. The host needs to want you to stay with them, and you need to want
stay with the host. From their perspective, they’re inviting a stranger into their home, so you want
to present yourself as a respectful and considerate guest.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing hosts, especially in popular destinations, are often spammed with grammar-mangled,
copy-pasted requests. Your goal is to stand out from this crowd.</p>

<h3 id="write-a-personalized-well-constructed-message">Write a personalized, well-constructed message</h3>
<p>Writing a personalized message request will maximize your chances of finding a host. Hosts want to
know that you’re asking to stay with <em>them</em>, not just mass-spamming for a free stay.  In fact, many
hosts’ profiles will ask guests to include some “passphrase” statement to ensure that the requester
has actually read the profile.</p>

<p>When I write a request, I always start strong with a few sentences personalized to the host’s
profile, then I write a
short two or three sentence copy-paste about my visit in the city. If the host wants to find out
more about me, the rest is on my Couchsurfing profile.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of a message I sent that introduces me briefly, indicates that I read their
profile, and states that I’m flexible about hanging out. The first paragraph is personalized (the
host’s profile mentions something about Latin dances); the second one is copy-pasted.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hey (host name),</p>

  <p>My name is Louis, I’m also in IT (I work in the USA as a programmer). I’m going to be in
Istanbul for a few days before I travel to Erbil to teach breakdancing, would you be willing to host
me for two nights? Unfortunately, I don’t know any Latin dances :(</p>

  <p>I’ve couchsurfed many times in the past, and I’m a very respectful and clean guest. I’m also down to
hang out or not depending on your schedule – these are weekday dates so I expect you might be
working. My schedule is very open to spend time together, except that I may be meeting up with other
dancers one of the nights.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="have-a-well-fleshed-out-profile">Have a well-fleshed out profile</h3>
<p>If you are trying to find a host for the first time, having a populated profile is crucial. Again,
from the perspective of the host, they can only base their opinion on what they see:
profile, messages, references. Although I’ve never hosted, I’ve been told by previous hosts of three
profile factors that often contribute to accepting requests:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>References</strong>: It’s chicken-and-egg, but it’s hard for hosts to host you if no one is vouching
for you. For those starting off, ask any friends who have Couchsurfed in the past to leave a
reference. Another option is to meet up with someone in the local Couchsurfing community and get
a reference.</li>
  <li><strong>“Proof of existence”:</strong> My profile contains a link to this site and my YouTube channel. I’ve had
multiple hosts tell me that simply poking around these links made me more trustworthy.</li>
  <li><strong>Couchsurfing verification:</strong> Couchsurfing has an option to upload and verify your identity for a
fee. One of my previous hosts said that they have a strong preference for verified
profiles. I’ve never done verification, but it helps a lot if your profile is just starting off.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="should-i-bring-a-gift">Should I bring a gift?</h2>
<p>Gifting is universal across cultures, and I recommend bringing or buying a gift for your host
– even something small like candy. It’s the thought that counts.</p>

<h2 id="concluding-thoughts">Concluding thoughts</h2>
<p>Overall, I’ve had extremely positive experiences with Couchsurfing and would highly recommend
it to anyone. I’ve made countless great memories through Couchsurfing, but I’ve only had one “bad
experience,” where the host was very controlling. Even that was still fun overall.</p>

<p>In my mind, there are two minor downsides to Couchsurfing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Social requirement: during my travels, I sometimes just don’t feel like socializing.</li>
  <li>Less schedule flexibility to go “home.” Since most hosts don’t give you a key, you often have to
coordinate with your host. This is especially bad if you’re jetlagged, and you need to get
creative to find a place to sleep during the day.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m a semi-experienced Couchsurfing guest, but my experience is still a small sample of that of
more experienced individuals, such as the power hosts who have hosted over one hundred guests.</p>

<p>If you have any other questions about Couchsurfing, feel free to leave them in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Dharamshala Airport to McLeod Ganj]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/22/transportation-from-dharamshala-airport-to-mcleod-ganj/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-22T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/22/transportation-from-dharamshala-airport-to-mcleod-ganj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last updated: June 2018</em></p>

<p>This post describes what to expect when going from the Dharamshala Airport to MacLeod Ganj,
Dharamshala, India – the central tourist area of Dharamshala.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We took a taxi from the airport to McLeod Ganj for 800 rupees, though the exact price depends on the
location of your residence. Go to the prepaid taxi booth and talk to the booth. There will be a number of drivers and a clerk outside of the stand. The drivers may try to
circumvent you from speaking to the booth, ignore them temporarily and get the slip signed off. In
our case, we ended up getting a lower price confirmed by the booth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Agra to Delhi Airport]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/21/transportation-from-agra-to-delhi-airport/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/21/transportation-from-agra-to-delhi-airport</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last updated: June 2018</em></p>

<p>This post describes how to get from <a href="https://wikitravel.org/en/Agra">Agra, India</a>, to New Delhi,
India. It focuses on how to get to the airport in the same day, though all of the advice applies
more generally to getting from one city to the other.</p>

<p>While attending a wedding in Agra, I had to get from Agra to Delhi in the same day in order to catch
a 14:00 flight.  The distance from Agra to Delhi is quite large (3-5 hour drive depending on
traffic), so I did some research on the most economical methods of reaching the Delhi airport. This
is a summary of my research that will hopefully help other travelers evaluate their options.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="traditional-taxi-service">Traditional taxi service</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~4000 rupees</strong></p>

<p>It’s easy to get a bunch of conflicting prices here. Definitely don’t book through a hotel (hostel
will probably give you better price) as they will way overcharge you – hotels’ quoted prices 
were around 200 USD.</p>

<p>We used <a href="https://www.tripadvisor.in/Attraction_Review-g297683-d13188303-Reviews-D_K_Car_and_Driver_India-Agra_Agra_District_Uttar_Pradesh.html">D.K. Car and Driver India</a>, which was the first result on TripAdvisor at the time of our trip. I called him using the hotel phone, but he also responded to my Facebook messages in about an hour, which was advantageous since I was trying to book at 4 PM the day before. Everything went seamlessly, so I’m willing to stick in my endorsement for D.K. here.</p>

<p>We paid around 4000 rupees, which at the time of writing, was about 60 USD. The trip was four hours.</p>

<h2 id="savaari--clearcar--other-taxi-aggregator">Savaari / ClearCar / other taxi aggregator</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~2500 rupees</strong>. The sites don’t give an exact amount, but this is an estimation based on
their formulas for trips over 80km.</p>

<p>There are a number of taxi aggregators in India (Savaari, ClearCar, etc.) that do “outstation” (out of town) trips. These are essentially like Uber, except that you book the car in advance, and it shows up at the specified time. Savaari was suggested by a native Indian
acquaintance of mine, as he was using it to leave Agra after the wedding. </p>

<p>After doing some research of reviews, it
seems that these services aren’t fully reliable; many reviews contained instances of drivers being late,
cancelling the hour beforehand, intentionally taking longer routes, etc. While online reviews are
likely biased toward the bad instances, it does suggest that these services could be hit-or-miss
(although it must be “hit” enough that a native Indian suggested it to us).</p>

<p>Despite being the best balance of convenience and price, I ended up not going with this option due
to the potential time unreliability, especially for a 7AM flight. However, <strong>if you simply want to get from
Agra to Delhi as a group with looser time constraints, Savaari is both cheaper and more convenient
than public transportation.</strong></p>

<h2 id="public-transportation">Public transportation</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~1000 rupees / person.</strong> Air-conditioned class train tickets ranged from 700 to 1200 rupees.</p>

<p>Public transportation here means train, metro, and bus/short-distance cab.  For the trains, view
up-to-date timetables and book tickets at <a href="https://www.irctc.co.in/">IRCTC</a>. I’m not sure if they
take international cards; I’ve seen varying reports online.</p>

<p>In general, public transportation (train/metro) is a good option for Agra to Delhi. </p>

<p>For getting to the airport specifically, it becomes more complicated. We ran into a myriad of issues trying to plan a public transit route. The fastest 2.25 hour express trains from Agra to Delhi ran only in the evening, which didn’t work for our 14:00 flight, so the train would be least 3 hours. Additionally, the trains for our timetable only went to Hazrat Nizmuddin station, which would require either a bus/cab to the airport or airport metro line.</p>

<p>To summarize, the trip would involve:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Residence in Agra to Agra Cantt station (<strong>10-20 min</strong>)</li>
  <li>Agra Cantt to New Delhi Station or Hazrat Nizmuddin station (<strong>2.25 to 3.5 hours</strong>, depending on what
train you catch)</li>
  <li>If at New Delhi Station, metro to airport. If at Hazrat Nizmuddin station, figure out a way to get
to the airport metro, then head to airport (either way, <strong>30 min to 1 hour</strong>, and traffic is bad).</li>
</ul>

<p>If you have an evening flight, then public transportation to the airport is a viable
option, as you have more time flexibility without waking up at an ungodly hour. If traveling solo,
this is the cheapest option by far, but if your group
has two or more people and you have time flexibility, a Savaari cab becomes about the same
price per person.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dubrovnik Bus Departure Schedule (Croatia)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-bus-departure-schedule/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-02T21:15:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-bus-departure-schedule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains the bus schedule for departures from Dubrovonik, Croatia. Dubrovonik is a
popular coastal destination (and the filming site of King’s Landing for the <em>Game of Thrones</em> TV
show!). </p>

<p><em>Last updated: 1 September 2015</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Timetables may differ between on and off seasons. My trip was at the beginning of September, which is on
the border of on and off seasons.</p>

<h2 id="timetable">Timetable</h2>

<p>If you find an updated timetable during your travels, please send it to me to update this page for
other travelers.</p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/dubrovonikbus/timetable.jpg" alt="Bus timetable" /></p>

<h2 id="destinations">Destinations</h2>

<p><strong>International:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Sarajevo</li>
  <li>Medugorje</li>
  <li>Kotor</li>
  <li>Budva</li>
  <li>Trieste</li>
  <li>Herceg Novi</li>
  <li>Ulcinj</li>
  <li>Podgorica</li>
  <li>Zenica</li>
  <li>Mos</li>
  <li>Ivanica - Trebinje</li>
  <li>Skopje</li>
  <li>Ljubljana</li>
  <li>Petrovac</li>
  <li>Bar</li>
  <li>Tivat</li>
  <li>Frankfurt</li>
  <li>Tuzla</li>
  <li>Beograd (Belgrade)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Domestic:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Metkovic</li>
  <li>Ploce</li>
  <li>Orebic</li>
  <li>Korcula - Vela Luka</li>
  <li>Makarska</li>
  <li>Split</li>
  <li>Trogir</li>
  <li>Sibenik</li>
  <li>Zadar</li>
  <li>Rijeka</li>
  <li>Pula</li>
  <li>Karlovac</li>
  <li>Zagreb</li>
  <li>Osijek, Vinkovci, S. Brod</li>
  <li>Varazdin</li>
  <li>Vrgorac</li>
  <li>Otric-Seoci</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dubrovnik's Best Currency Exchange (Croatia)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-best-currency-exchange/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-02T21:15:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-best-currency-exchange</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains information about the best place to exchange currency in Dubrovnik, Croatia:
<strong>OK Travel Agency</strong>.</p>

<p>Dubrovnik is a popular coastal destination (and the filming site of King’s Landing for the <em>Game of Thrones</em> TV
show!). </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="directions">Directions</h2>

<p>The travel agency is located at <strong>Obala Stjepana Radića 32, Dubrovnik, Croatia</strong>. </p>

<p>It is very
convenient to reach when arriving in Dubrovonik by bus or boat, because it is located next to the main
port and central bus station. </p>

<p>It is further from Old Town, and you will take one of the buses to the central bus station or
port (most of them stop here), then walk to the agency. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/dubrovonikcurrency/oktravel.jpg" alt="Outside of OK Travel Agency" /></p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d5868.382096555248!2d18.08878992153864!3d42.65730670065322!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x134c7525b02fd643%3A0x9fe451262d4d1f78!2sObala+Stjepana+Radi%C4%87a+32%2C+20000%2C+Dubrovnik%2C+Croatia!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1441228112407" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="rates">Rates</h2>

<p>I received exchange rates from OK Travel Agency that were <strong>0.8% from
the midmarket rate</strong> (the rate from internet searches). There was <strong>no commission</strong>.</p>

<p>Rates change over time, but in September 2015, the midmarket rate was 7.55 kuna to the euro. I
received 7.49 kuna to the euro. <script type="math/tex">(1 - 7.49 / 7.55 = 0.079)</script></p>

<p><em>Last updated: 2 September 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Tirana to Ulcinj / Budva / Kotor]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/tirana-kotor/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-01T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/tirana-kotor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article describes directions from Tirana, Albania to Ulcinj / Budva / Kotor, Montenegro by bus,
based on my travels in August 2015. It is possible
to start early and arrive in Kotor by the afternoon, but be prepared to wake up early to ride four
buses. </p>

<p>I caught the
first bus at 7:00 and arrived in Kotor around 14:00. </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="leg-1-tirana-to-schkoder">Leg 1: Tirana to Schkoder</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> about 1.25 hrs to 1.75 hrs, depending on traffic</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> 500 lek (about €2)</p>

<p>See the <a href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania/">Tirana to Schkoder article</a>.</p>

<h2 id="leg-2-schkoder-to-ulcinj">Leg 2: Schkoder to Ulcinj</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> About 1.25 hours, depending on border control</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €5</p>

<p>The buses (vans) are near the fountain at the city center. Ask around for
Schkoder if nobody is shouting, or ask the driver from Tirana. I asked the driver from Tirana, who
showed me to the next van.
The driver leaves at 9:00, sitting at a cafe and chatting with his friends before then. </p>

<p>Ask the Schkoder-Ulcinj driver to drop you off at the bus stop. The rest is easy –
Montenegro has much more signage for its bus system than Albania does.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t forget to have your passport ready for border control!</strong></p>

<p>Below is the location of the buses in Schkoder.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2961.8742367571995!2d19.513413874485096!3d42.06731499235399!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x134e00fb86c50699%3A0xb04ce3e5ed35f40f!2sRruga+Teuta%2C+Shkod%C3%ABr%2C+Albania!5e0!3m2!1sen!2s!4v1441188846897" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="leg-3-ulcinj-to-budva">Leg 3: Ulcinj to Budva</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.25 hours</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €7</p>

<p>According to possibly-outdated information from the internet, there are only two buses direct from
Ulcinj to Kotor in a day. It may be possible to catch a bus directly to Kotor; otherwise, head to
Budva. </p>

<p>An alternative option is to go from Ulcinj to Bar, but buses from Bar to Kotor are less frequent. </p>

<p>I’m not sure about the precise schedule, but buses from Ulcinj to Budva should be fairly frequent. 
I arrived from Ulcinj five minutes before a bus was leaving for Budva.</p>

<h2 id="leg-4-budva-to-kotor">Leg 4: Budva to Kotor</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.25 hours</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €3</p>

<p>From Budva, buses leave to Kotor every thirty minutes.</p>

<h2 id="fare">Fare</h2>

<p>500 lek + €5 + €7 + €3 = <strong>€18</strong></p>

<p>This is much cheaper than the “direct transfer service” offered by Montenegro Hostel from Tirana to
Kotor (€35). </p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Tirana to Durres / Schkoder (Albania)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-31T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains bus directions based on my travels in Albania in August 2015. 
Durres is a coastal city around thirty minutes away, containing
ferries to Italy and beaches. </p>

<p>Schkoder is a historical city around 1.25 to 1.75 hours away,
depending on traffic. It is a northern border city with bus transfers to Ulcinj, Montenegro. </p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Confirm these
directions. Two years ago, the bus to Schkoder was at a different location, and some of the
directions that I found were outdated.</p>

<h2 id="directions-to-the-bus-stop">Directions to the bus stop</h2>

<p>The Google Maps diagram below shows the bus stop, which is in the roundabout of Karl Topia Square.
It shouldn’t be too hard to find the correct bus: each bus has a person shouting its destination.  </p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2995.868120776664!2d19.804230999999994!3d41.333481!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zNDHCsDIwJzAwLjUiTiAxOcKwNDgnMTUuMiJF!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1441137271939" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="bus">Bus</h2>

<p>The buses, known as <em>furgons</em>, are more akin to vans or cars. For an afternoon bus to Durres, I took
a van that fit approximately 15 people. For a 7 AM bus to Schkoder, the vehicle was someone’s
five-seat Volkswagen. Don’t be worried if it just seems like you’re getting in someone’s car (you
are).</p>

<p>The buses don’t leave until they are full or almost full. For Durres, this seems to be approximately
every thirty minutes. For Schkoder, this seems to be approximately every hour. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/tiranabus/bus.jpg" alt="Vans that will take you through beautiful Albania" /></p>

<h2 id="fare">Fare</h2>

<p>In August 2015, the fare for each direction was:</p>

<ul>
  <li>150 lek to Durres</li>
  <li>500 lek to Schkoder</li>
</ul>

<p>The drivers take euro. If you want to get rid of some remaining lek, they also take euro-lek mix.</p>

<p>Enjoy the Albanian music on the drive!</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation to Mount Dajti (Tirana, Albania)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/30/mt-dajt-tirana-albania/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-30T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/30/mt-dajt-tirana-albania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.tripadvisor.com/Attraction_Review-g294446-d606455-Reviews-Mount_Dajti-Tirana.html">Mount
Dajti</a> is a mountain near Tirana, the capital of Albania. It is a popular picnic
and hiking spot. This article includes directions and information from Tirana
city center to Mount Dajti.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="directions-to-the-cable-car-station">Directions to the cable car station</h2>
<p>The <a href="www.dajtiekspres.com/">Dajti Express</a> cable car is the preferred method of going up. The site does not say its hours of operation, but as of August 2015 it
operates from 9:00 - 22:00. </p>

<p>The cable car station is about 5 km from Skanderbeg Square, the city center. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/dajti/view.jpg" alt="View from the cable car, scratched glass and all" /></p>

<h3 id="by-public-bus">By public bus</h3>
<p>The bus waits outside the clock tower near Skanderbeg Square, dropping you off a short, uphill walk from the
cable car station. The bus should say Porcelani on it. It
costs about 100 lek. </p>

<h3 id="by-dajti-express-van">By Dajti Express van</h3>

<p>I couldn’t find information about this on the internet (I suspect nothing has been updated), but on my return trip, there was a <strong>free
van</strong> that
stopped directly at the cable car station at the base of the mountain. </p>

<p>The Google Maps link below shows where it dropped me off outside the cafes near Skanderbeg Square, which is likely where it picks up for a free trip to the cable car
station. If you don’t mind waiting, then you can wait there for a potential free trip by looking for
the van pictured below (and let me know if you’re successful!).  People in Tirana are also very
friendly, and it doesn’t hurt to ask around.</p>

<div style="text-align:center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2996.102796304338!2d19.818874999999995!3d41.328378!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zNDHCsDE5JzQyLjIiTiAxOcKwNDknMDguMCJF!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1440968571219" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/dajti/van.jpg" alt="The mystery van operated by Dajti Express" /></p>

<h3 id="by-foot-or-bike">By foot or bike</h3>
<p>Since the station is 5 km away from Skanderbeg, running or biking to the station are viable options.</p>

<p>There is some information on the internet about hiking trails from the base of the mountain to the
summit, but I’m not familiar with these routes.</p>

<h2 id="trail-map">Trail Map</h2>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/dajti/trails.jpg" alt="Trail map" /></p>

<p>I didn’t find this map very useful, and online reviews say that the trails are not well marked (I
had this impression as well, though I didn’t actually end up hiking – I crashed an Albanian Sunday
barbecue instead).</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Best Meat and Rice in Taipei: Barbecue Pork Rice 御狀元烤肉飯 (Taipei, Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/meat-and-rice-zhaopaikaoroufan/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/meat-and-rice-zhaopaikaoroufan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>御狀元烤肉飯 (<em>yu zhuang yuan kao rou fan</em>) (“Emperor’s Best Barbecue Pork and Rice” – not sure if
that’s the correct translation) is a meat and rice joint in Taipei near Taipei Main Station.</p>

<p>This was my favorite place to eat in Taiwan. I worked near Taipei Main Station and would eat here
three to four days a week – for lunch <em>and</em> dinner on some days. It’s extremely cheap and very
tasty for meat and rice (and egg and vegetable) lovers.</p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="signature-dish">Signature Dish</h2>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/zpkrf/signature.jpg" alt="Signature dish: barbecue pork rice (zhao pai kao rou fan)" /></p>

<p>For 79 NT (less than 3 USD), the barbecue pork rice contains:</p>

<ul>
  <li>rice</li>
  <li>fried egg</li>
  <li>garlic cabbage</li>
  <li>pickled vegetables</li>
  <li>barbecue pork</li>
  <li>yummy sauce</li>
</ul>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/zpkrf/with-chicken.jpg" alt="Barbecue pork rice with fried chicken" /></p>

<p>For an extra 6 NT (around 20 cents USD), they will add fried chicken cutlet.</p>

<h2 id="directions">Directions</h2>

<p>The closest subway exit is Taipei Main Station exit M6 (Caesar Park Hotel). The store is located on
Xuchang Street past the Paris Shop.</p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/zpkrf/signpost.jpg" alt="This sign hangs near the entrance" /></p>

<p>It may be helpful to see the <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/uceKr">Google Maps street view</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3614.6629865749737!2d121.51611240000001!3d25.045508700000003!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x3442a9731d0f5025%3A0x8ee7ca88ac8492f9!2sXuchang+St%2C+Zhongzheng+District%2C+Taipei+City%2C+Taiwan+100!5e0!3m2!1sen!2s!4v1440960795318" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="menu">Menu</h2>

<p class="minipic"><img src="http://louisrli.github.io/images/travel/zpkrf/menu.jpg" alt="Menu" /></p>

<h3 id="translation">Translation</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Frog rice (<em>pen shui ji rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Pickled vegetables chicken rice (<em>pao cai ji rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Soy sauce chicken leg rice (<em>jiang lu ji tui fan</em>) </li>
  <li>Ka la (cracking?) chicken cutlet rice (<em>ka la ji pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Osaka pork cutlet rice (<em>da ban zhu pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Thai chicken cutlet rice (<em>tai shi ji pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Thai pork cutlet rice (<em>tai shi zhu pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li><strong>Barbecue pork rice (signature dish)</strong> (<em>zhao pai kao rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Pickled vegetables barbecue pork rice (<em>pao cai kao rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Combo chicken and pork rice (<em>shuang pin kao rou fan</em>)</li>
</ol>

<p>I’ve only had the barbecue pork and the combo (but I’ve tried it many times).</p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yangmingshan Transportation 阳明山 (Taipei, Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/yangmingshan/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/yangmingshan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an English guide for transportation to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yangmingshan">Yangmingshan
(阳明山)</a>, a national park north of Taipei, Taiwan. 
Yangmingshan is a popular destination for locals and tourists, containing numerous hiking trails and
hot springs.</p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="travel-to-yangmingshan">Travel to Yangmingshan</h2>

<p>The easiest way to reach Yangmingshan is by taking the <strong>260 bus from Taipei Main Station</strong>
to the very last stop. <strong>The bus stops outside exit M1.</strong> The second-to-last stop also contains the phrase “Yangmingshan” – make
sure to get off at the final stop.</p>

<p>The 260 bus also runs along North Zhongshan Road (中山北路). It may be more convenient to find a 260
bus stop along this road rather than going to Taipei Main Station.</p>

<p><strong>The fare is about 30 NTD</strong>. If using an Easy Card, swipe the card when going both on and off the bus.</p>

<h2 id="travel-within-yangmingshan">Travel within Yangmingshan</h2>

<p>The internal 108 bus runs on stops within Yangmingshan. This small bus makes stops around the whole
park.</p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[English Guide to Sun Moon Lake 日月潭 (Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/sun-moon-lake/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-10T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/sun-moon-lake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a guide to transportation, food, activities, and lodging for a Sun Moon Lake trip, based on
my own experiences. My friend and I traveled from Taipei to Sun Moon Lake in July 2015, staying one
night by the lake. </p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="traveling-to-sun-moon-lake">Traveling to Sun Moon Lake</h2>

<h3 id="from-taichung">From Taichung</h3>

<p>We traveled from Taichung (台中), since we wanted to explore the city the night before.
Taipei to Taichung is one hour by high speed rail (HSR), two hours by train (TRA), four hours by
bus.</p>

<p>We purchased a package deal for Sun Moon Lake from Nantou Bus Company across from Gancheng station,
which is near the train station. Packages can also be purchased from the Taichung HSR station.</p>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.ntbus.com.tw/en-p-1.html">many options for packages</a>, but the 570 NT package
includes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Round trip bus tickets between Taichung and Sun Moon Lake (383 NT)</li>
  <li>Ferry rides for one day (200 NT)</li>
  <li>Bike rental for two hours from Merida Bikes or one hour from GIANT (200 NT)</li>
  <li>Round trip bus tickets between Shuishe and Xiangshan, two stops at Sun Moon Lake (48 NT)</li>
</ul>

<p>According to my computationally intense calculations, this <strong>saves you 261 NT.</strong> It’s a good deal.</p>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.5 hours<br />
<strong>Price:</strong> 570 NT for package deal (see <a href="http://www.ntbus.com.tw/en-p-1.html">Nantou site</a> for other
options)<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Across from Gancheng station (sells packages), Taichung HSR station (sells packages),
or Taichung TRA station. It stops at Shuishe Pier, the main hub of Sun Moon Lake.  </p>

<h2 id="from-taipei">From Taipei</h2>
<p>I didn’t travel from Taipei, but the <a href="http://www.sunmoonlake.gov.tw/English/TravelInfoEng/BusInfo/TaipeiToSML.htm">King Bus
timetable</a> lists bus
times from Taipei Main Station.  </p>

<p><strong>Type:</strong> Bus<br />
<strong>Duration:</strong> 4 hours<br />
<strong>Price:</strong> 460 NT each way<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Taipei Bus Station</p>

<p>Miscellaneous: We stayed at a nice and cheap hotel in Taichung, the <a href="https://www.kayak.com/Taichung-Hotels-Moon-Lake-Hotel.2070096.ksp">Moon Lake
Hotel</a> (11 USD per
night). It is less than a kilometer away from the train station.</p>

<p><strong>Type:</strong> Bus  </p>

<h2 id="getting-around">Getting Around</h2>

<h3 id="ferry">Ferry</h3>

<p>The ferry is the most convenient way to cover a lot of ground and hit the main destinations. It has three stops, forming a triangle along the lake. </p>

<ul>
  <li>The first pier is <strong>Shuishe</strong>, the main pier. </li>
  <li>The second pier is <strong>Xuanzang Pier</strong>, and it has a legendary tea egg store that has been run by the same
woman for about fifty years (13 NT per egg). </li>
  <li>The last pier is <strong>Ita Thao</strong>, which has many food stands.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="bike">Bike</h3>

<p>Biking is a scenic way to get around the lake. Details on bike shops can be found
<a href="http://www.sunmoonlake.gov.tw/English/TravelInfoEng/LakeTour/BikeRental.htm">here</a>. See the <strong>Activities</strong> section for more information
about the bikes in the package deal.</p>

<h3 id="bus">Bus</h3>

<p>The Round-the-Lake bus, which goes ‘round the lake, is the main bus. A trip on the bus is more or less 20 NT. An unlimited trip ticket is 80 NT. You can use your EasyCard.</p>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> Wave down the bus drivers as they approach, because they probably won’t stop for you
otherwise.</p>

<h2 id="things-to-try">Things To Try</h2>

<h3 id="food">Food</h3>

<p>Ita Thao has all the good food. Edibles to try:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Pork buns (Ita Thao):</strong> I recommend the stand that has pumpkin pork buns.</li>
  <li><strong>Assam tea (Ita Thao):</strong> Stands advertising Assam tea are everywhere. It’s a type of tea imported
  from India or Japan. It tastes like tea. For some reason (I don’t know because I’m Chinese
  illiterate), it’s famous in the area.</li>
  <li><strong>Chicken stuffed with rice (Ita Thao):</strong> I have no idea what this is called. Look for a stand with deer horns.
  Also, if you don’t like spicy, ask for “no spicy” because even “small spicy” was super spicy.</li>
  <li><strong>Old woman tea eggs (Xuanguan Pier):</strong> These were mentioned above. They’re at the first ferry stop after Shuishe.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="places">Places</h3>

<p>There are many destinations at Sun Moon Lake, but I recommend:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ci’en Pagoda</strong>, a tall building commissioned by Chiang-Kai Shek, has a sweeping view of the lake. 
Sun Moon Lake has hiking trails, but many of them don’t have a nice view of the lake. 
To reach the pagoda, take the round-the-lake bus. Although Ci’en Pagoda is not listed as a stop, it <strong>is</strong>
the second-to-last stop before (I think) Xuanzang Temple. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ita Thao</strong>, an area with many food stands. Because food.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> The bus does not stop at Ci’en Pagoda between 1 and 3 PM, and none of the main
piers are within short walking distance (around 5 km). We tried leaving at 1:30 PM.  Not wanting to
wait around for 1.5 hours, we hitchhiked our way back.</p>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> Bug your bus driver to stop. Our bus driver was not-too-nice and chose not to stop Ci’en
Pagoda– despite knowing that it was
our destination. You might notice a pattern here involving interactions with bus drivers.</p>

<h3 id="activities">Activities</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Walking</strong>: Self explanatory.</li>
  <li><strong>Biking</strong>: The best activity by far. The package that we did gave us bikes for two hours from Merida Bike, which was enough time to bike
about a third of the lake (going out and coming back to the bike rental shop). Renting bikes for
longer (i.e., to go around the whole lake) costs more, but I’m unsure how much more. Bike shops want bikes back by around 6:30 PM.</li>
  <li><strong>Cable car:</strong> It exists, but I didn’t do it.</li>
  <li><strong>Being ignored by bus drivers:</strong> It exists, and I did do it.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h3>

<p>None of these were that interesting to us, but if you have more time, this is an incomplete list of
other activities in the area:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Aboriginal Culture Village (<a href="http://www.nine.com.tw/webe/html/information/">link</a>):</strong> This sounds like a village for cultural edification, but it turns
  out it’s actually an amusement park.</li>
  <li><strong>Puli:</strong> It’s a town.</li>
  <li><strong>Cingjing Farm (<a href="http://www.cingjing.gov.tw/en/about/">link</a>):</strong> It’s a farm. It’s about 40 minutes from Sun Moon Lake.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lodging">Lodging</h2>

<p>Because Sun Moon Lake is a popular tourist destination, lodging is relatively expensive. </p>

<p>Super secret hacker budget stay: <strong>Naluisland House</strong>. This place is so secret that it doesn’t show up
on <a href="http://kayak.com">Kayak</a> or have reviews on
<a href="http://www.tripadvisor.com/Hotel_Review-g304160-d6453391-Reviews-Naluisland_House-Nantou.html">TripAdvisor</a>. 
You can book through Agoda or Ctrip.</p>

<p>We shared a room with two queen sized beds between four people, and it came out to about <strong>450 NT
per person</strong> (15
USD in July 2015). Our room was sufficient for a one night stay. There are rooms with four beds for
a little more. Some rooms also have private bathrooms, which costs a little more as well. </p>

<p>To get to Naluisland House, take the ferry or bus to Ita Thao, which is one of the major destinations of Sun Moon
Lake. However, buses and ferries close around 5:30 PM – be very careful to get to Ita Thao before
then. We learned that a taxi from Shuishe, the main port, costs about 500 NT (try negotiating).</p>

<p>I’m not sure if the owner speaks English, but she was very helpful. </p>

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<p><em>Last updated: July 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Senior Thesis: Security Analysis of Java Web Applications Using String Constraint Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/05/03/senior-thesis/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-03T00:00:00+03:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/05/03/senior-thesis</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I submitted my undergraduate thesis at the beginning of April, titled “Security Analysis of Java Web
Applications Using String Constraint Analysis.” I was advised by Professor Stephen Chong.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Here’s the abstract:</p>

<blockquote>

  <p>Web applications are exposed to myriad security vulnerabilities related to malicious user string
input. In order to detect such vulnerabilities in Java web applications, this project employs string
constraint analysis, which approximates the values that a string variable in a program can take on.
In string constraint analysis, program analysis generates string constraints – assertions about the
relationships between string variables. We design and implement a dataflow analysis for Java
programs that generates string constraints and passes those constraints to the CVC4 SMT solver to
find a satisfying assignment of string variables. Using example programs, we illustrate the
feasibility of the system in detecting certain types of web application vulnerabilities, such as SQL
injection and cross-site scripting.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://louisrli.github.io/downloads/louisli-thesis.pdf">Download the PDF</a> or view it below. </p>

<embed src="http://louisrli.github.io/downloads/louisli-thesis.pdf" type="application/pdf" width="100%" height="600" />

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Being a Better Teaching Assistant: Five Concrete Tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/five-tips-for-being-an-effective-teaching-fellow/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-27T23:13:28-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/01/27/five-tips-for-being-an-effective-teaching-fellow</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The purpose of this post is to provide concrete pointers to becoming a better undergraduate teaching
fellow (Harvard lingo for student instructor, course assistant, etc.). </p>

<p>Being an undergraduate instructor can be tricky. First, the students are the same age as you. Second, it can be hard to know how to improve. In my experience as both a student writing feedback and an instructor receiving feedback, students usually won’t write more than two sentences of feedback. </p>

<p>The word “teaching” usually evokes an image of an instructor at a whiteboard. While effective
communication skills are important, the environment and perceptions that an instructor
fosters among students is equally important. For that reason, I’m choosing to focus on aspects outside of
teaching classroom material. </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>

<p>I’m still an undergraduate with a fraction of the teaching experience of a
professor – but the advantage of youth is that I can still remember the most basic and glaring
mistakes that student instructors make. </p>

<p>These tips are derived from three sources:</p>

<ol>
  <li>My own mistakes as a teaching fellow</li>
  <li>My own experience as a student</li>
  <li>My observations of other student instructors</li>
</ol>

<h1 id="explicitly-emphasize-your-accessibility">1. Explicitly emphasize your accessibility.</h1>
<p><strong>Concrete action</strong>: At the beginning of every section (or every section for the first half of the
semester), tell the students to email you any questions that they have about the course or problem
sets – no matter how trivial.</p>

<p><strong>Phrasing is important.</strong> As an instructor, I particularly emphasized my willingness to look at the
rigor of proofs,
a common concern in introductory mathematics courses – telling students that I would avoid saying
whether their answer was correct but would instead give feedback on the rigor of their proofs.</p>

<p>Consider the result of being passively open to questions. In the back of their heads, students
know that they <em>can</em> approach you for questions, but they may be worried about looking “dumb” or
coming off as annoying. Explicitly emphasizing your accessibility fosters an environment that allows
you to help struggling students.</p>

<h1 id="avoid-saying-that-things-are-easy">2. Avoid saying that things are easy.</h1>
<p><strong>Concrete action</strong>: Try to catch yourself before using any of these phrases or their variants:
“this problem is easy”, “this problem is really simple”, “this is not too hard”, etc.</p>

<p>Here’s a real story (identifying details omitted). A student in a course (that I was teaching) told
me that another instructor thought that the course was easy when the
instructor, who had a strong mathematics background, had taken it. The student, who was struggling
in the course, was clearly bothered by this.</p>

<p>Ultimately, telling a student that the course was “supposed to be” easy
achieved nothing positive. It only served to foster the student’s apprehension about the course.</p>

<p>Many people would find it obvious that an instructor shouldn’t tell a struggling student that a task
is easy. However, note that it’s also a bad <em>preface</em> to an example problem – before anybody
mentions confusion. Deeming the problem “easy” beforehand will make potentially confused
students feel worse.</p>

<h1 id="admit-when-you-dont-know-the-answer----then-find-it">3. Admit when you don’t know the answer – then find it.</h1>
<p><strong>Concrete action</strong>: If a student puts you on the spot with a question, and you can’t figure out the
answer, admit it, but <em>make sure</em> to follow up with the student later.</p>

<p>An appropriate response – one I’ve used many times – is along the lines of: “I’m sorry, I don’t
know off the top of my head. I’ll find out and send you an email.” (Of course, you should always first <em>try</em> to answer the question) </p>

<p>Most of the time, the student doesn’t urgently need the answer. As much as it might ring the ego,
it’s better to send the student a well thought-out answer than stalling (wasting everyone’s time) or
giving a copout answer (hurting the student’s learning). </p>

<h1 id="dont-rely-on-the-solutions-key">4. Don’t rely on the solutions key.</h1>
<p><strong>Concrete action</strong>: Fully solve any solution that you’re responsible for explaining
(example problem in section, homework problem, etc.). </p>

<p>In my experience, failing to do this will, with nontrivial probability, result in trying to parse
the solutions under high pressure. <strong>Having the solutions key is not the same as having the
ability to explain the steps of a solution</strong> (I know of a few other instructors that were capable of
procuring explanations quickly – I am not one of them). Working through the solutions beforehand
ensures that you can maximize your helpfulness to students.</p>

<h1 id="follow-the-course-materials-with-the-students">5. Follow the course materials with the students.</h1>
<p><strong>Concrete action</strong>: Read any potential source of questions – textbook
chapters, slides, notes – in step with the timeline of the course.</p>

<p>Familiarize yourself with the students’ readings. Even if you know the course concepts, students often have fairly specific
questions about certain examples in the readings. The ideal response is to explain
an example after rereading it once, having already reviewed the students’
readings. </p>

<p>The wrong response to a question – which, I guiltily admit, has happened to me on occasion –
is to ask the student to wait, spending substantially longer to read, parse, and understand the
example in question. </p>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>
<p>A good way to improve as an instructor is to consider the qualities that you appreciate in
instructors (or more saliently, the qualities that you dislike).</p>

<p>If you haven’t considered teaching as an undergraduate, I strongly encourage you to think about it. Teaching as an
undergrad is a unique (and sometimes
<a href="http://harvardpolitics.com/harvard/harvard-undergraduates-teaching-harvard-doesnt-want-talk/">controversial</a>)
opportunity.</p>

<p><em>Thank you to Ruth Fong for contributing to this article.</em></p>

<p><em>Thank you to Paul Bamberg, Stephen Chong, Harry Lewis, Emily Riehl, and Salil Vadhan for providing me valuable
opportunities to teach during my college years. I am especially indebted to Paul for propelling me into
teaching as an undergraduate.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Topological Proof of Bolzano-Weierstrass Without Constructing Sequences]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/bolzano-weierstrass-without-sequences/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-07T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/11/07/bolzano-weierstrass-without-sequences</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bolzano%E2%80%93Weierstrass_theorem">Bolzano-Weierstrass theorem</a>
is a common theorem taught in introductory real analysis and topology courses. </p>

<p>All of the proofs that I’ve read for the Bolzano-Weierstrass theorem involve constructing sequences.
In my introductory topology course, I wanted to see if I could write a simple proof of the theorem
<em>without</em> having to explicitly construct any sequences.</p>

<p>(It’s worth noting that the proof for compact <script type="math/tex">\implies</script> sequentially compact requires constructing
sequences. If we take this as given, then we get to avoid sequences.)</p>

<h2 id="theorem-bolzano-weierstrass">Theorem (Bolzano-Weierstrass)</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>Any bounded sequence in <script type="math/tex">\mathbb{R}^n</script> has a convergent subsequence.</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="proof">Proof</h2>

<p>We will make use of the following propositions, which I will assume to be previously proved. The
proofs of these are in a standard topology textbook (I’m reading from Munkres, 2nd edition). </p>

<p>I’ll redefine various notions of compactness below, since there exists some ambiguity in the
different forms of compactness.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Definition.</strong> A topological space is <strong>sequentially compact</strong> if every
infinite sequence has a convergent subsequence.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Proposition 1.</strong> The interval <script type="math/tex"> [a, b] \subset \mathbb{R} </script> is compact.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Proposition 2.</strong> The product of compact spaces is compact.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In fact, this proposition true in both the infinite case (<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tychonoff's_theorem">Tychonoff’s
theorem</a>) and the finite case.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Proposition 3.</strong> (Munkres, Theorem 28.2) <script type="math/tex"> X </script> is compact <script type="math/tex"> \implies </script> <script type="math/tex"> X </script> is
sequentially compact.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We now prove Bolzano-Weierstrass.</p>

<p>Let <script type="math/tex"> \{ x_i \} </script> be a bounded sequence in <script type="math/tex"> \mathbb{R}^n </script>. We need to show that <script type="math/tex"> \{ x_i \}
</script> has a convergent subsequence.</p>

<p>Since the sequence is bounded in <script type="math/tex"> \mathbb{R}^n </script>, by definition of bounded, every element of
the sequence is contained in some closed interval of <script type="math/tex"> \mathbb{R}^n </script>:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> A = [m, M]^n </script>

<p>where <script type="math/tex"> m, M </script> denote the “minimum” and “maximum” of our bounded interval. </p>

<p>Note that <script type="math/tex">[m, M] </script> is compact (Proposition 1). </p>

<p>It follows that <script type="math/tex"> A </script> is compact – it is the product of compact spaces (Proposition 2). </p>

<p>Because <script type="math/tex"> A </script> is compact, <script type="math/tex"> A </script> is sequentially compact (Proposition 3). </p>

<p>In a sequentially compact space, any sequence of points has a convergent subsequence. Note that <script type="math/tex">
\{ x_i \} </script> is one such sequence contained in the sequentially compact space <script type="math/tex"> A </script>, and it
follows that <script type="math/tex"> \{ x_i \} </script> must have a convergent subsequence.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[det(-A) = -det(A) for Odd Square Matrix]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/negative-determinant-odd-even-matrix/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-06T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/11/06/negative-determinant-odd-even-matrix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The proof for this is straightforward, but I didn’t find it explicitly stated elsewhere on the web
– it may just be one of those propositions that’s hard to phrase as a search query. In words:
the negative determinant of an odd square matrix is the determinant of the negative matrix.</p>

<h2 id="proposition">Proposition</h2>
<blockquote>
  <p>If <script type="math/tex">A</script> is an <script type="math/tex"> n \times n </script> square matrix and <script type="math/tex"> n </script> is odd, then <script type="math/tex"> \det(-A) =
-\det(A) </script>.</p>
</blockquote>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="proof">Proof</h2>

<p>Negating all elements of a row of the matrix <script type="math/tex">A</script> negates the determinant of the matrix
(<a href="https://proofwiki.org/wiki/Effect_of_Sequence_of_Elementary_Row_Operations_on_Determinant">proof</a>
– think about it as multiplying a row by the scalar <script type="math/tex">-1</script>). </p>

<p><script type="math/tex">-A</script> is equivalent to <script type="math/tex"> A </script> with each of its rows negated. Because <script type="math/tex"> n </script> is
odd:</p>

<script type="math/tex; mode=display"> \det(-A) = (-1)^n \det(A) = -\det(A) </script>

<h2 id="context">Context</h2>
<p>This fact was needed to prove that if <script type="math/tex"> A </script> is a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthogonal_group">special orthogonal
matrix</a> and <script type="math/tex"> n </script>
is odd, then <script type="math/tex"> A </script> has at least one eigenvector with eigenvalue <script type="math/tex"> 1 </script>.</p>

<p>Note that if <script type="math/tex">n</script> is even, we can prove that <script type="math/tex">\det(A) = \det(-A)</script> using the same technique.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for Computer Science Internship Interviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/01/18/tips-for-computer-science-internship-interviews/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-18T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/01/18/tips-for-computer-science-internship-interviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is meant to help computer science undergraduates looking for a software engineering internship in the summer. Applying to internships can be daunting, and this post will hopefully address some of the commonly asked questions that I see on Reddit’s <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions">cscareerquestions</a>.
Along with some other miscellanea regarding applications, this post covers two things: </p>

<ol>
  <li>What are most internship interviews like?</li>
  <li>How should I prepare for them?</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>I did <a href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2013/06/28/researchtips/">research</a> last summer, and this summer was my first time seriously looking for an internship. From the beginning of September 2013 to the beginning of January 2014 (around 16 weeks), I did a lot of interviewing: 20 technical interviews, four recruiter interviews, two coding challenges, one product manager interview, and one trader interview (involuntarily moved from software engineering). 
One of the reasons that I did so many interviews was that I did poorly on many of my interviews for the first month. 
Despite having read about interviewing on the internet, I wish I had known more <em>concretely</em> how to prepare.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Finally, note that I mostly interviewed with medium to large companies in Silicon Valley: your mileage may vary with local companies or smaller startups.
Out of respect for the companies that I interviewed with, I won’t be linking specific companies to specific interview questions.</p>

<h1 id="the-three-types-of-internship-interviews">The three types of internship interviews</h1>

<p>I would categorize my internship interviews as falling into one of three categories:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>The programming interview:</strong> algorithms, data structures, coding</li>
  <li><strong>The “what you’ve done interview”:</strong> you and your projects</li>
  <li><strong>The language-specific interview:</strong> quizzed about a language you claim to know</li>
</ol>

<p>I’ll explain these in more depth below, adding details on how to prepare for each category. Note
that not every interview falls precisely into one of the three categories, and some interviews
are a mix of multiple categories.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <h2 id="the-programming-interview">The programming interview</h2>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The <strong>programming interview</strong> is the most common type of interview, especially if you’re not interviewing for a specific team.
This is how most people envision computer science interviews: you’re asked one or more programming questions, 
and you implement solutions on a collaborative editor like <a href="http://stypi.com">Stypi</a> or <a href="http://collabedit.com">Collabedit</a>. </p>

<p>I would further divide these interviews into two topics:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Questions involving loops, lists, or strings (easier)</li>
  <li>Questions involving specific data structures (harder)</li>
</ol>

<p>I think the first category is easier, and it includes questions like: <em>Remove duplicates from a list</em> or <em>Generate all of the permutations of a string</em>. Even if you don’t immediately know the answer, there’s a chance that you can figure it out without requiring knowledge of a specific algorithm or data structure.</p>

<p>I find the second category trickier, and sometimes the question will be hard 
or near impossible if you don’t know about a specific data structure or algorithm.
For example, if you’ve never done breadth-first tree traversal, 
and you’re asked: <em>Print the values in this tree level-by-level</em> 
(a question that I received from two different companies),
the question will be much harder.<br />
In one interview, I did poorly when we delved 
deeply into variations of hash tables, but I was only familiar 
with basic linked list hash tables.</p>

<p>At the end of every question, you will almost always be asked to 
discuss the Big-O complexity of your implementation. </p>

<h3 id="checklist">Checklist</h3>

<p>Here’s what I didn’t realize at first: instead of just walking
in, <strong>you should study for interviews</strong>.
Unless you do algorithmic challenges on a regular basis, it’s worth the time
to read and practice.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Read <em><a href="http://www.amazon.com/Programming-Interviews-Exposed-Secrets-Programmer/dp/047012167X">Programming Interviews Exposed</a></em>:</strong> 
Focus on these topics: string manipulation, linked lists, doubly linked lists, hash tables, 
trees, queues, stacks, depth-first search, breadth-first-search, basic graphs,
basic complexity.</li>
  <li><strong>Check Glassdoor</strong>: Many companies have interview questions on Glassdoor. Your goal isn’t
to study the interview questions in advance, but you can get a good idea of the general difficulty
of the programming questions.</li>
  <li><strong>Practice at least once</strong>: I’ll let the interview books cover
this process in more detail, but if this is your first interview, 
I highly recommend practicing an interview question from start to finish with a friend.</li>
</ul>

<p>I would take books like <em>Programming Interviews Exposed</em> with a grain of salt. Except for some of the very big companies, like Facebook,
the interview questions for internships are generally much easier than those for senior developers. You won’t be asked to write
a red-black tree from scratch. From my experience, the list above comprehensively covers the topics from my interview experience
(suggestions welcome).</p>

<p>Depth- and breadth-first search (DFS and BFS, respectively) were extremely popular, and I would estimate <strong>over half of my algorithms interviews 
were best solved with DFS or BFS</strong>. Know them!</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <h2 id="the-what-youve-done-interview">The “what you’ve done” interview</h2>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The <strong>“what you’ve done” interview</strong> is a non-technical, pleasant conversation with your interviewer,
where you get the opportunity to talk about your resume and projects. I found that this
type of interview was more common in small and medium sized companies.</p>

<p>Empirically, I did better on these interviews than on algorithmic interviews, because
it was an opportunity to pitch myself as a passionate developer.
I usually talked about my research, my past internship, 
and/or my experience at <a href="https://www.meteor.com/blog/2013/07/09/congratulations-to-the-meteor-summer-hackathon-2013-teams">the Meteor Summer Hackathon</a>.</p>

<p>Note that I’m a junior (third year undergraduate student). 
If you’re a freshman or sophomore, don’t panic if you don’t have a lot to
talk about yet. Without sideprojects and/or past internships, however,
this interview can be tough. 
You can use course projects, but I think people know that most course projects
are a few files that are hacked together in a few days (varies by school, of course).</p>

<h3 id="checklist-1">Checklist</h3>

<p>Be prepared to talk in-depth about any jobs and projects on your resume. 
For each project, you’ll want to be ready to answer these questions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What was the project?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What was the scope of the project? (i.e., how much time, how big was it)</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What was your role in the project?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What did you learn?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What were some of the challenges in the project?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you prepare these answers, you’ll be ready to answer a more general question that frequently shows up in interviews:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tell me about a technical challenge that you had.</p>
</blockquote>

<ol>
  <li>
    <h2 id="the-language-specific-interview">The language-specific interview</h2>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>The language-specific interview tests your knowledge about a specific language that you
claim to know on your resume. This interview often shows up if you’ve been placed to interview 
with a specific team (e.g., iOS Safari team at Apple, YUI team at Yahoo).</p>

<p>I was never asked coding questions in these interviews, but the interviewers
expected me to show my knowledge through my answers to quiz questions,
my discussion of relevant projects, and my opinions on language features.</p>

<h3 id="checklist-2">Checklist</h3>

<p>If you are placed to interview with a team that uses a specific
language (or framework), you should prepare for the following questions.
I was asked each of these on multiple occasions:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What makes {language} different from other languages?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you had to change something in {language}, what would you change?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a></a> <!-- break the blockquote --></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tell me about a technical challenge that you had when you were working on a project in {language}.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="javascript-specific-questions">JavaScript specific questions</h3>

<p>In addition to the above questions, I was also asked the following question 
on three different occasions for JavaScript-related internships:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tell me about closures in JavaScript.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I usually answered with an explanation of 1. callbacks 2. function scope in JavaScript. 
Closures allow for more traditional object-oriented programming (e.g., objects in Backbone.js are just closures).</p>

<p>One question that I was <em>not</em> asked in any interview was to recite the value of <code>this</code> in various contexts
(not that this means it isn’t fair game).</p>

<h2 id="odds-and-ends">Odds and ends</h2>

<p>Again, not every interview will fall into one of these three categories. I encountered a couple of weird interview styles:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Straight quizzing:</em> One first round interview a recruiter who read quiz questions about databases, Unix systems, and web requests.
The recruiter had a list of answers, and I suspect one important metric, in addition to correctness, was how confidently you answered.</li>
  <li><em>Coursework:</em> I interviewed with a very cool stealth startup working on something that has it roots in security research. Correspondingly,
the whole interview was about my coursework in compilers and theory of computation – no technical questions.</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="beginning-the-interview">Beginning the interview</h1>

<p>Some bigger companies dive straight into the technical part of interviews, but your interviewer will <strong>almost always</strong> ask you a very important question (or some variant) that you should prepare:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Tell me about yourself.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Keep it succinct! I would say it should be a minute long at most. Hit the important points about your interests and experience, and spare your interviewer the life story. I’m saying this because I made the mistake of having a long pitch in the first few interviews, and I could tell that the interviewer ended up getting bored.</p>

<h1 id="ending-the-interview">Ending the interview</h1>

<p>Even when the interview runs over the allocated time, your interviewer will ask:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Do you have any questions for me?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I used to have a lot of trouble with this, but after I started treating it as
an opportunity for conversation, it became much easier. This is a chance to connect on a personal level with the interviewer.
If your performance was borderline, having an insightful conversation
with the interviewer can’t hurt.</p>

<p>If the interviewer hadn’t described himself or herself yet, the first thing I asked was:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Can you tell me more about what you do?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I let the conversation flow from there. If there’s not much to follow up on, I’ll
ask about how they test their product or choose to target new features. There’s <a href="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/16436/do-you-have-any-questions-for-us-in-an-interview">a very good list</a> on Programmers Stack Exchange, although not all of them are suitable for potential interns to ask.</p>

<h1 id="miscellaneous-faq">Miscellaneous: FAQ</h1>

<p>These are my answers to questions that either I was asking at the beginning of the application process or I see 
frequently asked. Most of these don’t have black-or-white answers.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How long should my resume be?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>For companies based in the US, your resume should not be longer than one page. Personally,
I don’t like reading resumes longer than one page. From what I’ve read from various
recruiters and managers on the internet, they don’t either, although it doesn’t mean
automatic rejection.</p>

<p>Make sure your resume looks professional – spacing, font, structure. Use a serif font!</p>

<p>If your resume is too long, consider cutting out parts that are not tech related – clubs, extracurriculars, experience in a different field.</p>

<p>Finally, don’t include things like your high school GPA, because they don’t matter to the people reading your resume.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When should I start applying?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Most internship applications started popping up in October and November.
I think it doesn’t hurt to apply earlier, although one friend told me that
intern candidates at his company usually fared better in spring than in fall.</p>

<p>Before last summer, after I had already decided to do research, I did receive
a few emails for interviews as late as March. If you didn’t jump on it in October,
don’t panic.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How important are sideprojects? </p>
</blockquote>

<p>It depends on the company, but if you’re a freshman (first year) or 
a sophomore (second year), it’s important. 
When I applied to my first internship in freshman spring, 
the recruiter emailed me back saying that the manager 
wanted to know if I had any sideprojects. In addition
to spicing up your resume, it gives you
something substantive to talk about in the “what you’ve done” interviews.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How long can it take to hear back after an interview?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It varies by company. 
From small to medium sized companies, I heard back anywhere from a day to a week.
Without exception, after a final round interview, it took every big company two weeks to a month 
to respond with either an offer or rejection.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How can I overcome nervousness during interviews?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In some of the algorithmic interviews, when I started doing poorly, I would just freeze and ramble – especially if I hadn’t slept much the previous night because of schoolwork.
Eventually, the interviewer would (pretty much) tell me the answer, which almost always led to rejection after the interview. </p>

<p>If this happens to you, my advice is to tell the interviewer, “Let me consolidate my thoughts for a moment.” Take a few deep breaths, don’t think about anything, and then tackle the question again.</p>

<p>If you feel nervous from the very beginning, try to persuade yourself that it’s only a friendly conversation. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>How can I know how well my interview went?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In my experience, if the interviewer starts talking about how much responsibility interns 
have <em>and</em> you didn’t explicitly ask about it – the interview probably went well.  This is not a guarantee by any means.</p>

<p>I’ve read a few things on the internet about asking your interviewer how they felt the interview went. 
I haven’t tried this before, but feel free to let me know if you have. 
I think it would be a useful source of feedback.</p>

<p>Hope this helps.</p>

<p><em>Any specific questions or insights? Feel free to to comment or ping me at <code>pong [at] outlook.com</code></em></p>

<p><strong>UPDATE</strong>: Before publishing this article, I asked one person – Kevin Gong, a senior at UC
Berkeley – to edit this article. This was the last time that I talked to him. 
In March 2014, Kevin passed away in a car accident. He was
incredibly passionate about applying technology to the world and helping younger students kickstart
their careers. If this article helped you, please consider donating to the <a href="https://www.facebook.com/events/1562918887253164/">Kevin K. Gong Memorial Scholarship for Bright Minds and Big Hearts</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
