<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: travel | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2018-07-12T17:24:19+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Couchsurfing Safe? (and other common questions)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-24 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://couchsurfing.com">Couchsurfing</a> is a site that connects travelers to local hosts in a city.
As long as both the traveler and host agree, the traveler stays with the host free of charge. 
Although the traveler stays for free, experienced couchsurfers don’t view the site as a way find
free lodging but instead as an opportunity to spend time with a local.</p>

<p>I usually try to Couchsurf when I travel, though it’s not always possible depending on the popularity of the destination. At the time of writing, I’ve stayed with about ten hosts through my travels.</p>

<p>This post is targeted towards people who are curious about using Couchsurfing as a guest but unsure
what to expect from the experience.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I have a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S">travel-related YouTube
channel</a>.
Subscribe!</p>

<h2 id="is-couchsurfing-safe">Is Couchsurfing safe?</h2>
<p>The most common question is: is Couchsurfing safe?</p>

<p>The answer is yes, but use your caution. You’re signing up to stay in a stranger’s home, so you
definitely want to research your host beforehand. A well-reviewed host is a pretty safe bet.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing works on a reference system; both hosts and guests provide references after the
exchange. Personally, I only look for hosts that have a decent number of references (five or more).
By definition, this also increases the chances that they’re willing to accept guests.</p>

<p>However, navigating references can be tricky. Even if a guest had a slightly bad experience,
negative references are rare; guests don’t want to receive a negative reference in return.
This has two implications.</p>

<p>First, even a single negative
reference, for both a host or a guest, is considered a major red flag – something very egregious
must have happened. Second, finding out whether a
host is problematic requires carefully reading reviews. Since guests may tiptoe around directly
negative feedback, it’s important to analyze for any hints of negativity dispersed among
compliments (e.g., host was too controlling, didn’t show up, etc.).</p>

<p>As an unfortunate reality of the world, Couchsurfing can be more difficult for
females. There are a multitude of articles describing unwanted solicitation from hosts. My
recommendation is to prefer female couchsurfing hosts, although those are harder to find. Otherwise,
carefully read other females’ reviews for a particular host.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do-with-your-hosts">What do you do with your hosts?</h2>
<p>There’s no definitive answer - it completely depends on your host.</p>

<p>Different hosts have different personalities, schedules, budgets, and so on. All of them will talk
to you, but not all will actually hang out. Your host is <em>not</em> obligated to be your tour guide.</p>

<p>A non-exhaustive spectrum of hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hosts that don’t hang out outside of home, often because they host couchsurfers non-stop and
can’t afford time-wise to show every guest around the city</li>
  <li>Hosts that work during the day and want to get dinner in the evening</li>
  <li>Hosts that will spend a whole day to take you somewhere or show you around</li>
</ul>

<p>To illustrate this concretely, here are things I’ve done in the past with my hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hiking at a national park and getting stuck (Taiwan)</li>
  <li>Walked around for an hour and had a beer (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Went to a Noel Gallagher concert (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Talked for a few hours, staying only one night (Petah Tiqva)</li>
  <li>Cooked dinner (Venice)</li>
  <li>Ate ramen at home (Seoul)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-are-the-accommodations">What are the accommodations?</h2>
<p>Similarly, your accommodations vary depending on host.</p>

<p>Hosts will be very annoyed if you treat Couchsurfing like a hostel or hotel. Be considerate, clean
up after yourself, and so on: they’re not obligated to provide any services. After all, they’re
letting you crash in their home <em>for free.</em> In this vein, most hosts do not give their guests a key,
rightfully not wanting a stranger to freely have access to their home.</p>

<p>A few examples of my past accommodations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A couch, many times</li>
  <li>Shared a bed with my host, twice (not in any sexual fashion)</li>
  <li>A private room with a bed in a penthouse apartment (super rare, obviously!)</li>
  <li>A guy who had 10+ couchsurfing guests in his apartment at any time with people sleeping
everywhere</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-can-i-do-to-find-a-host-to-stay-with">What can I do to find a host to stay with?</h2>
<p>Couchsurfing is a two-way street. The host needs to want you to stay with them, and you need to want
stay with the host. From their perspective, they’re inviting a stranger into their home, so you want
to present yourself as a respectful and considerate guest.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing hosts, especially in popular destinations, are often spammed with grammar-mangled,
copy-pasted requests. Your goal is to stand out from this crowd.</p>

<h3 id="write-a-personalized-well-constructed-message">Write a personalized, well-constructed message</h3>
<p>Writing a personalized message request will maximize your chances of finding a host. Hosts want to
know that you’re asking to stay with <em>them</em>, not just mass-spamming for a free stay.  In fact, many
hosts’ profiles will ask guests to include some “passphrase” statement to ensure that the requestor
has actually read the profile.</p>

<p>When I write a request, I always start strong with a few sentences personalized to the hosts’
profile, then I write a
short two or three sentence copy-paste about my visit in the city. If the host wants to find out
more about me, the rest is on my Couchsurfing profile.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of a message I sent that introduces me briefly, indicates that I read their
profile, and states that I’m flexible about hanging out. The first paragraph is personalized (the
host’s profile mentions something about Latin dances); the second one is copy-pasted.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hey (host name),</p>

  <p>My name is Louis, I’m also in IT (I work in the USA as a programmer). I’m going to be in
Istanbul for a few days before I travel to Erbil to teach breakdancing, would you be willing to host
me for two nights? Unfortunately, I don’t know any Latin dances :(</p>

  <p>I’ve couchsurfed many times in the past, and I’m a very respectful and clean guest. I’m also down to
hang out or not depending on your schedule – these are weekday dates so I expect you might be
working. My schedule is very open to spend time together, except that I may be meeting up with other
dancers one of the nights.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="have-a-well-fleshed-out-profile">Have a well-fleshed out profile</h3>
<p>If you are trying to find a host for the first time, having a non-empty profile is crucial. Again,
from the perspective of the host, they can only base their opinion from what they see on the site:
profile, messages, references. Although I’ve never hosted, I’ve been told by previous hosts of three
profile factors that often contribute to accepting requests:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>References</strong>: It’s chicken-and-egg, but it’s hard for hosts to host you if no one is vouching
for you. For those starting off, ask any friends who have Couchsurfed in the past to leave a
reference. Another option is to meet up with someone in the local Couchsurfing community and get
a reference.</li>
  <li><strong>“Proof of existence”:</strong> My profile contains a link to this site and my YouTube channel. I’ve had
multiple hosts tell me that simply poking around these links made me more trustworthy.</li>
  <li><strong>Couchsurfing verification:</strong> Couchsurfing has an option to upload and verify your identity for a
fee. One of my previous hosts said that they have a strong preference for verified
profiles. I’ve never done verification, but it helps a lot if your profile is just starting off.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="should-i-bring-a-gift">Should I bring a gift?</h2>
<p>Gifting is universal across cultures, and I recommend bringing or buying a gift for your host
– even something small like candy. It’s the thought that counts.</p>

<h2 id="concluding-thoughts">Concluding thoughts</h2>
<p>Overall, I’ve had extremely positive experiences with Couchsurfing and would highly recommend
it to anyone. I’ve made countless great memories through Couchsurfing, but I’ve only had one “bad
experience”, where the host was very controlling. Even that was still an overall fun experience.</p>

<p>In my mind, there are two minor downsides to Couchsurfing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It requires you to be social. During my travels, I sometimes just don’t feel like
socializing.</li>
  <li>Less schedule flexibility for going “home.” Since most hosts don’t give you a key, you oten
have to coordinate with your host. This is especially bad if you’re jetlagged, and you need to get
creative for where to sleep during the day.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m a semi-experienced Couchsurfing guest, but my experience is still a small slice of that of
more experienced individuals, such as the power hosts that have hosted over one hundred guests.</p>

<p>If you have any other questions about Couchsurfing, feel free to leave them in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Dharamshala Airport to McLeod Ganj]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/22/transportation-from-dharamshala-airport-to-mcleod-ganj/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-22 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/22/transportation-from-dharamshala-airport-to-mcleod-ganj</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last updated: June 2018</em></p>

<p>This post describes what to expect when going from the Dharamshala Airport to MacLeod Ganj,
Dharamshala, India – the central tourist area of Dharamshala.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>We took a taxi from the airport to McLeod Ganj for 800 rupees, though the exact price depends on the
location of your residence. Go to the prepaid taxi booth and talk to the booth. There will be a number of drivers and a clerk outside of the stand. The drivers may try to
circumvent you from speaking to the booth, ignore them temporarily and get the slip signed off. In
our case, we ended up getting a lower price confirmed by the booth.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Agra to Delhi Airport]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/21/transportation-from-agra-to-delhi-airport/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/21/transportation-from-agra-to-delhi-airport</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Last updated: June 2018</em></p>

<p>This post describes how to get from <a href="https://wikitravel.org/en/Agra">Agra, India</a>, to New Delhi,
India. It focuses on how to get to the airport in the same day, though all of the advice applies
more generally to getting from one city to the other.</p>

<p>While attending a wedding in Agra, I had to get from Agra to Delhi in the same day in order to catch
a 14:00 flight.  The distance from Agra to Delhi is quite large (3-5 hour drive depending on
traffic), so I did some research on the most economical methods of reaching the Delhi airport. This
is a summary of my research that will hopefully help other travelers evaluate their options.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="traditional-taxi-service">Traditional taxi service</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~4000 rupees</strong></p>

<p>It’s easy to get a bunch of conflicting prices here. Definitely don’t book through a hotel (hostel
will probably give you better price) as they will way overcharge you – hotels’ quoted prices 
were around 200 USD.</p>

<p>We used <a href="https://www.tripadvisor.in/Attraction_Review-g297683-d13188303-Reviews-D_K_Car_and_Driver_India-Agra_Agra_District_Uttar_Pradesh.html">D.K. Car and Driver India</a>, which was the first result on TripAdvisor at the time of our trip. I called him using the hotel phone, but he also responded to my Facebook messages in about an hour, which was advantageous since I was trying to book at 4 PM the day before. Everything went seamlessly, so I’m willing to stick in my endorsement for D.K. here.</p>

<p>We paid around 4000 rupees, which at the time of writing, was about 60 USD. The trip was four hours.</p>

<h2 id="savaari--clearcar--other-taxi-aggregator">Savaari / ClearCar / other taxi aggregator</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~2500 rupees</strong>. The sites don’t give an exact amount, but this is an estimation based on
their formulas for trips over 80km.</p>

<p>There are a number of taxi aggregators in India (Savaari, ClearCar, etc.) that do “outstation” (out of town) trips. These are essentially like Uber, except that you book the car in advance, and it shows up at the specified time. Savaari was suggested by a native Indian
acquaintance of mine, as he was using it to leave Agra after the wedding. </p>

<p>After doing some research of reviews, it
seems that these services aren’t fully reliable; many reviews contained instances of drivers being late,
cancelling the hour beforehand, intentionally taking longer routes, etc. While online reviews are
likely biased toward the bad instances, it does suggest that these services could be hit-or-miss
(although it must be “hit” enough that a native Indian suggested it to us).</p>

<p>Despite being the best balance of convenience and price, I ended up not going with this option due
to the potential time unreliability, especially for a 7AM flight. However, <strong>if you simply want to get from
Agra to Delhi as a group with looser time constraints, Savaari is both cheaper and more convenient
than public transportation.</strong></p>

<h2 id="public-transportation">Public transportation</h2>

<p><strong>Cost: ~1000 rupees / person.</strong> Air-conditioned class train tickets ranged from 700 to 1200 rupees.</p>

<p>Public transportation here means train, metro, and bus/short-distance cab.  For the trains, view
up-to-date timetables and book tickets at <a href="https://www.irctc.co.in/">IRCTC</a>. I’m not sure if they
take international cards; I’ve seen varying reports online.</p>

<p>In general, public transportation (train/metro) is a good option for Agra to Delhi. </p>

<p>For getting to the airport specifically, it becomes more complicated. We ran into a myriad of issues trying to plan a public transit route. The fastest 2.25 hour express trains from Agra to Delhi ran only in the evening, which didn’t work for our 14:00 flight, so the train would be least 3 hours. Additionally, the trains for our timetable only went to Hazrat Nizmuddin station, which would require either a bus/cab to the airport or airport metro line.</p>

<p>To summarize, the trip would involve:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Residence in Agra to Agra Cantt station (<strong>10-20 min</strong>)</li>
  <li>Agra Cantt to New Delhi Station or Hazrat Nizmuddin station (<strong>2.25 to 3.5 hours</strong>, depending on what
train you catch)</li>
  <li>If at New Delhi Station, metro to airport. If at Hazrat Nizmuddin station, figure out a way to get
to the airport metro, then head to airport (either way, <strong>30 min to 1 hour</strong>, and traffic is bad).</li>
</ul>

<p>If you have an evening flight, then public transportation to the airport is a viable
option, as you have more time flexibility without waking up at an ungodly hour. If traveling solo,
this is the cheapest option by far, but if your group
has two or more people and you have time flexibility, a Savaari cab becomes about the same
price per person.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dubrovnik Bus Departure Schedule (Croatia)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-bus-departure-schedule/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-02 22:15:33 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-bus-departure-schedule</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains the bus schedule for departures from Dubrovonik, Croatia. Dubrovonik is a
popular coastal destination (and the filming site of King’s Landing for the <em>Game of Thrones</em> TV
show!). </p>

<p><em>Last updated: 1 September 2015</em></p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Timetables may differ between on and off seasons. My trip was at the beginning of September, which is on
the border of on and off seasons.</p>

<h2 id="timetable">Timetable</h2>

<p>If you find an updated timetable during your travels, please send it to me to update this page for
other travelers.</p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/dubrovonikbus/timetable.jpg" alt="Bus timetable" /></p>

<h2 id="destinations">Destinations</h2>

<p><strong>International:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Sarajevo</li>
  <li>Medugorje</li>
  <li>Kotor</li>
  <li>Budva</li>
  <li>Trieste</li>
  <li>Herceg Novi</li>
  <li>Ulcinj</li>
  <li>Podgorica</li>
  <li>Zenica</li>
  <li>Mos</li>
  <li>Ivanica - Trebinje</li>
  <li>Skopje</li>
  <li>Ljubljana</li>
  <li>Petrovac</li>
  <li>Bar</li>
  <li>Tivat</li>
  <li>Frankfurt</li>
  <li>Tuzla</li>
  <li>Beograd (Belgrade)</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Domestic:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>Metkovic</li>
  <li>Ploce</li>
  <li>Orebic</li>
  <li>Korcula - Vela Luka</li>
  <li>Makarska</li>
  <li>Split</li>
  <li>Trogir</li>
  <li>Sibenik</li>
  <li>Zadar</li>
  <li>Rijeka</li>
  <li>Pula</li>
  <li>Karlovac</li>
  <li>Zagreb</li>
  <li>Osijek, Vinkovci, S. Brod</li>
  <li>Varazdin</li>
  <li>Vrgorac</li>
  <li>Otric-Seoci</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dubrovnik's Best Currency Exchange (Croatia)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-best-currency-exchange/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-02 22:15:33 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/02/dubrovnik-best-currency-exchange</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains information about the best place to exchange currency in Dubrovnik, Croatia:
<strong>OK Travel Agency</strong>.</p>

<p>Dubrovnik is a popular coastal destination (and the filming site of King’s Landing for the <em>Game of Thrones</em> TV
show!). </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="directions">Directions</h2>

<p>The travel agency is located at <strong>Obala Stjepana Radića 32, Dubrovnik, Croatia</strong>. </p>

<p>It is very
convenient to reach when arriving in Dubrovonik by bus or boat, because it is located next to the main
port and central bus station. </p>

<p>It is further from Old Town, and you will take one of the buses to the central bus station or
port (most of them stop here), then walk to the agency. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/dubrovonikcurrency/oktravel.jpg" alt="Outside of OK Travel Agency" /></p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d5868.382096555248!2d18.08878992153864!3d42.65730670065322!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x134c7525b02fd643%3A0x9fe451262d4d1f78!2sObala+Stjepana+Radi%C4%87a+32%2C+20000%2C+Dubrovnik%2C+Croatia!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1441228112407" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="rates">Rates</h2>

<p>I received exchange rates from OK Travel Agency that were <strong>0.8% from
the midmarket rate</strong> (the rate from internet searches). There was <strong>no commission</strong>.</p>

<p>Rates change over time, but in September 2015, the midmarket rate was 7.55 kuna to the euro. I
received 7.49 kuna to the euro. <script type="math/tex">(1 - 7.49 / 7.55 = 0.079)</script></p>

<p><em>Last updated: 2 September 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
