<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: travel | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-09T14:09:27+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Traveling from Istanbul to Şile by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/01/istanbul-to-sile/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-01 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/01/istanbul-to-sile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The intention of this post is to document how to travel from Istanbul to Şile by
bus. At the time of writing, there do not appear to be any English resources for
this route. The official IETT app and Google Maps both document this incorrectly.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Şile is a popular place for the residents of Istanbul to escape for a day trip.
Technically, Şile is part of Istanbul, although it’s quite remote. The bus ride
is about two hours away; by car, it is about 45 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="bus-line">Bus Line</h2>
<p>Taking any bus that is prefixed with <strong>139</strong> is okay, all of them stop at Şile
first but their continuing routes after Şile may differ.</p>

<p>The
<a href="https://www.iett.istanbul/en/main/hatlar/139/%C3%9CSK%C3%9CDAR%20-%20%C5%9E%C4%B0LE-%C4%B0ETT-Otob%C3%BCs-Sefer-Saatleri-ve-Duraklar%C4%B1">IETT</a>
site gives a description of the stops; however, as explained below, the bus stop
location is incorrect on the site. Also note that this link only shows the 139
bus, but the 139A, 139T, etc. also run, meaning that there is approximately one
bus to Şile every hour.</p>

<p>The bus has various stops in the Şile area, though the bus terminal is a safe
bet for a place to get off.</p>

<h2 id="bus-stop-location">Bus Stop Location</h2>
<p><strong>Do not wait at the Üsküdar Marmaray bus station.</strong> The correct location for
this intercity bus is the Şemsipaşa stop (<a href="https://goo.gl/maps/3YyADTwU8gENbKk98">Google Maps
link</a>), which is about a block west.
There, you will see a paper with times for the bus to Şile.</p>

<p>A ticket is required for this bus. The place to purchase the tickets is about a
two minute walk from the bus stop (<a href="https://goo.gl/maps/R4AqwriFRpaxxnDp8">Google Maps
link</a>). At the time of writing (July
2020), a one way ticket was 14.50 lira. If you don’t speak Turkish, you probably
can’t get on the bus without a ticket, although I’ve been told it’s possible to
sit on the floor if the bus is full.</p>

<p>If you try to buy too close to the departure time, it’s possible that the bus
may be full.</p>

<p>It may be possible to buy online, but the author of this article doesn’t know
how.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sim Card Price in Turkey in February 2020]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Getting a SIM card in Turkey for short to medium term stays in Turkey is
straightforward. In this article, I describe my experience with prices in
<em>February 2020</em> using Turkcell.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I bought my SIM card in Fatih. I’m actually not sure if what I got was a good
deal. Turkcell offers all types of short-term deals for tourists as well. I
visited three stores in Fatih and they all gave me approximately the same rate
(some trying to squeeze +/- 10 lira) without the option for any smaller plans.</p>

<p>These rates are for foreigners. You’ll see advertisements for cellphone data at
amazing prices, but these require a Turkish bank account.</p>

<h2 id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>My plan was <strong>20 GB data for 120 lira</strong> (around 20 USD at the time of writing). However,
it should be noted that the 20 GB is <strong>for one month only</strong>.</p>

<p>Although the SIM card lasts for multiple months, you do need to top up in future
months. The top-up is at a rate rate that I don’t remember, but it’s much
cheaper than the initial upfront cost.</p>

<p>I didn’t really keep track of the SMS and call time in the plan, though that’s
included. It’s 2020, use WhatsApp :)</p>

<h3 id="long-term-stays">Long-term stays</h3>
<p>It should be noted that the SIM card situation for long-term stays (more than
120 days) gets much more expensive. You have to pay a foreigner registration fee
that’s more than 200 USD. I won’t go much into it here, but you can read about
it <a href="https://toomanyadapters.com/buying-sim-card-turkey/">on this page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="purchasing">Purchasing</h2>
<p>Bring your passport. It took about ten to fifteen minutes for the guy to finish
registering everything.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sahibinden: The Craigslist of Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Sahibinden</strong> (literally, “owners”) is the Craigslist equivalent of Turkey.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="usage">Usage</h2>

<p>In order to respond to listings (at least housing listings, in my experience),
you do need access to a Turkish cellphone number. The site will ask you to enter
a verification code that is texted to the Turkish number before you can respond.</p>

<h2 id="housing">Housing</h2>
<p>Sahibinden’s housing search is top-notch. In addition to the filters that one
would expect such as flat type and price, it also allows filtering by
furnished/unfurnished, renting from owner/broker, building age.</p>

<p><img src="/images/travel/sahibinden/example.png" alt="Example map search" /></p>

<p>On a separate topic, finding housing in Istanbul has a number of options. I’d
recommend reading <a href="https://yabangee.com/finding-a-flat-in-istanbul-a-basic-guide-to-accommodation/">this article</a>, particularly on the difference between renting
from a broker and an owner.</p>

<p>Note: I do dispute one part of this article. They say that renting through an
owner usually has higher quality furnishing. At least in Sisli, my experience
was the opposite: broker flats tended to be newer and have better
furnishing. Most importantly, there were way more broker listings than owner
listings, which meant that the options were “better” for my specific needs based
purely on a higher volume of selection.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-shady-housing-deals">Avoiding shady housing deals</h3>
<p>Like Craigslist, Sahibinden actually includes a warning about housing scams,
though it’s in Turkish. This notification is mostly common sense: don’t wire
money to anyone you haven’t actually met.</p>

<p>I also found that some ads seemed to reuse pictures from other ads (e.g., two
flats in different locations with the exact same pictures and different owners).
Usually, one of them (I believe) is a scam. Longer-term accounts have a
small award image for how long they’ve been on Sahibinden (e.g., 11 years); the
shady ones had no such image. I’m not saying all accounts without the award are
scams, but if you run into two ads with the same pictures, the legitimate one is
probably the certified one.</p>

<p>My friend that lives in Istanbul also told me a few other things to watch out
for when using Sahibinden for housing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Renting daily flats through Sahibinden is difficult (even short- to
medium- term can be a bit of a hassle, as many owners want stable tenants.
However, when renting from a broker, they do like short-term tenants because
they usually charge the full broker fee of one month’s rent).</li>
  <li>Posters will often post really nice looking pictures but the apartment
actually looks a lot worse in person.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best ATM (No-Fee) in Istanbul, Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The best ATM in Istanbul, Turkey is a coveted title. There’s a lot of banks that
accept international cards, but some of them will try to extract more money from
you via service fee or dynamic currency conversion (DCC).</p>

<p>The best ATM is <strong>HSBC</strong> (only 1000 lira at a time, mixed denominations).</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-best-atm-hsbc">The Best ATM: HSBC</h2>
<p>At the moment, HSBC has no extra fees and serves mostly 100 TL bills with some
50 and 20 TL.</p>

<p>In February 2020, QNB used to allow large transactions, no fees, and serving
only 100 TL bills, but this is no longer the case as of June 2020.</p>

<p>Depending on the ATM, they may try to apply DCC, so when the DCC menu comes
up, make sure to click <strong>Istemiyorum</strong> (it was on the left side), which means:
“I do not want.” Make sure you say no to DCC. DCC is very bad (Google it).</p>

<p>See the table below for a relative comparison.</p>

<h2 id="atm-comparisons">ATM Comparisons</h2>
<p>Credit for this table goes to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Turkey/comments/cute4k/a_guide_to_turkish_atms_if_you_are_using_a_card/">some anonymous user on
Reddit</a>, who I’m actually,
very truly grateful for taking the time to write and do this exploration. As of
February 2020, I can verify that at least some of these were true, as I tried
about five ATMs in central Sisli.</p>

<p>If you have any updates or additions to this table, please add them below.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bank</th>
      <th>Non-DCC Fee</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>HSBC</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Mixed bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>AKBANK</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 20 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HalkBank</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 5 TL/10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ZiraatBanksi</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>VakifBank</td>
      <td>Flat 10 lira fee</td>
      <td>I went to one and it was 4%.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>QNB Finansbank</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Garanti</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Bankamatik</td>
      <td>2.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>YapiKredi</td>
      <td>3%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Denizbank</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="fees-on-the-card-side">Fees on the card side</h2>
<p>This is not really an advertisement, since I don’t really make money
from this blog.</p>

<p>In addition to the fees charged by the owning bank of the ATM, the owning bank
of the card might also have foreign transaction fees. I use Charles Schwab (for
my god-bless USA of bank account), which has no fees. It also waives ATM fees,
but I’ve actually never been sure if that works for international bank fees such as
the ones above.</p>

<p>If for whatever reason this inspires you to sign up for Schwab, I have <a href="http://www.schwab.com/public/schwab/nn/refer-prospect.html?refrid=REFERY23JXD3D">this
referral
link</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Couchsurfing Safe? (and other common questions)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions/"/>
    <updated>2018-06-24 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2018/06/24/is-couchsurfing-safe-and-other-common-questions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://couchsurfing.com">Couchsurfing</a> is a site that connects travelers to local hosts in a city.
As long as both the traveler and host agree, the traveler stays with the host free of charge. 
Although the traveler stays for free, experienced couchsurfers don’t view the site as a way to find
free lodging but instead as an opportunity to spend time with a local.</p>

<p>I usually try to Couchsurf when I travel, though it’s not always possible depending on the popularity of the destination. At the time of writing, I’ve stayed with about ten hosts through my travels.</p>

<p>This post is targeted towards people who are curious about using Couchsurfing as a guest but unsure
what to expect from the experience.</p>

<!-- more -->

<!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S).
Subscribe! -->

<h2 id="is-couchsurfing-safe">Is Couchsurfing safe?</h2>
<p>The most common question is: is Couchsurfing safe?</p>

<p>The answer is yes, but use caution. You’re signing up to stay in a stranger’s home, so you
definitely want to research your host beforehand. A well-reviewed host is a pretty safe bet.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing works on a reference system; both hosts and guests provide references after the
exchange. Personally, I only look for hosts that have a decent number of references (five or more).
By definition, this also increases the chances that they’re willing to accept guests.</p>

<p>However, navigating references can be tricky. Even if a guest had a slightly bad experience,
negative references are rare; guests don’t want to receive a negative reference in return.
This has two implications.</p>

<p>First, even a single negative
reference, for both a host or a guest, is considered a major red flag – something very egregious
must have happened. Second, finding out whether a
host is problematic requires carefully reading reviews. Since guests may tiptoe around directly
negative feedback, it’s important to analyze for any hints of negativity dispersed among
compliments (e.g., host was too controlling, didn’t show up, etc.).</p>

<p>As an unfortunate reality of the world, Couchsurfing can be more difficult for females.  Many
articles describe unwanted solicitation from hosts. My recommendation is to prefer female
couchsurfing hosts, although those are harder to find. Otherwise, carefully read other females’
reviews for a particular host.</p>

<h2 id="what-do-you-do-with-your-hosts">What do you do with your hosts?</h2>
<p>There’s no definitive answer - it completely depends on your host.</p>

<p>Different hosts have different personalities, schedules, budgets, and so on. All of them will talk
to you, but not all will actually hang out. Your host is <em>not</em> obligated to be your tour guide.</p>

<p>A non-exhaustive spectrum of hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hosts that don’t hang out outside of home, often because they host couchsurfers non-stop and
can’t afford time-wise to show every guest around the city</li>
  <li>Hosts that work during the day and want to get dinner in the evening</li>
  <li>Hosts that will spend a whole day to take you somewhere or show you around</li>
</ul>

<p>To illustrate this concretely, here are things I’ve done in the past with my hosts:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Hiked at a national park and got stuck (Taiwan)</li>
  <li>Walked around for an hour and had a beer (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Went to a Noel Gallagher concert (Copenhagen)</li>
  <li>Talked for a few hours, staying only one night (Petah Tiqva)</li>
  <li>Cooked dinner (Venice)</li>
  <li>Ate ramen at home (Seoul)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-are-the-accommodations">What are the accommodations?</h2>
<p>Similarly, your accommodations vary depending on host.</p>

<p>Hosts will be very annoyed if you treat Couchsurfing like a hostel or hotel. Be considerate, clean
up after yourself, and so on: they’re not obligated to provide any services. After all, they’re
letting you crash in their home <em>for free.</em> In this vein, most hosts do not give their guests a key,
rightfully not wanting a stranger to freely have access to their home.</p>

<p>A few examples of my past accommodations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A couch, many times</li>
  <li>Shared a bed with my host, twice (not in any sexual fashion)</li>
  <li>A private room with a bed in a penthouse apartment (super rare, obviously!)</li>
  <li>A guy who had 10+ couchsurfing guests in his apartment at any time with people sleeping
everywhere</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-can-i-do-to-find-a-host-to-stay-with">What can I do to find a host to stay with?</h2>
<p>Couchsurfing is a two-way street. The host needs to want you to stay with them, and you need to want
stay with the host. From their perspective, they’re inviting a stranger into their home, so you want
to present yourself as a respectful and considerate guest.</p>

<p>Couchsurfing hosts, especially in popular destinations, are often spammed with grammar-mangled,
copy-pasted requests. Your goal is to stand out from this crowd.</p>

<h3 id="write-a-personalized-well-constructed-message">Write a personalized, well-constructed message</h3>
<p>Writing a personalized message request will maximize your chances of finding a host. Hosts want to
know that you’re asking to stay with <em>them</em>, not just mass-spamming for a free stay.  In fact, many
hosts’ profiles will ask guests to include some “passphrase” statement to ensure that the requester
has actually read the profile.</p>

<p>When I write a request, I always start strong with a few sentences personalized to the host’s
profile, then I write a
short two or three sentence copy-paste about my visit in the city. If the host wants to find out
more about me, the rest is on my Couchsurfing profile.</p>

<p>Here’s an example of a message I sent that introduces me briefly, indicates that I read their
profile, and states that I’m flexible about hanging out. The first paragraph is personalized (the
host’s profile mentions something about Latin dances); the second one is copy-pasted.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hey (host name),</p>

  <p>My name is Louis, I’m also in IT (I work in the USA as a programmer). I’m going to be in
Istanbul for a few days before I travel to Erbil to teach breakdancing, would you be willing to host
me for two nights? Unfortunately, I don’t know any Latin dances :(</p>

  <p>I’ve couchsurfed many times in the past, and I’m a very respectful and clean guest. I’m also down to
hang out or not depending on your schedule – these are weekday dates so I expect you might be
working. My schedule is very open to spend time together, except that I may be meeting up with other
dancers one of the nights.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="have-a-well-fleshed-out-profile">Have a well-fleshed out profile</h3>
<p>If you are trying to find a host for the first time, having a populated profile is crucial. Again,
from the perspective of the host, they can only base their opinion on what they see:
profile, messages, references. Although I’ve never hosted, I’ve been told by previous hosts of three
profile factors that often contribute to accepting requests:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>References</strong>: It’s chicken-and-egg, but it’s hard for hosts to host you if no one is vouching
for you. For those starting off, ask any friends who have Couchsurfed in the past to leave a
reference. Another option is to meet up with someone in the local Couchsurfing community and get
a reference.</li>
  <li><strong>“Proof of existence”:</strong> My profile contains a link to this site and my YouTube channel. I’ve had
multiple hosts tell me that simply poking around these links made me more trustworthy.</li>
  <li><strong>Couchsurfing verification:</strong> Couchsurfing has an option to upload and verify your identity for a
fee. One of my previous hosts said that they have a strong preference for verified
profiles. I’ve never done verification, but it helps a lot if your profile is just starting off.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="should-i-bring-a-gift">Should I bring a gift?</h2>
<p>Gifting is universal across cultures, and I recommend bringing or buying a gift for your host
– even something small like candy. It’s the thought that counts.</p>

<h2 id="concluding-thoughts">Concluding thoughts</h2>
<p>Overall, I’ve had extremely positive experiences with Couchsurfing and would highly recommend
it to anyone. I’ve made countless great memories through Couchsurfing, but I’ve only had one “bad
experience,” where the host was very controlling. Even that was still fun overall.</p>

<p>In my mind, there are two minor downsides to Couchsurfing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Social requirement: during my travels, I sometimes just don’t feel like socializing.</li>
  <li>Less schedule flexibility to go “home.” Since most hosts don’t give you a key, you often have to
coordinate with your host. This is especially bad if you’re jetlagged, and you need to get
creative to find a place to sleep during the day.</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m a semi-experienced Couchsurfing guest, but my experience is still a small sample of that of
more experienced individuals, such as the power hosts who have hosted over one hundred guests.</p>

<p>If you have any other questions about Couchsurfing, feel free to leave them in the comments below.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
