<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: school | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/school/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-03T16:24:33+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sophomore Spring: A Brief List of What I Learned]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2013/05/13/what-i-learned-this-semester/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-13 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2013/05/13/what-i-learned-this-semester</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here’s a concise list of [some of] the things that I learned this semester. I would say that the things that I learned this semester are a lot more diverse than those from last semester (I’d describe last semester as…math).</p>

<h2 id="research">Research</h2>

<p>(I work in an HCI research group).</p>

<p><strong>Demo or die</strong>.</p>

<p><strong>Experimental design in HCI</strong> is very similar to experimental design in psychology. HCI is human-computer interaction; psychology is human interaction.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><strong>What does my advisor do in his day-to-day life?</strong> As an HCI professor, he is a master of experimental design. As an advisor, his day is often filled with meetings, colloquia, and proposals. I wonder when he finds time to hack on something or put together a project (but amazingly, he manages to do it).</p>

<p><strong>What is the life of a grad student like?</strong> They seem to have a lot of time to code things. They attend a lot of talks, possibly looking for inspiration?</p>

<p>Group meeting is very insightful.</p>

<p>I’ve known, but now better understand, the concept of <strong>programming as a tool.</strong> The person reading your paper doesn’t care about your code, your backend, or your choice of framework.</p>

<h2 id="programming-languages">Programming Languages</h2>

<p>The class could be titled <em>Programming Languages Theory</em>, since it’s an introductory class. I think students who haven’t taken it and aren’t familiar with the field aren’t too sure what topics to expect.</p>

<p>What is programming language (PL) theory? Here’s a meme-style joke that I usually think of when someone asks me what it is:</p>

<dl>
  <dt>What students outside of computer science think:</dt>
  <dd>“Oh, so you learn how to program in a lot of different programming languages.”</dd>
  <dt>What computer science students unfamiliar with PL think (myself included at the time):</dt>
  <dd>“You do something formal with programming languages. You prove things about them. Or something like that.”</dd>
  <dt>What it really is:</dt>
  <dd>“Logic and inference rules. Induction. Semantics and types. More inference rules. Models.”</dd>
</dl>

<p>There is a lot more to the field, but that’s what was packed into the introductory course.</p>

<p>There also seem to be a lot of ways to teach a PL course. From looking at other resources on the internet, a lot of professors choose to make the whole course closely follow some programming language, and all concepts are taught with applications. I think I prefer the approach in my course, where the first half was purely theory and the second half mixed theory with code.</p>

<h2 id="computational-linguistics">Computational Linguistics</h2>

<p>Lambda-calculus has applications in grammars and quantifiers!</p>

<p>I actually gained a good understanding of the problems in natural language processing. It was a good class for breadth, and my final project, which tackled <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word-sense_disambiguation">word sense disambiguation</a>, was pretty interesting.</p>

<p>Prolog is interesting. I’m pretty impressed by how easy it is to build a basic parser in Prolog.</p>

<h2 id="rover">Rover</h2>

<p><strong>Clients don’t care about the technical details.</strong> Don’t make excuses, get things done, and translate them to the appropriate nontechnical language.</p>

<p><strong>Keep communicating with the client.</strong> Just as you would <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB122511931313072047.html">manage up</a> with your boss, go out of your way to maintain a good relationship with clients.</p>

<h2 id="development">Development</h2>

<p>Javascript frameworks seem to be the new thing. Client-side frameworks for single page web applications make a lot of sense though, reducing the unnecessary overhead of maintaining the server. I’d definitely like to try <a href="http://meteor.com">Meteor</a>. No jQuery spaghetti.</p>

<p>That being said, a <em>lot</em> more experience with web development this semester through my research project. If I could go back, I would have used a Javascript framework (but that’s what the first major project in a language is for!).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
