<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: taiwan | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/taiwan/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-04-24T15:07:16+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Best Meat and Rice in Taipei: Barbecue Pork Rice 御狀元烤肉飯 (Taipei, Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/meat-and-rice-zhaopaikaoroufan/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-17 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/17/meat-and-rice-zhaopaikaoroufan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>御狀元烤肉飯 (<em>yu zhuang yuan kao rou fan</em>) (“Emperor’s Best Barbecue Pork and Rice” – not sure if
that’s the correct translation) is a meat and rice joint in Taipei near Taipei Main Station.</p>

<p>This was my favorite place to eat in Taiwan. I worked near Taipei Main Station and would eat here
three to four days a week – for lunch <em>and</em> dinner on some days. It’s extremely cheap and very
tasty for meat and rice (and egg and vegetable) lovers.</p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->
</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="signature-dish">Signature Dish</h2>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/zpkrf/signature.jpg" alt="Signature dish: barbecue pork rice (zhao pai kao rou fan)" /></p>

<p>For 79 NT (less than 3 USD), the barbecue pork rice contains:</p>

<ul>
  <li>rice</li>
  <li>fried egg</li>
  <li>garlic cabbage</li>
  <li>pickled vegetables</li>
  <li>barbecue pork</li>
  <li>yummy sauce</li>
</ul>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/zpkrf/with-chicken.jpg" alt="Barbecue pork rice with fried chicken" /></p>

<p>For an extra 6 NT (around 20 cents USD), they will add fried chicken cutlet.</p>

<h2 id="directions">Directions</h2>

<p>The closest subway exit is Taipei Main Station exit M6 (Caesar Park Hotel). The store is located on
Xuchang Street past the Paris Shop.</p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/zpkrf/signpost.jpg" alt="This sign hangs near the entrance" /></p>

<p>It may be helpful to see the <a href="https://goo.gl/maps/uceKr">Google Maps street view</a>.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d3614.6629865749737!2d121.51611240000001!3d25.045508700000003!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x3442a9731d0f5025%3A0x8ee7ca88ac8492f9!2sXuchang+St%2C+Zhongzheng+District%2C+Taipei+City%2C+Taiwan+100!5e0!3m2!1sen!2s!4v1440960795318" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0;" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="menu">Menu</h2>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/zpkrf/menu.jpg" alt="Menu" /></p>

<h3 id="translation">Translation</h3>

<ol>
  <li>Frog rice (<em>pen shui ji rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Pickled vegetables chicken rice (<em>pao cai ji rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Soy sauce chicken leg rice (<em>jiang lu ji tui fan</em>) </li>
  <li>Ka la (cracking?) chicken cutlet rice (<em>ka la ji pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Osaka pork cutlet rice (<em>da ban zhu pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Thai chicken cutlet rice (<em>tai shi ji pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Thai pork cutlet rice (<em>tai shi zhu pai fan</em>)</li>
  <li><strong>Barbecue pork rice (signature dish)</strong> (<em>zhao pai kao rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Pickled vegetables barbecue pork rice (<em>pao cai kao rou fan</em>)</li>
  <li>Combo chicken and pork rice (<em>shuang pin kao rou fan</em>)</li>
</ol>

<p>I’ve only had the barbecue pork and the combo (but I’ve tried it many times).</p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->
</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Yangmingshan Transportation 阳明山 (Taipei, Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/yangmingshan/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-11 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/11/yangmingshan</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is an English guide for transportation to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yangmingshan">Yangmingshan
(阳明山)</a>, a national park north of Taipei, Taiwan. 
Yangmingshan is a popular destination for locals and tourists, containing numerous hiking trails and
hot springs.</p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->
</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="travel-to-yangmingshan">Travel to Yangmingshan</h2>

<p>The easiest way to reach Yangmingshan is by taking the <strong>260 bus from Taipei Main Station</strong>
to the very last stop. <strong>The bus stops outside exit M1.</strong> The second-to-last stop also contains the phrase “Yangmingshan” – make
sure to get off at the final stop.</p>

<p>The 260 bus also runs along North Zhongshan Road (中山北路). It may be more convenient to find a 260
bus stop along this road rather than going to Taipei Main Station.</p>

<p><strong>The fare is about 30 NTD</strong>. If using an Easy Card, swipe the card when going both on and off the bus.</p>

<h2 id="travel-within-yangmingshan">Travel within Yangmingshan</h2>

<p>The internal 108 bus runs on stops within Yangmingshan. This small bus makes stops around the whole
park.</p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->
</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[English Guide to Sun Moon Lake 日月潭 (Taiwan)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/sun-moon-lake/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-10 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/07/10/sun-moon-lake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a guide to transportation, food, activities, and lodging for a Sun Moon Lake trip, based on
my own experiences. My friend and I traveled from Taipei to Sun Moon Lake in July 2015, staying one
night by the lake. </p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->

<!-- more --></p>

<h2 id="traveling-to-sun-moon-lake">Traveling to Sun Moon Lake</h2>

<h3 id="from-taichung">From Taichung</h3>

<p>We traveled from Taichung (台中), since we wanted to explore the city the night before.
Taipei to Taichung is one hour by high speed rail (HSR), two hours by train (TRA), four hours by
bus.</p>

<p>We purchased a package deal for Sun Moon Lake from Nantou Bus Company across from Gancheng station,
which is near the train station. Packages can also be purchased from the Taichung HSR station.</p>

<p>There are <a href="http://www.ntbus.com.tw/en-p-1.html">many options for packages</a>, but the 570 NT package
includes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Round trip bus tickets between Taichung and Sun Moon Lake (383 NT)</li>
  <li>Ferry rides for one day (200 NT)</li>
  <li>Bike rental for two hours from Merida Bikes or one hour from GIANT (200 NT)</li>
  <li>Round trip bus tickets between Shuishe and Xiangshan, two stops at Sun Moon Lake (48 NT)</li>
</ul>

<p>According to my computationally intense calculations, this <strong>saves you 261 NT.</strong> It’s a good deal.</p>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.5 hours<br />
<strong>Price:</strong> 570 NT for package deal (see <a href="http://www.ntbus.com.tw/en-p-1.html">Nantou site</a> for other
options)<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Across from Gancheng station (sells packages), Taichung HSR station (sells packages),
or Taichung TRA station. It stops at Shuishe Pier, the main hub of Sun Moon Lake.  </p>

<h2 id="from-taipei">From Taipei</h2>
<p>I didn’t travel from Taipei, but the <a href="http://www.sunmoonlake.gov.tw/English/TravelInfoEng/BusInfo/TaipeiToSML.htm">King Bus
timetable</a> lists bus
times from Taipei Main Station.  </p>

<p><strong>Type:</strong> Bus<br />
<strong>Duration:</strong> 4 hours<br />
<strong>Price:</strong> 460 NT each way<br />
<strong>Location:</strong> Taipei Bus Station</p>

<p>Miscellaneous: We stayed at a nice and cheap hotel in Taichung, the <a href="https://www.kayak.com/Taichung-Hotels-Moon-Lake-Hotel.2070096.ksp">Moon Lake
Hotel</a> (11 USD per
night). It is less than a kilometer away from the train station.</p>

<p><strong>Type:</strong> Bus  </p>

<h2 id="getting-around">Getting Around</h2>

<h3 id="ferry">Ferry</h3>

<p>The ferry is the most convenient way to cover a lot of ground and hit the main destinations. It has three stops, forming a triangle along the lake. </p>

<ul>
  <li>The first pier is <strong>Shuishe</strong>, the main pier. </li>
  <li>The second pier is <strong>Xuanzang Pier</strong>, and it has a legendary tea egg store that has been run by the same
woman for about fifty years (13 NT per egg). </li>
  <li>The last pier is <strong>Ita Thao</strong>, which has many food stands.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="bike">Bike</h3>

<p>Biking is a scenic way to get around the lake. Details on bike shops can be found
<a href="http://www.sunmoonlake.gov.tw/English/TravelInfoEng/LakeTour/BikeRental.htm">here</a>. See the <strong>Activities</strong> section for more information
about the bikes in the package deal.</p>

<h3 id="bus">Bus</h3>

<p>The Round-the-Lake bus, which goes ‘round the lake, is the main bus. A trip on the bus is more or less 20 NT. An unlimited trip ticket is 80 NT. You can use your EasyCard.</p>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> Wave down the bus drivers as they approach, because they probably won’t stop for you
otherwise.</p>

<h2 id="things-to-try">Things To Try</h2>

<h3 id="food">Food</h3>

<p>Ita Thao has all the good food. Edibles to try:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Pork buns (Ita Thao):</strong> I recommend the stand that has pumpkin pork buns.</li>
  <li><strong>Assam tea (Ita Thao):</strong> Stands advertising Assam tea are everywhere. It’s a type of tea imported
  from India or Japan. It tastes like tea. For some reason (I don’t know because I’m Chinese
  illiterate), it’s famous in the area.</li>
  <li><strong>Chicken stuffed with rice (Ita Thao):</strong> I have no idea what this is called. Look for a stand with deer horns.
  Also, if you don’t like spicy, ask for “no spicy” because even “small spicy” was super spicy.</li>
  <li><strong>Old woman tea eggs (Xuanguan Pier):</strong> These were mentioned above. They’re at the first ferry stop after Shuishe.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="places">Places</h3>

<p>There are many destinations at Sun Moon Lake, but I recommend:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ci’en Pagoda</strong>, a tall building commissioned by Chiang-Kai Shek, has a sweeping view of the lake. 
Sun Moon Lake has hiking trails, but many of them don’t have a nice view of the lake. 
To reach the pagoda, take the round-the-lake bus. Although Ci’en Pagoda is not listed as a stop, it <strong>is</strong>
the second-to-last stop before (I think) Xuanzang Temple. </p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Ita Thao</strong>, an area with many food stands. Because food.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> The bus does not stop at Ci’en Pagoda between 1 and 3 PM, and none of the main
piers are within short walking distance (around 5 km). We tried leaving at 1:30 PM.  Not wanting to
wait around for 1.5 hours, we hitchhiked our way back.</p>

<p><strong>Advice:</strong> Bug your bus driver to stop. Our bus driver was not-too-nice and chose not to stop Ci’en
Pagoda– despite knowing that it was
our destination. You might notice a pattern here involving interactions with bus drivers.</p>

<h3 id="activities">Activities</h3>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Walking</strong>: Self explanatory.</li>
  <li><strong>Biking</strong>: The best activity by far. The package that we did gave us bikes for two hours from Merida Bike, which was enough time to bike
about a third of the lake (going out and coming back to the bike rental shop). Renting bikes for
longer (i.e., to go around the whole lake) costs more, but I’m unsure how much more. Bike shops want bikes back by around 6:30 PM.</li>
  <li><strong>Cable car:</strong> It exists, but I didn’t do it.</li>
  <li><strong>Being ignored by bus drivers:</strong> It exists, and I did do it.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="miscellaneous">Miscellaneous</h3>

<p>None of these were that interesting to us, but if you have more time, this is an incomplete list of
other activities in the area:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Aboriginal Culture Village (<a href="http://www.nine.com.tw/webe/html/information/">link</a>):</strong> This sounds like a village for cultural edification, but it turns
  out it’s actually an amusement park.</li>
  <li><strong>Puli:</strong> It’s a town.</li>
  <li><strong>Cingjing Farm (<a href="http://www.cingjing.gov.tw/en/about/">link</a>):</strong> It’s a farm. It’s about 40 minutes from Sun Moon Lake.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="lodging">Lodging</h2>

<p>Because Sun Moon Lake is a popular tourist destination, lodging is relatively expensive. </p>

<p>Super secret hacker budget stay: <strong>Naluisland House</strong>. This place is so secret that it doesn’t show up
on <a href="http://kayak.com">Kayak</a> or have reviews on
<a href="http://www.tripadvisor.com/Hotel_Review-g304160-d6453391-Reviews-Naluisland_House-Nantou.html">TripAdvisor</a>. 
You can book through Agoda or Ctrip.</p>

<p>We shared a room with two queen sized beds between four people, and it came out to about <strong>450 NT
per person</strong> (15
USD in July 2015). Our room was sufficient for a one night stay. There are rooms with four beds for
a little more. Some rooms also have private bathrooms, which costs a little more as well. </p>

<p>To get to Naluisland House, take the ferry or bus to Ita Thao, which is one of the major destinations of Sun Moon
Lake. However, buses and ferries close around 5:30 PM – be very careful to get to Ita Thao before
then. We learned that a taxi from Shuishe, the main port, costs about 500 NT (try negotiating).</p>

<p>I’m not sure if the owner speaks English, but she was very helpful. </p>

<p><!-- I have a [travel-related YouTube
channel](https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLtD-FIua473Cf6Ylh3PeoEmoq3c6BJH0S) on life in Taiwan.
Subscribe! -->
</p>

<p><em>Last updated: July 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
