<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: internships | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/internships/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-17T17:34:36-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[louisrli@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tips for Computer Science Internship Interviews]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/01/12/guide-to-internship-interviews/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-12 00:00:00 -0500</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2014/01/12/guide-to-internship-interviews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h1>Introduction</h1>

<p>This post is meant to help computer science undergraduates looking for a software engineering internship for the summer. In particular, this post covers two things:</p>

<ol>
<li>What are most internship interviews like?</li>
<li>How should I prepare for them?</li>
</ol>


<p>From the beginning of September 2013 to the beginning of January 2014 (around 16 weeks), I did a lot of interviewing: 20 technical interviews, four recruiter interviews, two coding challenges, one product manager interview, and one trader interview (involuntarily moved from software engineering). I definitely didn&rsquo;t get offers from all of them. I did, however, learn a lot about what internship interviews are generally like.</p>

<p>Applying to internships can be daunting. I hope this post can address some of the questions that I commonly see on Quora or Reddit <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/cscareerquestions">cscareerquestions</a>.</p>

<p>Finally, note that I mostly interviewed with medium to large &ldquo;mainstream&rdquo; companies; your mileage may vary.</p>

<p>TODO: link to other page</p>

<h1>The three types of internship interviews</h1>

<h3>1. The programming interview</h3>

<p><strong>Who:</strong> All companies, but usually medium to large companies</p>

<p><strong>What:</strong> This is how most people envision computer science interviews: you&rsquo;re asked one or more programming questions, and you implement the answers on a site like <a href="http://stypi.com">Stypi</a> or <a href="http://collabedit.com">Collabedit</a>.</p>

<p>I would roughly divide into two parts:
1. Easy list interview questions
2. Data structure questions</p>

<p><strong>How to prepare:</strong>
&ndash; Read Programming Interviews Exposed
&ndash; Check Glassdoor
&ndash; Data structures: Know linked lists, doubly linked lists, queues, stacks, hash tables.
&ndash; Algorithms: know depth- and breadth-first search and figuring out complexity.</p>

<h3>2. The &ldquo;what you&rsquo;ve done&rdquo; interview</h3>

<p>When:</p>

<p>My experience with nearly all of the very small companies that I interviewed with, as well as the internship that I did two summers ago. Medium-sized companies or small companies might use these totally nontechnical interviews. They ask you about your sideprojects. No formal technical questions but they get an idea of how experienced you are. Usually I had to talk about &hellip;</p>

<p>How to prepare:</p>

<p>Be prepared to talk in-depth about any jobs and projects on your resume. Particularly, you&rsquo;ll want to have:
&ndash; What is the project?
&ndash; What was the scope of the project? (i.e., how much time, how big was it)
&ndash; What did you learn?
&ndash; What were some of the challenges in the project?</p>

<h3>3. The language-specific interview</h3>

<p>When:
You&rsquo;re interviewing for a specific team. Some short quiz questions about the language. Questions about your experience with the language. What was a technical problem you had in the language?</p>

<p>How to prepare:</p>

<blockquote><p>What makes <language> different from other languages?</p>

<p>If you had to change something in <language>, what would you change?</p>

<p>I see on your resume that you used <language> at this job.</p>

<p>Tell me about a technical challenge that you had when you were working on a project in <this language>.</p></blockquote>

<p>I had four interviews &mdash; two with Apple&rsquo;s iOS Safari j</p>

<h1>Beginning the interview</h1>

<blockquote><p>Tell me about yourself.</p></blockquote>

<p>Most interviewers ask some variant of this at the beginning. Sometimes, they&rsquo;ll instead ask you about a specific project, as in <em>the accomplishments interview</em>. Other companies don&rsquo;t care, especially the bigger ones, and they&rsquo;ll dive right into the technical part of the interview. Either way, you&rsquo;ll very likely to be asked to give a short pitch about yourself.</p>

<p>For example, my pitch went something like this, which was usually tweaked depending on the company or role that I was interviewing with:</p>

<blockquote><p>TODO: insert pitch here</p></blockquote>

<h2>Miscellaneous</h2>

<p>be nice: hey, how are you doing?</p>

<h1>Ending the interview</h1>

<blockquote><p>Do you have any questions for me?</p></blockquote>

<h2>Miscellaneous</h2>

<p>In my experience, if the interviewer starts talking about how much responsibility interns have <em>and</em> you didn&rsquo;t explicitly ask about it &mdash; the interview probably went well.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve read a few things on the internet about asking your interviewer how they felt the interview went. I don&rsquo;t feel comfortable with it, but if you feel like you&rsquo;re struggling a lot on interviews, it may be worth a shot.</p>

<h1>Odds and ends</h1>

<p>Shape Security &mdash; emphasis on coursework
Yelp first round &mdash; random quiz questions
random questions about how you would design a system</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
