<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: turkish | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/turkish/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2023-03-01T11:20:22+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Understanding the Turkish Accusative]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2021/01/14/understanding-the-turkish-accusative/"/>
    <updated>2021-01-14 00:00:00 +0100</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2021/01/14/understanding-the-turkish-accusative</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<style>
blockquote {
  font-style: unset;
}

blockquote hr {
  margin: 0.3em 0;
}

blockquote p:first-child {
  font-size: 12px;
  border-bottom: 1px solid #ddd;
}

/* In case we want to bold the example headers later. */
blockquote p:first-child strong {
  font-weight: unset;
}

blockquote p {
  margin-top: 0.3em !important;
  margin-bottom: 0.3em !important;
}

</style>

<p>The purpose of this post is to answer: “when do I use or not use the Turkish
accusative?” Most resources on the accusative describe it as a case ending
applied to a definite direct object. Some say it’s the equivalent of when you
use “the” in English. I found these definitions to be vague and often actively
misleading.</p>

<p>Much of this knowledge is thanks to the <a href="https://discord.me/turkceogrenelim">Türkçe Öğrenelim
Discord</a>. Feel free to join the community
and support them on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/letslearnturkish">Patreon</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h1 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites</h1>

<p>This post is not intended for complete beginners of Turkish grammar. It will not
explain any constructions or cover the basics of the accusative; there are ample
other resources.</p>

<h1 id="why-this-post">Why this post?</h1>

<p>Finding a comprehensive resource for the accusative tops the list of
my frustrations in learning Turkish (thankfully the Discord exists). I haven’t found a single public resource on the internet that goes in-depth into accusative usage. All of them try to summarize it in a single sentence by
providing some type of rule or guideline – this guideline is usually ambiguous
or incomplete. That is to say, <strong>if your goal is to use the accusative in all
scenarios without making mistakes</strong>, no existing online resource achieves this.</p>

<p>My hope is that this article will get you close to there, though I can’t promise
that I know Turkish well enough to cover all cases. The most thorough resource that I know would be the discussions in <em>Turkish: A
  Comprehensive Grammar</em>. I’d say, however, that one gets
  <em>too</em> detailed at some point. It’s worth a read if you care about this though.</p>

<h2 id="examples-of-incomplete-accusative-definitions">Examples of incomplete accusative definitions</h2>

<p>Below are some examples from different sources in defining the accusative.
I’ve included these to contrast how trusting these definitions can lead learners
astray. Thinking of the accusative as the case for
definite direct objects is not incorrect, but it certainly isn’t comprehensive. <strong>The
purpose of this article is to cover cases where the “direct object” definition
does not suffice.</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><em>“Nouns that are affected by the action of a verb use the accusative case.”</em>
(<a href="https://www.turkishaholic.com/lessons/free/turkish-case-markers/">Turkishaholic</a>)</li>
  <li><em>“In Turkish, the direct object gets a suffix when it is definite. The direct
object is definite when it refers to a specific object or a specific
collection of objects that is known to the addressee.”</em>
(<a href="https://elon.io/learn-turkish/lesson/the-accusative-case-suffix#:~:text=In%20Turkish%2C%20the%20definite%20direct,to%20prevent%20two%20consecutive%20vowels.">elon.io</a>).</li>
  <li><em>“This is used for direct objects - the object that is receiving an action (the
apple begin eaten, the wine being drunk, etc.). Note that cases only apply
for things that have “the” in front of them in English (as the nominative
covers ones that don’t).”</em> (<a href="https://duolingo.fandom.com/wiki/Turkish_Skill:Accusative">Duolingo Wiki – ew</a>)</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="with-plurals">With plurals</h1>

<p>The definitions above all seem to apply that the accusative provides
specificity, but with plurals, its role is reversed. For most cases, adding the
accusative makes a plural general; the lack of accusative makes it specific.</p>

<p>To put it another way, to express a general group, there are two options: plural
with the accusative or singular nominative.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Plural accusative vs singular nominative</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Insanları</strong> tanımayı seviyorum.<br />
<strong>Insan</strong> tanımayı seviyorum.<br />
I like to get to know people (people, as a general group).</p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>Gömlekleri</strong> sever misin?<br />
<strong>Gömlek</strong> sever misin?<br />
Would you / do you like shirts (generally speaking of shirts)?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A plural without the accusative is specific:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Plural without accusative, specific</strong></p>

  <p>Dün ona yeni <strong>gömlekler</strong> aldık.<br />
Yesterday, we bought some new (specific) shirts for him.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, there are some cases where plural accusative is specific rather than
general. I’m actually not sure what the rule is that distinguishes the example
above or below. If you know, then please let me know, and I’ll update this section.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Plural accusative, specific</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Gömlekleri</strong> sevdin mi?<br />
Did you like the (specific) shirts?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Overall, this counters the oversimplified definition that the accusative is used
to mark a definite object. The definition of the accusative as parallel to
English “the” is especially egregious to me.</p>

<p>To close it off, as expected by the simple definitions of accusative, using it
with the singular makes the object specific, not general (note that
there are again exceptions that are so detailed it’s not worth mentioning here, see <em>Turkish: A Comprehensive Grammar</em> 22.4.3):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Singular accusative vs singular nominative</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Gömleği</strong> sever misin?<br />
Would you / do you like the (specific) shirt?</p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>Gömlek</strong> sever misin?<br />
Would you / do you like shirts (generally speaking of shirts)?</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://discordapp.com/channels/337748083855327232/337749314036039692/710448813524910291">This
discussion</a>
on the Turkish Discord is useful (and this section is borrowed from there).</p>

<h1 id="with-numbers">With numbers</h1>

<p>Most beginners of Turkish learn the rule, “no accusatives with bir or numbers.”
However, this turns out, again, to be an oversimplification.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Indefinite numbered items</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Bir çocuk</strong> gördüm.<br />
I saw <strong>a child</strong>.</p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>Iki kitap</strong> aldım.<br />
I bought <strong>two books</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="referring-to-specific-objects-in-context">Referring to specific objects in context</h2>

<p>The accusative can be used with numbers when referencing a specific object that
is previously referred to in context.</p>

<p>For example, when you delete a message on Facebook, it says: “Bir mesajı
sildin.” You had previously clicked this message; you know exactly which message
is being deleted.</p>

<p>As explained on the Turkish Discord:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Accusative with bir</strong></p>

  <p>Bir <strong>mesaj</strong> sildin<br />
You deleted a message (just any message)</p>
  <hr />

  <p>Bir <strong>mesajı</strong> sildin<br />
You deleted a message (that specific one)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Another example adapted from <em>Turkish: A Comprehensive Grammar</em>, 14.3.3.2, uses
the accusative when the books were referenced and known to the
listener as part of the first sentence, which can be thought of as a form of
definiteness.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Referencing items in context</strong></p>

  <p>Kitaplarımı bana verdi, ama <strong>iki kitabı</strong> unuttu.<br />
He gave me my books, but he forgot <strong>two of them</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="with-the-possessive-but-not-compound-nouns">With the possessive (but not compound nouns)</h2>

<p>When using the possessive with a number, it will still take the accusative.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Possessive, number, and accusative</strong></p>

  <p>Bir <strong>kıtabımı</strong> ona verdi.<br />
I gave him a book of mine.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Note that without the possessive, there is no accusative:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Non-possessive with number</strong></p>

  <p>Bir <strong>kitap</strong> ona verdi.<br />
I gave him a book.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="with-question-words">With question words</h1>

<p>The accusative form of question words such as ne (“what”) and kim (“who”) will
occasionally be seen. This can be used more specifically in place of a word that
would normally take that spot in the sentence with the accusative. It often
makes sense in response to somebody.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>Ne yaptın?<br />
What did you do?</p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>Neyi</strong> yaptın?<br />
You did <strong>what</strong>?</p>
  <hr />

  <p>Kimi aradın?<br />
Who did you call?</p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>A</strong>: Zaten biliyorum.<br />
I already know.<br />
<strong>B</strong>: <strong>Neyi</strong> biliyorsun?<br />
<strong>What (exactly)</strong> do you know?<br />
<strong>A</strong>: Bu bilgiyi biliyorum.<br />
I already know this information.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In the last example, I don’t think that saying “ne biliyorsun” would necessarily be
incorrect, but neyi offers a certain amount of precision, in response to the
verb (biliyorum) that speaker A used.</p>

<h1 id="with-verbal-nouns">With verbal nouns</h1>

<p>For example, when using any verbal nouns, such as <strong>yüzme</strong> or <strong>yaptığın</strong>,
these will take the accusative if the verb requires it. As far as I know, these
will not appear without the accusative (again, under the “direct object
definition”, this was confusing to me. What does it mean for a verbal noun to be
definite?)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Yüzmeyi</strong> biliyorum.<br />
I know how to swim / I know <strong>swimming</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Almost all Turkish learners will learn how to express wanting to do a verb. This
could be considered to an exception to the verbal noun accusatives above (since
the infinite is considered a noun). However, there’s an exception to the
exception!</p>

<p>When another word appears between the infinite and istemek, then it takes on the
accusative -mA form rather than the infinite.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>istemek can take the accusative</strong></p>

  <p>Seni dövmek istiyorum.<br />
I want to beat you up.</p>
  <hr />

  <p>Seni dövme<strong>yi</strong> <strong>çok</strong> istiyorum.<br />
I really want to beat you up.</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="accusative-and-distance-from-the-verb">Accusative and distance from the verb</h1>

<p>This is actually a more general rule for the above. A word cannot be in the
nominative and far from the verb. For example, observe the insertion of the word
<em>çok</em> below and in the previous example.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Wrong</strong></p>

  <p>Kedi çok seven bir köpek<br />
A dog that loves cats</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Correct</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Kedi</strong> seven bir köpek<br />
A dog that loves <strong>cats</strong></p>
  <hr />

  <p><strong>Kediyi</strong> çok seven bir köpek<br />
A dog that really loves cats</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="you-just-have-to-know">“You just have to know”</h1>

<p>There are some cases where you just have to know that the accusative is
required or not. For example, as a foreigner, one of your most common phrases:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>A common phrase</strong></p>

  <p>Türkçe biliyor musun?<br />
Do you know Turkish?</p>
  <hr />

  <p>Türkçe biliyorum.<br />
I know Turkish.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It does <em>not</em> use the accusative. Why? I’m not sure if there’s a sensible
explanation. To me, it makes more sense that Turkish is definite here; it refers
to a specific language, Turkish. But this is simply the way it is: there is no
accusative.</p>

<p>In another example put forth in the Turkish Discord, the opposite is true with
the verb <em>sevmek</em>. The accusative would be
used here this time to refer to the Turkish language specifically. It would be
incorrect to drop the accusative here.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Accusative with sevmek</strong></p>

  <p>Türkçeyi seviyorum.
I love the Turkish language.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>But it can also be used without the accusative:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>An explanation in the Discord</strong></p>

  <p>“Türkçe seviyorum” could be used in a context where you like doing something IN Turkish. Like “in which language do you like watching series?” You could say “Türkçe seviyorum.”</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h1>

<p>This is by no means meant to completely cover the cases of using or not using
the accusative, but hopefully it clarifies specific situations where the
“definite direct object” definition is insufficient.</p>

<p>Finally, even if you don’t get these correct in speech or writing, don’t sweat
it: what you want to express will probably be understood. Language is
approximate.  People definitely aren’t writing in perfect grammar on the
internet – go check out some Turkish YouTube comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fiilimsi: Turkish Verbal Nouns, Adjectives, and Adverbs]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/04/20/turkish-fiilimsi-verbal-derivatives/"/>
    <updated>2020-04-20 00:00:00 +0200</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/04/20/turkish-fiilimsi-verbal-derivatives</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<style>
blockquote {
  font-style: unset;
}

blockquote hr {
  margin: 0.3em 0;
}

blockquote p:first-child {
  font-size: 12px;
  border-bottom: 1px solid #ddd;
}

/* In case we want to bold the example headers later. */
blockquote p:first-child strong {
  font-weight: unset;
}

blockquote p {
  margin-top: 0.3em !important;
  margin-bottom: 0.3em !important;
}

</style>

<p>This post talks about the concept of “fiilimsi”, which are nouns, adjectives, or
adverbs derived from verbs. In English, for example, these include gerunds
(“<em>Running</em> is fun”) or participle adjectives (“The dog <em>that I saw</em>”).</p>

<p>This post is not intended to be a comprehensive resource of all fiilimsi.
There are three categories of fiilimsi:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>isim-fiil</strong>: verbal noun</li>
  <li><strong>sıfat-fiil</strong>: verbal adjective</li>
  <li><strong>zarf-fiil</strong>: verbal adverb</li>
</ol>

<p>There’s a noticeable lack of English language resources on the internet about
certain Turkish language topics. There’s a few articles about verbal derivations
but only with minimal details. I hope this post fills that niche.</p>

<p>Almost all of this material was derived from a lesson on the <a href="https://discord.me/turkceogrenelim">Türkçe Öğrenelim
Discord</a>. Feel free to join the community
and support them on <a href="https://www.patreon.com/letslearnturkish">Patreon</a>.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h1 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites</h1>
<p>This post is not intended for complete beginners of Turkish grammar. Fiilimsi
builds on many of the foundations of Turkish grammar. This post assumes
prerequisite familiarity in the following topics,
and as such will not be explaining any of the following in example
sentences:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Possessive</li>
  <li>Buffer letters, consonant mutation, vowel harmony</li>
  <li>Infinitive form</li>
  <li>Subjects and objects in Turkish</li>
</ul>

<p>There are sentence examples and grammar derivations that utilize the following,
though it’s possible to grasp the basic idea without a strong understanding of
these:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Simple present tense, past tense</li>
  <li>Dative, locative, accusative cases</li>
  <li>Future tense</li>
  <li>Reported past tense</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="isim-fiil-verbal-nouns">Isim-fiil: Verbal nouns</h1>

<h2 id="-makmek-infinitive-as-a-subject">-mak/mek: Infinitive as a subject</h2>

<p>Infinitives are the “dictionary form” of a verb ending with <strong>-mak/mek</strong>, e.g.,
bakmak (to look).</p>

<h3 id="usage">Usage</h3>
<p>The verbal noun infinitive form:</p>

<ul>
  <li>used as subject</li>
  <li>cannot be <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Declension">declined</a> – that is, no
suffixes are added to it</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uqIEiUv1bVQ">a line from this song</a>)</p>

  <p><strong>Eğlenmek</strong> güzel şey.<br />
<strong>To have fun</strong> is a beautiful thing / <strong>having fun</strong> is a beautiful thing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It should be noted that there are many other uses of the infinitive, but here
we’re talking only about its usage as a noun derived from a verb.</p>

<h2 id="-mame-gerund-form">-ma/me: Gerund form</h2>

<p>The gerund form is constructed by adding <strong>-ma/-me</strong> to the verb root
(alternatively, one can think of simply removing the <strong>k</strong> from the infinitive).</p>

<ul>
  <li>yap<strong>ma</strong> (doing)</li>
  <li>bak<strong>ma</strong> (looking)</li>
  <li>sor<strong>ma</strong> (sormak)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="usage-1">Usage</h3>
<p>The gerund form:</p>

<ul>
  <li>used as object</li>
  <li>can be declined</li>
</ul>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>Kitap <strong>okuma</strong>yı seviyorum.<br />
I love reading books.</p>

  <p>Dans <strong>etme</strong>ye başladım.<br />
I started dancing.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: The <em>-ma/-me</em> suffix is also used for the negative conjugation, but do
not confuse it with the gerund construction. They can actually stack, for
example <strong>anla-ma-ma</strong> is the noun “not understanding” (<strong>anlamak</strong> – to
understand).</p>

<h3 id="declension-exception-ablative">Declension exception: ablative</h3>
<p>There is one exception where we use the infinitive instead; for the ablative
form (<strong>-dan/den</strong>), we still use the infinitive form. This also violates the
“no declension infinitive” rule. In the example below, eğlenmekten is the
object.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Eğlenmekten</strong> keyif alırım.<br />
I enjoy having fun.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Likely this is because the gerund form causes ambiguity with
<strong>-meden/-madan</strong> (eğlenmeden), which is also a verbal adverb suffix.</p>

<h3 id="declension-exception-locative">Declension exception: locative</h3>

<p>The locative can also be used interchangeably in some contexts. In the example
below, both are valid uses of the verbal noun as an object.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>Böyle yap<strong>mada</strong> sorun yok.<br />
Böyle yap<strong>makta</strong> sorun yok.<br />
There is no problem in doing this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>However, you cannot use the genitive suffixes with the infinitive, so for the
example sentence below, there is only one valid construction (yap-ma-n-da, with
the n coming from the second-person genitive).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>Böyle yap<strong>manda</strong> sorun yok.<br />
There is no problem in your doing this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>To summarize, you cannot use the accusative, dative, or genitive suffixes with
the infinitive, but you can use the ablative and locative.</p>

<h2 id="native-speaking-gerund-and-infinitive">Native speaking: gerund and infinitive</h2>
<p>There’s a tricky exception that’s technically not correct but will be seen in
daily speech. People add (gerund + possessed) suffixes as a way of
creating a verbal noun in lieu of <strong>both the gerund and infinitive forms above</strong>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Subject example</strong></p>

  <p>Denizde <strong>yüzmek</strong> eğlenceli. (gramatically correct)<br />
Denizde <strong>yüzmesi</strong> eğlenceli. (seen in daily speech)<br />
<strong>Swimming</strong> in the sea is fun.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this example, we have <strong>yüz-me-si</strong>, which adds the gerund and possessed
suffixes, respectively.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Object example</strong></p>

  <p>Denizde <strong>yüzmeyi</strong> seviyorum.<br />
Denizde <strong>yüzmesini</strong> seviyorum.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In this example, we have <strong>yüz-me-si-n-i</strong>, which adds the gerund, possessed,
-n- possessed buffer, and accusative suffixes, respectively.</p>

<h2 id="-ısişuşüş-the-way-of">-ıs/iş/uş/üş: “the way of”</h2>

<p><strong>DISCLAIMER</strong>: “the way of” is not always the exact meaning of this suffix; it
can vary phrase by phrase. However, it can give a general idea.</p>

<ul>
  <li>yap<strong>ış</strong> (the way of doing)</li>
  <li>bak<strong>ış</strong> (the way of looking)</li>
  <li>sor<strong>uş</strong> (the way of asking)</li>
</ul>

<p>There are two words derived in this manner that are very common on signs: giriş
and cıkış (entrance and exit).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>Bana <strong>bakışını</strong> sevmiyorum. <br />
I don’t like the way you looked at me.</p>

  <p>Onun <strong>çıkışını</strong> gördün mü? <br />
Did you see how he left? / Did you see the way he left?</p>
</blockquote>

<h1 id="sıfat-fiil-verbal-adjectives">Sıfat-fiil: Verbal adjectives</h1>

<h2 id="-yan-en-subject-participles">-(y)an/-en: Subject participles</h2>
<p>In English, you’ll see this grammar concept associated with the terms relative
clause and participle.</p>

<p>We use these to form a verbal adjective that describes a noun.
It is called the subject participle because the described noun is the subject
performing the action.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>evime gel<strong>en</strong> misafir<br />
the guest <strong>who comes / is coming / came</strong> to my house</p>

  <p>uyu<strong>yan</strong> adam <br />
the man <strong>who sleeps / is sleeping / slept</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="negation">Negation</h3>

<p>Negation works as one might expect.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>uyu<strong>mayan</strong> adam<br />
the man <strong>who is not sleeping</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: In practice, the -y- buffer will always be there since <strong>-ma/me</strong> end
with a vowel.</p>

<h3 id="tense">Tense</h3>
<p>The tense is implied by context. It can take the present continuous, simple
past, and simple present (aka wide present) tenses.</p>

<h2 id="-dik-and-possessor-suffix-object-participles">-dIk and possessor suffix: Object participles</h2>

<p>Recall that <strong>-dIk notation</strong> indicates it could be <strong>-dık -dik -duk -dük</strong>. The
d also mutates to t when appropriate (consonant mutation).</p>

<p>This adjective is called the object participle, because the noun described by
the verbal adjective is the object of the verb. Because of this, we also need to
specify who is performing the action of the verb; this is done by the possessor
ending.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples</strong></p>

  <p>oku<strong>duğum</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that I read / am reading / read (the past)</strong></p>

  <p>oku<strong>duğun</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that you read (…same tenses)</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Tip</strong>: In practice, the <strong>k</strong> in <strong>-dIk</strong> almost always mutates to a <strong>ğ</strong> since all
of the possessor endings start with a vowel. The only exception is when the
plural is added to onlar, as below.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (with onlar)</strong></p>

  <p>onların <strong>okuduğu</strong> kitap<br />
onların <strong>okudukları</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that they read / am reading / read (past)</strong></p>

  <p>oku<strong>duğun</strong> kitap<br />
the book <strong>that you read (…same tenses)</strong></p>
  <h3 id="negation-1">Negation</h3>
  <p>Negation again works as one would expect.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>bak<strong>madığım</strong> adam<br />
the man <strong>who I am not looking at</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="tense-1">Tense</h3>
<p>The tense is implied by context. It can take the present continuous, simple
past, and simple present (aka wide present) tenses.</p>

<h3 id="usage-with-sonra">Usage with sonra</h3>

<p>You will also see this suffix used with the word sonra (“after”), but without the
possessed ending.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>O kahvaltı yap<strong>tıktan sonra</strong> bir sigara içer.<br />
After eating breakfast, he smokes a cigarette.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Notably, it is not symmetrically used with önce, which uses the <strong>-mAdAn</strong>
suffix with verbs with our previously described gerund form.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Uyu<strong>madan önce</strong> kitap okurum.<br />
Before sleeping, I read books.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="future-and-reported-past-participles">Future and reported past participles</h2>
<p>Building upon the two forms we learned above, we can create both object and
subject participles using the suffixes of both the future and reported past tenses. These tenses
won’t be covered here, so this section can be skipped if the reader is not
familiar with them.</p>

<p>Understanding of these derivations follow easily with an understanding of the
<strong>-acak/ecek</strong> future suffixes and the <strong>-mış/miş/muş/müş</strong> reported past
suffixes.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (future tense)</strong></p>

  <p>konuşacak adam<br />
the man who will speak</p>

  <p>konuşacağı adam<br />
the man he/she will talk to</p>

  <p>adam konuşacak<br />
the man will talk (normal future tense)</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (reported past tense)</strong></p>

  <p>kitap <strong>okumuş</strong> çocuk<br />
the child <strong>who (apparently) read</strong> books</p>

  <p><strong>boşanmış</strong> kadın<br />
the woman <strong>who (apparently) was divorced</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="other-verbal-adjectives">Other verbal adjectives</h2>
<p>There are a bunch of other verbal adjectives, often with different meaning.
There’s a <a href="https://www.dilbilgisi.net/fiilimsi-konu-anlatimi/">Turkish page</a>
containing some of them here, but they’re less important and often vary in
meaning phrase-by-phrase.</p>

<h1 id="zarf-fiil-verbal-adverbs">Zarf-fiil: Verbal adverbs</h1>
<p>This is not intended to comprehensively cover all zarf-fiil, but it covers a
few of the most common ones.</p>

<h2 id="-eliali-since">-eli/ali: Since</h2>
<p>This suffix means “since” in the sense of time passing (not “since” as in the
word “because”, which can also be used in English). It can only be used events
happening since a specific time duration.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Okuldan <strong>geleli</strong> beş saat oldu.<br />
It has been five hours <strong>since I came</strong> from the school.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If you want to express the concept of “since” relative to an event, then the
verb is repeated in the past tense.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Türkiye’ye <strong>geldim geleli</strong> birçok kişiyle tanıştım.<br />
I’ve met many people <strong>since I came</strong> to Turkey.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="subject-of-the-since-clause">Subject of the since-clause</h3>
<p>The subject is optional, but it can be used to clarify the subject of the since-clause when it cannot be derived from context.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Examples (with pronoun)</strong></p>

  <p><strong>Sen</strong> okuldan gel<strong>eli</strong> beş saat oldu.<br />
It has been five hours since <strong>you</strong> came from the school.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="-madanmeden-before-with-önce--without">-madan/meden: before (with önce) / without</h2>

<h3 id="meaning-without">Meaning “without”</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Maske <strong>takmadan</strong> dışarı çıkmak yasaktır.<br />
It is forbidden to go out <strong>without wearing</strong> a mask.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="meaning-before">Meaning “before”</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Ben polisi aramadan buradan ayrıl.<br />
Leave this place before I call the police.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="with-önce">With önce</h4>
<p>In the section on -dIk, it was explained that “(verb + dIktAn) sonra” could be used to say something that happened after an action. The -madan/meden suffix serves is often seen with <em>önce</em>. With or without önce is essentially the same (to my understanding).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Çalışmaya başla<strong>madan önce</strong> bir kahve içerim.<br />
Before studying, I drink a coffee.</p>
</blockquote>

<h4 id="-madan-meden-modifying-a-negative-verb">-madan/-meden modifying a negative verb</h4>
<p>There is a second construction using -madan/-meden. In this one, if the modified verb is negative, then the adverb happens first in the sequence of events. This is a bit confusing to explain but easily clarified with equivalent examples. Note the negative suffix in the verbs below.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Kitap <strong>okumadan</strong> yat<strong>ma</strong>dı.<br />
Kitap okudu ve yattı. (equivalent)<br />
He read a book before he slept.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A direct English translation can be a bit weird due to the negatives.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Question example</strong></p>

  <p>Siz ne <strong>yapmadan</strong> okula gitmiyorsunuz?<br />
What do you <strong>do before</strong> going to school?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The example could literally be translated as, “you don’t go to school before
doing what?”</p>

<p><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=V_bC-hn7cC8">This video</a> (in Turkish, albeit slow
Turkish) is a good explanation of this negative construction. Credit goes to
this video for the examples above.</p>

<h2 id="-ar--maz---er--mez-as-soon-as">-ar -maz / -er -mez: as soon as</h2>
<p>Note that the title isn’t precisely correct, the set of suffixes is the same as
those used in the simple present tense, which has a ruleset not within the scope
of this article. One can think of this construction as simply the positive and
negative simple present tense third person forms in succession.</p>

<p>Like -eli/ali, the subject is implied by context, but can optionally be
clarified by a pronoun.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>(Biz) <strong>Dışarıya çıkar çıkmaz</strong> yağmur başladı.<br />
<strong>As soon as we went out,</strong> it started to rain.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example constructions</strong></p>

  <p>yapar yapmaz<br />
gelir gelmez<br />
görür görmez</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="-yarakerek-by">-(y)arak/erek: “by”</h2>
<p>This adverb indicates that something was achieved in a certain manner.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Türkçe <strong>öğrenerek</strong> ne yapmayı planlıyorsun?<br />
What do you plan to do <strong>by learning</strong> Turkish?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>A good way to remember this is the word <strong>bilerek</strong>, which means “on purpose.”
But with the literal translation of the suffix, it would mean “by knowing.”</p>

<h2 id="negation-2">Negation</h2>
<p>Simply add -ma/-me with a y buffer. For example, <strong>istemeyerek</strong>
(unintentionally, reluctantly, “by not wanting”).</p>

<h2 id="-ıpipupüp-two-actions-in-succession">-ıp/ip/up/üp: two actions in succession</h2>
<p>Again, notice that the subject is implied in the example sentence below. The
suffixed verb is the one that occurs first.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Konuyu <strong>anlatıp pratik</strong> yapacağız.<br />
We will explain the subject and then do practice.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Usually, there is only one usage of -ip in a sentence.</p>

<h3 id="-ip-durmak-idiom">-ip durmak: idiom</h3>
<p><strong>-ip durmak</strong> means to keep doing something all the time.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Example</strong></p>

  <p>Öksürüp duruyor.<br />
He’s constantly coughing.</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="difference-from-sonradan">Difference from sonradan</h3>
<p>Sonradan (“afterwards”) can ostensibly express the same set of sentences, but
the connotation is slightly different. With -ip, the implication is that one
thing happened very quickly after another, while with sonradan, the time gap
could be wider.</p>

<h2 id="further-reference">Further reference</h2>
<p>The end of Unit 10 in <em>The Delights of Learning Turkish</em> is a decent English
language resource for these verbal adverbs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
