<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: albania | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/albania/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-01T22:05:30+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[louisrli@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Tirana to Durres / Schkoder (Albania)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-31 00:00:00 +0200</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains bus directions based on my travels in Albania in August 2015. 
Durres is a coastal city around thirty minutes away, containing
ferries to Italy and beaches. </p>

<p>Schkoder is a historical city around 1.25 to 1.75 hours away,
depending on traffic. It is a northern border city with bus transfers to Ulcinj, Montenegro. </p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Confirm these
directions. Two years ago, the bus to Schkoder was at a different location, and some of the
directions that I found were outdated.</p>

<h2 id="directions-to-the-bus-stop">Directions to the bus stop</h2>

<p>The Google Maps diagram below shows the bus stop, which is in the roundabout of Karl Topia Square.
It shouldn’t be too hard to find the correct bus: each bus has a person shouting its destination.  </p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2995.868120776664!2d19.804230999999994!3d41.333481!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zNDHCsDIwJzAwLjUiTiAxOcKwNDgnMTUuMiJF!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1441137271939" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="bus">Bus</h2>

<p>The buses, known as <em>furgons</em>, are more akin to vans or cars. For an afternoon bus to Durres, I took
a van that fit approximately 15 people. For a 7 AM bus to Schkoder, the vehicle was someone’s
five-seat Volkswagen. Don’t be worried if it just seems like you’re getting in someone’s car (you
are).</p>

<p>The buses don’t leave until they are full or almost full. For Durres, this seems to be approximately
every thirty minutes. For Schkoder, this seems to be approximately every hour. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/tiranabus/bus.jpg" alt="Vans that will take you through beautiful Albania" /></p>

<h2 id="fare">Fare</h2>

<p>In August 2015, the fare for each direction was:</p>

<ul>
  <li>150 lek to Durres</li>
  <li>500 lek to Schkoder</li>
</ul>

<p>The drivers take euro. If you want to get rid of some remaining lek, they also take euro-lek mix.</p>

<p>Enjoy the Albanian music on the drive!</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
