<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: albania | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/albania/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-03T21:33:55+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[louisrli@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Tirana to Ulcinj / Budva / Kotor]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/tirana-kotor/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-01 00:00:00 +0200</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/09/01/tirana-kotor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article describes directions from Tirana, Albania to Ulcinj / Budva / Kotor, Montenegro by bus,
based on my travels in August 2015. It is possible
to start early and arrive in Kotor by the afternoon, but be prepared to wake up early to ride four
buses. </p>

<p>I caught the
first bus at 7:00 and arrived in Kotor around 14:00. </p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="leg-1-tirana-to-schkoder">Leg 1: Tirana to Schkoder</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> about 1.25 hrs to 1.75 hrs, depending on traffic</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> 500 lek (about €2)</p>

<p>See the <a href="/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania/">Tirana to Schkoder article</a>.</p>

<h2 id="leg-2-schkoder-to-ulcinj">Leg 2: Schkoder to Ulcinj</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> About 1.25 hours, depending on border control</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €5</p>

<p>The buses (vans) are near the fountain at the city center. Ask around for
Schkoder if nobody is shouting, or ask the driver from Tirana. I asked the driver from Tirana, who
showed me to the next van.
The driver leaves at 9:00, sitting at a cafe and chatting with his friends before then. </p>

<p>Ask the Schkoder-Ulcinj driver to drop you off at the bus stop. The rest is easy –
Montenegro has much more signage for its bus system than Albania does.</p>

<p><strong>Don’t forget to have your passport ready for border control!</strong></p>

<p>Below is the location of the buses in Schkoder.</p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2961.8742367571995!2d19.513413874485096!3d42.06731499235399!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x134e00fb86c50699%3A0xb04ce3e5ed35f40f!2sRruga+Teuta%2C+Shkod%C3%ABr%2C+Albania!5e0!3m2!1sen!2s!4v1441188846897" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="leg-3-ulcinj-to-budva">Leg 3: Ulcinj to Budva</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.25 hours</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €7</p>

<p>According to possibly-outdated information from the internet, there are only two buses direct from
Ulcinj to Kotor in a day. It may be possible to catch a bus directly to Kotor; otherwise, head to
Budva. </p>

<p>An alternative option is to go from Ulcinj to Bar, but buses from Bar to Kotor are less frequent. </p>

<p>I’m not sure about the precise schedule, but buses from Ulcinj to Budva should be fairly frequent. 
I arrived from Ulcinj five minutes before a bus was leaving for Budva.</p>

<h2 id="leg-4-budva-to-kotor">Leg 4: Budva to Kotor</h2>

<p><strong>Duration:</strong> 1.25 hours</p>

<p><strong>Fare:</strong> €3</p>

<p>From Budva, buses leave to Kotor every thirty minutes.</p>

<h2 id="fare">Fare</h2>

<p>500 lek + €5 + €7 + €3 = <strong>€18</strong></p>

<p>This is much cheaper than the “direct transfer service” offered by Montenegro Hostel from Tirana to
Kotor (€35). </p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transportation from Tirana to Durres / Schkoder (Albania)]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-31 00:00:00 +0200</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2015/08/31/tirana-durres-schkoder-albania</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This article contains bus directions based on my travels in Albania in August 2015. 
Durres is a coastal city around thirty minutes away, containing
ferries to Italy and beaches. </p>

<p>Schkoder is a historical city around 1.25 to 1.75 hours away,
depending on traffic. It is a northern border city with bus transfers to Ulcinj, Montenegro. </p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Confirm these
directions. Two years ago, the bus to Schkoder was at a different location, and some of the
directions that I found were outdated.</p>

<h2 id="directions-to-the-bus-stop">Directions to the bus stop</h2>

<p>The Google Maps diagram below shows the bus stop, which is in the roundabout of Karl Topia Square.
It shouldn’t be too hard to find the correct bus: each bus has a person shouting its destination.  </p>

<div style="text-align: center;">
<iframe src="https://www.google.com/maps/embed?pb=!1m18!1m12!1m3!1d2995.868120776664!2d19.804230999999994!3d41.333481!2m3!1f0!2f0!3f0!3m2!1i1024!2i768!4f13.1!3m3!1m2!1s0x0%3A0x0!2zNDHCsDIwJzAwLjUiTiAxOcKwNDgnMTUuMiJF!5e0!3m2!1sen!2sus!4v1441137271939" width="400" height="300" frameborder="0" style="border:0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</div>

<h2 id="bus">Bus</h2>

<p>The buses, known as <em>furgons</em>, are more akin to vans or cars. For an afternoon bus to Durres, I took
a van that fit approximately 15 people. For a 7 AM bus to Schkoder, the vehicle was someone’s
five-seat Volkswagen. Don’t be worried if it just seems like you’re getting in someone’s car (you
are).</p>

<p>The buses don’t leave until they are full or almost full. For Durres, this seems to be approximately
every thirty minutes. For Schkoder, this seems to be approximately every hour. </p>

<p class="minipic"><img src="/images/travel/tiranabus/bus.jpg" alt="Vans that will take you through beautiful Albania" /></p>

<h2 id="fare">Fare</h2>

<p>In August 2015, the fare for each direction was:</p>

<ul>
  <li>150 lek to Durres</li>
  <li>500 lek to Schkoder</li>
</ul>

<p>The drivers take euro. If you want to get rid of some remaining lek, they also take euro-lek mix.</p>

<p>Enjoy the Albanian music on the drive!</p>

<p><em>Last updated: August 2015</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
