<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: istanbul | Louis Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/categories/istanbul/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2020-07-09T14:09:27+03:00</updated>
  <id>http://louisrli.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Louis Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Istanbul Frontend Bootcamp Retrospective]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/02/teaching-thoughts/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-02 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/02/teaching-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This post is a compendium of my thoughts as an instructor for a
non-profit coding bootcamp teaching frontend web development (JavaScript and
React). It first establishes the context, then explores the best ways to
maximize teaching impact based on the constraints of the context.</p>

<p>This post has four parts:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Why is this bootcamp different from other ways people learn
coding?</li>
  <li>Two teaching philosophies</li>
  <li>Concrete strategies for practitioners</li>
  <li>Miscellaneous thoughts</li>
</ol>

<!-- more -->

<h1 id="differences-from-traditional-bootcamps">Differences from traditional bootcamps</h1>
<p>In this section, I set the context for this bootcamp and discuss some
important differences to keep in mind between this bootcamp and other
coding class settings, primarily with respect to time and money investment. The
purpose of this background is to start the reader thinking about how these might
affect the students’ mentality.</p>

<h2 id="the-istanbul-bootcamp">The Istanbul Bootcamp</h2>

<p>The bootcamp is approximately five months, with three months of classes and
approximately two months of a final project. The students are mostly
Turkish and Syrian in nationality. The class size is approximately 24. The
male-female ratio is approximately 60-40.</p>

<p>During the application process, the students are asked to do an HTML/CSS
exercise, but otherwise, no previous coding experience is required. However,
some students certainly have more existing experience than others, which has the
potential to demoralize students.</p>

<h2 id="from-universities">From universities</h2>
<p>Compared to universities, there are two primary differences in the bootcamp:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Students do not pay for the bootcamp</li>
  <li>Students are not graded in the bootcamp</li>
</ol>

<p>I encourage the reader to consider this question: “why do students in
university make an effort?”</p>

<h2 id="from-paid-bootcamps">From paid bootcamps</h2>
<p>Compared to paid bootcamps, the students are not paying a large sum of money.
The tuition of HackReactor is $18,000. That’s quite an investment.</p>

<h2 id="ramifications">Ramifications</h2>
<p>We’ve established some of the differences between this bootcamp and other
similar venues of teaching coding. Next, let’s consider some 
consequences of these discrepancies.</p>

<p>In this section, I won’t discuss solutions. I will simply posit some salient
problems.</p>

<h3 id="ease-of-quitting">Ease of quitting</h3>
<p>In this context, the threshold for quitting is much lower than in university or
paid bootcamps.</p>

<p>Our bootcamp students frequently broach the idea of quitting during stressful
times, likely because the sunk cost is low. In contrast, in university or
paid bootcamps, the threshold is higher, because the student doesn’t want to
lose three years of money/time invested or ten thousand US dollars,
respectively.</p>

<h3 id="lack-of-motivation-to-do-assignments">Lack of motivation to do assignments</h3>
<p>Consider this hypothetical: if a university had no grades and no exams, how many
students would do the assignments as compared to a university that had these?</p>

<p>Even in considering this hypothetical, one can see the problem. There is no
external motivator or metric for our bootcamps’ students. Students should only
be removed from the bootcamp for particularly egregious behavior, but it is
certainly not taken lightly – part of our ethical responsibility is to
encourage them psychologically.</p>

<p>One of my favorite phrases, for all parts of life: “you can’t make anyone do
anything in this world” (barring duress and so on).</p>

<h3 id="propensity-to-complain">Propensity to complain</h3>
<p>In general, students in our bootcamps like to gripe about various parts of the
bootcamp: homework, projects, process, class, etc. Whether this is due to a
cultural or a venue difference, I can’t say.</p>

<p>However, I do believe that one reason for this propensity for complaining is the
aforementioned lack of investment, which emboldens the students. While
complaining is not inherently dangerous, a cycle of complaining potentially
causes students to demotivate each other and consequently increases the risk of
quitting.</p>

<p>Note that there is a nuance between feedback and complaining, and instructors
should still objectively evaluate complaints for genuine feedback.</p>

<h3 id="summary-of-differences">Summary of differences</h3>
<p>The summary of these differences is this: for our bootcamps, the student has
invested neither money nor time. The only way to motivate these students is to
<strong>foster an intrinsic interest in participating in the bootcamp</strong>.</p>

<p>The definition of “fostering intrinsic interest” will be expounded at length
below.</p>

<p>Outside the scope of this post: the filtering qualities of interviews are also
important in influencing student motivation.</p>

<h1 id="precursors-on-philosophy">Precursors on philosophy</h1>
<p>Before we continue into more concrete strategies, I want
to discuss two of my driving philosophies for teaching.</p>

<h2 id="treating-students-as-relationships">Treating students as relationships</h2>
<p>The first driving philosophy: <strong>the skills that I apply for teaching are
no different from those that I apply for a significant other or close friends</strong>.
That means understanding another individuals needs, desires, life state, past
experiences in the class, etc. What will make this person happy? What is this
person looking for? How can I provide these things?</p>

<p>I truly believe the following statement to be true: the success of this
particular coding bootcamp only slightly depends on how you teach the material,
<strong>it depends almost completely on how loved and motivated you make your students
feel</strong>. In this particular context, when the emotional environment is correct,
the students’ hard work and enthusiasm will follow.</p>

<p>This is not to say that coherent instruction does not make a difference – it
does. But in an art that requires self-research and emotional discipline from
students, a caring instructor with mediocre teaching skills will be far more
impactful than an emotionally-neutered instructor with excellent teaching
skills.</p>

<h2 id="maximizing-impact-for-time">Maximizing impact for time</h2>
<p>The second driving philosophy: find time-cheap but psychologically-impactful
ways to treat students.</p>

<p>Consider this question:
<strong>given that I have N students, how can I make them all feel loved and motivated
while minimizing the average amount of time I spend on an individual student?</strong></p>

<p>The things that I describe below, for the most part, will not eat up your
time. I wouldn’t do them if they did. But with this “one weird trick”, five
to fifteen minutes of your time can make all the difference in the world.</p>

<p>For what it’s worth, this graph represents all aspects of my life, not just
teaching. It makes life a bit easier, in my humble opinion, to hunt for these
optimizations.</p>

<p><img src="/images/graph.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<h1 id="fostering-intrinsic-interest">Fostering intrinsic interest</h1>
<p>Intrinsic interest means that the student cares, in their heart, about doing
well in the course, completing the assignments, and learning the material. A
non-exhaustive list of where intrinsic interest comes from:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The student feels cared for by the instructors</li>
  <li>The student feels pride in their work</li>
  <li>The student respects the instructors as people</li>
  <li>The student wants to continue despite hardships in coursework</li>
</ul>

<p>In the absence of any other external motivators, our bootcamps have no choice
but to rely on intrinsic interest. This section focuses on
providing <strong>concrete strategies</strong> for intrinsically motivating students. Each
section simultaneously posits a principle and pairs it with a description of a
real, implementable strategy.</p>

<p>This post is not meant to be a solely theoretical
exploration of what motivates students; these actions are intended to be
executed by practitioners.</p>

<h2 id="the-illusion-of-individual-attention">The illusion of individual attention</h2>
<p>I call this the illusion of individual attention, because in a class of 24, it’s
not possible for you to truly give sustained individual attention to every student.
However, you can perpetuate the idea that you are trying your best to get
individual attention to every student.</p>

<p>In a class of this size, students don’t expect individual attention. In fact, I
find that most students are very understanding of the fact that the instructors
are trying to juggle between the students.</p>

<p>Surprisingly, the students’ understanding of this is something that you
can capitalize on. When you <em>do</em> show a student individual attention, their
awareness of the resource constraints causes them to appreciate your efforts
even more, consequently inspiring them.</p>

<p>The ultimate cost of the actions below are very low, but they mean the world to
the students. Recall our efforts to maximize impact for minimal time.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Initial one-on-ones:</strong> Have a one-on-one with each student at the beginning of the course.</li>
  <li><strong>Availability for one-on-ones:</strong> Allocate one to two hours each week for 20 minute one-on-ones with students.
Even if they never capitalize on it, they appreciate the fact that it’s
possible.</li>
  <li><strong>Occasional check-ins:</strong> Occasionally message students randomly to ask how they’re doing or what their
thoughts are. It takes less than two minutes of time to message ten students.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="constructing-a-serious-environment">Constructing a serious environment</h2>
<p>The environment and tone that the teaching staff sets is by far one of the most
important things to do. If you seem to be lax about their performance, they will
certainly be lax about their performance.</p>

<p>I’ll cover this section with an anecdote.</p>

<p>The way I came to understand this is a bit amusing, in my opinion. After a few
strict lectures to the class, a number of students approached me concerned
about their performance or actions in the course. (Slightly unrelated note: when
you give strict talks to your whole class about assignments and such, I realized
that every student thinks you’re talking directly about them, even if they’re
doing completely fine).</p>

<p>While my external self had always taken the class very seriously – and my
internal self, of course, to a certain extent – I was truly surprised by how
worried these students were about their performance in the class. My initial
reaction was: “It was just a prank bro. I’m just a kid that likes to
breakdance (not a strict teacher trying to berate you).”</p>

<p>The reason that this surprised me so much was that, previously, I did feel like
I had trouble motivating my students to do their work. After all, recall the
differences that we established in the beginning. There are no grades. There is
no invested money. That’s not to say my students wouldn’t take it seriously, but
why are they taking it <em>this</em> seriously?</p>

<p>But then I realized, that I had unintentionally stumbled upon something that
I’ve always known in my relationships and friendships: <strong>If you are proactive
about taking something seriously, the other person will be much more likely to
take it seriously.</strong> Don’t sit around waiting for the other person to be the one
to do so.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Communicate your investment:</strong> “I take your education very seriously, and I
expect you to take it seriously too.”</li>
  <li><strong>Show with your actions:</strong> Words only mean so much in this world. Show your
students you take it seriously in the quality of your teaching and your
interactions with your students (see all the other sections).</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="professionalism-and-personalization">Professionalism and personalization</h2>

<h3 id="professionalism">Professionalism</h3>
<p>The more professional your content is, the more it reinforces students’ belief
in the authority and legitimacy of the classroom.</p>

<p>Suppose the contrasting hypothetical: your slides are poorly written; your
assignment instructions have no consistent formatting; your in-class activities
are full of typos. Inevitably, your students will start learning from other
content on the internet, and they’ll come to the following realization: “Wow,
the teaching materials that our teacher is giving us are shit quality.”</p>

<p>Among my students in particular, I have noticed how captivated they are by the
professional and formal aspects presented by the organization’s onboarding and
branding. To capitalize on that captivation, this professionalism needs to be
continued in the classroom.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Professional content:</strong> All slides, assignments, and course material should
be formatted professionally and flawlessly. Minimize typos.</li>
  <li><strong>Agenda slides:</strong> Show an agenda slide at the beginning of each class. It
provides a sense of official-ness, like university.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="personalization">Personalization</h3>
<p>Students like the idea that the organization is doing something for them. <em>Just</em> for
them. This doesn’t mean that you have to write the assignment
from scratch, but it should at least be presented in a manner that suggests that
you’re thinking of the student. Recall the goal: <strong>make the student feel cared
for</strong>.</p>

<p>Compare the following two situations:</p>

<p><strong>Positive impact</strong></p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Teacher: We thought about where the class currently is, and the teaching staff
designed this activity for you all based on your feedback and struggles.
Please do this activity.</p>

  <p>Student: Wow, the teacher put in so much effort for us!</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Neutral impact</strong> (but probably negative if chronic)</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>Teacher: Here’s a link to this site, please do this activity.</p>

  <p>Student: Sure.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Revamp outside resources:</strong> Avoid chronically linking to other resources for
activities. Either put them in your own document or write your own, giving
proper attribution as needed.  Even the act of putting it in your own document
pushes this edge.</li>
  <li><strong>Emphasize your effort:</strong> Mention to your students how the material was made
by your organization on their behalf. Let them know you made an effort for
them.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="projects-that-express-self-identity">Projects that express self-identity</h2>
<p>In the absence of grades, one of the best motivators for effort is to allow
students to express themselves through their work. Humans like expressing
themselves. Humans like to build things, look at them, and say, “This is me. I did
this.” This is a fact, and we can capitalize on this fact in order to
incentivize students.</p>

<p>When ten groups of students do assignments that all look almost exactly the
same, the student does not think, “This is me. I did this.”</p>

<p>My own students have constantly surprised me with how much effort they put into
projects. For example, they come into office hours and talk about the hours
working on something (styling, a special feature they came up, etc.) that was
outside the stated project requirements. Part of this is because I personally
would never do anything beyond the minimal requirements, but part of it is
because, until I was blown away repeatedly by this phenomenon, I had never
realized the power of allowing students to invest their identity in their work.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>

<p>Devise coding projects with open-ended interpretations (in styling or
functionality).</p>

<p>Different project designs can have different degrees of self-identity; I would
argue that some non-zero amount is necessary for every project.</p>

<p>For example, the final project of our course was “the board
project”, which required only the very general concept of boards and items that
could be put on boards. The ultimate result was a wide array of projects with a
personal touch: to-do lists, cookbooks, course project trackers, and the
students ultimately invested much more time than if we had assigned a “to-do
list project.”</p>

<h2 id="social-cohesion">Social cohesion</h2>
<p>When the social aspect of the class is strong, students try harder. Part of it
is that they enjoy the class, but part of it is that most people don’t want to
be known by their friends as the student who doesn’t try.</p>

<p>So the question is this: how do you encourage people to like each other? To be
honest, as instructors, we don’t have much agency here; you can’t make people
form bonds. However, you can try your best to facilitate situations where it can
happen.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Project partners:</strong> Select project partners with the intent of forming bonds between students of
similar levels</li>
  <li><strong>Promoting thought:</strong> Ask students who their favorite people to work with are (not for any
particular reason other than for them to ponder this question)</li>
  <li><strong>Allocate time for small socialization</strong>: Encourage socializing and jokes in class, allocate “empty time”</li>
  <li><strong>Use office hours:</strong> Leave time in office hours for students to chat with each other</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="expression-of-belief">Expression of belief</h2>
<p>Coding bootcamps can be quite intense for some of the students. There will come
a time when some students don’t believe in themselves or their ability to
understand the content. And when that time comes,
it’s not important whether or not you believed in them, it’s important whether
or not you <strong>communicated that you believed in them</strong>.</p>

<p>I again emphasize the illusion of individual attention.</p>

<p><strong>Concrete actions</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Individual messaging:</strong> Identifying students that are struggling, and telling them, directly to their
face (via Zoom, this is 2020), that you believe in them. Offer them the option
to meet one-on-one.</li>
  <li><strong>Humbling your journey:</strong> Show that you, too, come from humble beginnings. Whether that means you
went through a bootcamp yourself, or that you struggled a lot when you started
coding, show the students that their struggle is normal. For example, I showed
my students emails from my first two months in coding where I sent emails to
my friend raging about bugs in my code. I had multiple students tell me that
this humanized my journey despite the pedigree.</li>
  <li><strong>Inspirational speeches:</strong> Be liberal with the inspirational speeches in
class. They never stop feeling weird to me, but it matters.</li>
  <li><strong>Emphasize first exposure:</strong> Tell your students that when you show them
something for the first time, they’re not expected to understand it. A phrase
my students are familiar with: “This is just a first exposure.”</li>
</ul>

<h1 id="other-takeaways">Other takeaways</h1>
<p>These are miscellaneous addenda that don’t belong in the categories above, but
these are points I would tell myself if I could travel back in time. In the end,
these happened naturally, but I didn’t codify them into thoughts until the
middle of the course.</p>

<h2 id="teaching-a-way-of-thinking">Teaching a way of thinking</h2>
<p>I encourage you to ask yourself this question: “at the end of the course, who do
I hope my students to be?”</p>

<p>It’s not my place to say what the right or wrong answer is. If you’re a teacher,
you set the goals. But by the way, there is a wrong answer, and that wrong
answer is: “a student that knows JavaScript and React.”</p>

<p>The right answer is that the student:</p>
<ul>
  <li>is no longer scared to learn a new technology or tool</li>
  <li>never compares himself or herself to other people again</li>
  <li>is unfazed by setbacks, even when a small bug costs five hours of time
(instead of thinking, “programming is not for me”)</li>
</ul>

<p>I’m certain this is not a novel idea I’m proposing; most successful introductory
computer science courses, such as CS50, operate along the same mentality.</p>

<p>But I’d like to note something interesting here. None of the things above have
to do with specific knowledge of a subject; <strong>they all pertain to how the
students think as people</strong>.</p>

<p>With these goals in mind, here are some modes of operation:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Constantly introduce new things:</strong> Spend the course bombarding students with
new things. Just as they start to feel comfortable with something, you
introduce something (perhaps only slightly) new on top of it.</li>
  <li><strong>Demo your thought process:</strong> When feasible, walk the student how you thought
about the problem. “You see, I just Googled this thing.” “I worked backwards
from this variable to find the issue.”</li>
  <li><strong>Comfort your students:</strong> When your students finally fix a bug that took them
forever, comfort them psychologically. Tell them it’s normal. Emphasize your
belief in them.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="trust-the-process">Trust the process</h2>
<p>The students will learn the material eventually – trust the process. I’ll admit
that even I wasn’t sure whether my students were learning anything at some
point. There were times in the course when almost all of the students seemed
completely lost in all of the in-class activities (to be fair, I was also
pushing the pace very quickly).</p>

<p>Luckily, I had my trusty teaching partner Ammar, who informed me that
these struggles were normal. In the same way that I tell my students, “Hey, this
is normal,” Ammar’s evaluation sealed away any concerns I had. In the end, I
trust Ammar’s judgment completely, given that he’d experienced two bootcamps
before me.</p>

<p>I’ll also say this: in-class activities are a very short amount of time to exercise
real exploration beyond basics. The core of the learning will come from the
multi-week projects that students do. That’s the real shit, pardon my French.
And if the students are invested in completing projects, the learning will
follow.</p>

<h1 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h1>
<p>At this point, I’d like to highlight a critical observation: <strong>none of these
actions take much time</strong>. They are simply small flourishes to the interactions
with students.</p>

<p>But if you’ve ever played any skill-based game, then you’ll be familiar with
this concept: the people who are the best at anything in life are those that
push all the smallest advantages. The best chess players leave no tradeoff
unpunished. The best football players leave no misstep unexploited. Capitalizing
on small edges differentiates one who is the best at something and one who is
average.</p>

<p>Finally, achieving anything in our lives is a function of our goals, and
it’s good to recall our broader goals. In whatever context you teach
in, I encourage you to refresh your goals. For Re:Coded, they would be this:</p>

<ul>
  <li>To teach students the programmer mindset</li>
  <li>To empower students to obtain and excel at a development job</li>
</ul>

<p>And to achieve these goals, we should not simply be settling at teaching our
students React and JavaScript. The question is not where can we take the
students, but <em>how far</em> can we take them?</p>

<p>And for that reason, I urge you to never be complacent with your students.</p>

<p>One hour of your time per week could be the difference between your student hating
or loving the course.</p>

<p>Two hours of your time per week could be the difference between your student
landing a frontend job or not.</p>

<p>Three hours of your time per week could be the difference between your student
landing a job on a weak currency or a strong one.</p>

<p>Calculate the margins, and remember the graph.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Traveling from Istanbul to Şile by Bus]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/01/istanbul-to-sile/"/>
    <updated>2020-07-01 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/07/01/istanbul-to-sile</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The intention of this post is to document how to travel from Istanbul to Şile by
bus. At the time of writing, there do not appear to be any English resources for
this route. The official IETT app and Google Maps both document this incorrectly.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>Şile is a popular place for the residents of Istanbul to escape for a day trip.
Technically, Şile is part of Istanbul, although it’s quite remote. The bus ride
is about two hours away; by car, it is about 45 minutes.</p>

<h2 id="bus-line">Bus Line</h2>
<p>Taking any bus that is prefixed with <strong>139</strong> is okay, all of them stop at Şile
first but their continuing routes after Şile may differ.</p>

<p>The
<a href="https://www.iett.istanbul/en/main/hatlar/139/%C3%9CSK%C3%9CDAR%20-%20%C5%9E%C4%B0LE-%C4%B0ETT-Otob%C3%BCs-Sefer-Saatleri-ve-Duraklar%C4%B1">IETT</a>
site gives a description of the stops; however, as explained below, the bus stop
location is incorrect on the site. Also note that this link only shows the 139
bus, but the 139A, 139T, etc. also run, meaning that there is approximately one
bus to Şile every hour.</p>

<p>The bus has various stops in the Şile area, though the bus terminal is a safe
bet for a place to get off.</p>

<h2 id="bus-stop-location">Bus Stop Location</h2>
<p><strong>Do not wait at the Üsküdar Marmaray bus station.</strong> The correct location for
this intercity bus is the Şemsipaşa stop (<a href="https://goo.gl/maps/3YyADTwU8gENbKk98">Google Maps
link</a>), which is about a block west.
There, you will see a paper with times for the bus to Şile.</p>

<p>A ticket is required for this bus. The place to purchase the tickets is about a
two minute walk from the bus stop (<a href="https://goo.gl/maps/R4AqwriFRpaxxnDp8">Google Maps
link</a>). At the time of writing (July
2020), a one way ticket was 14.50 lira. If you don’t speak Turkish, you probably
can’t get on the bus without a ticket, although I’ve been told it’s possible to
sit on the floor if the bus is full.</p>

<p>If you try to buy too close to the departure time, it’s possible that the bus
may be full.</p>

<p>It may be possible to buy online, but the author of this article doesn’t know
how.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sim Card Price in Turkey in February 2020]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sim-card</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Getting a SIM card in Turkey for short to medium term stays in Turkey is
straightforward. In this article, I describe my experience with prices in
<em>February 2020</em> using Turkcell.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>I bought my SIM card in Fatih. I’m actually not sure if what I got was a good
deal. Turkcell offers all types of short-term deals for tourists as well. I
visited three stores in Fatih and they all gave me approximately the same rate
(some trying to squeeze +/- 10 lira) without the option for any smaller plans.</p>

<p>These rates are for foreigners. You’ll see advertisements for cellphone data at
amazing prices, but these require a Turkish bank account.</p>

<h2 id="plans">Plans</h2>
<p>My plan was <strong>20 GB data for 120 lira</strong> (around 20 USD at the time of writing). However,
it should be noted that the 20 GB is <strong>for one month only</strong>.</p>

<p>Although the SIM card lasts for multiple months, you do need to top up in future
months. The top-up is at a rate rate that I don’t remember, but it’s much
cheaper than the initial upfront cost.</p>

<p>I didn’t really keep track of the SMS and call time in the plan, though that’s
included. It’s 2020, use WhatsApp :)</p>

<h3 id="long-term-stays">Long-term stays</h3>
<p>It should be noted that the SIM card situation for long-term stays (more than
120 days) gets much more expensive. You have to pay a foreigner registration fee
that’s more than 200 USD. I won’t go much into it here, but you can read about
it <a href="https://toomanyadapters.com/buying-sim-card-turkey/">on this page</a>.</p>

<h2 id="purchasing">Purchasing</h2>
<p>Bring your passport. It took about ten to fifteen minutes for the guy to finish
registering everything.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Sahibinden: The Craigslist of Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/sahibinden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Sahibinden</strong> (literally, “owners”) is the Craigslist equivalent of Turkey.</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="usage">Usage</h2>

<p>In order to respond to listings (at least housing listings, in my experience),
you do need access to a Turkish cellphone number. The site will ask you to enter
a verification code that is texted to the Turkish number before you can respond.</p>

<h2 id="housing">Housing</h2>
<p>Sahibinden’s housing search is top-notch. In addition to the filters that one
would expect such as flat type and price, it also allows filtering by
furnished/unfurnished, renting from owner/broker, building age.</p>

<p><img src="/images/travel/sahibinden/example.png" alt="Example map search" /></p>

<p>On a separate topic, finding housing in Istanbul has a number of options. I’d
recommend reading <a href="https://yabangee.com/finding-a-flat-in-istanbul-a-basic-guide-to-accommodation/">this article</a>, particularly on the difference between renting
from a broker and an owner.</p>

<p>Note: I do dispute one part of this article. They say that renting through an
owner usually has higher quality furnishing. At least in Sisli, my experience
was the opposite: broker flats tended to be newer and have better
furnishing. Most importantly, there were way more broker listings than owner
listings, which meant that the options were “better” for my specific needs based
purely on a higher volume of selection.</p>

<h3 id="avoiding-shady-housing-deals">Avoiding shady housing deals</h3>
<p>Like Craigslist, Sahibinden actually includes a warning about housing scams,
though it’s in Turkish. This notification is mostly common sense: don’t wire
money to anyone you haven’t actually met.</p>

<p>I also found that some ads seemed to reuse pictures from other ads (e.g., two
flats in different locations with the exact same pictures and different owners).
Usually, one of them (I believe) is a scam. Longer-term accounts have a
small award image for how long they’ve been on Sahibinden (e.g., 11 years); the
shady ones had no such image. I’m not saying all accounts without the award are
scams, but if you run into two ads with the same pictures, the legitimate one is
probably the certified one.</p>

<p>My friend that lives in Istanbul also told me a few other things to watch out
for when using Sahibinden for housing:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Renting daily flats through Sahibinden is difficult (even short- to
medium- term can be a bit of a hassle, as many owners want stable tenants.
However, when renting from a broker, they do like short-term tenants because
they usually charge the full broker fee of one month’s rent).</li>
  <li>Posters will often post really nice looking pictures but the apartment
actually looks a lot worse in person.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best ATM (No-Fee) in Istanbul, Turkey]]></title>
    <link href="http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey/"/>
    <updated>2020-02-21 00:00:00 +0300</updated>
    <id>http://louisrli.github.io/blog/2020/02/21/best-atm-in-istanbul-turkey</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The best ATM in Istanbul, Turkey is a coveted title. There’s a lot of banks that
accept international cards, but some of them will try to extract more money from
you via service fee or dynamic currency conversion (DCC).</p>

<p>The best ATM is <strong>HSBC</strong> (only 1000 lira at a time, mixed denominations).</p>

<!-- more -->

<h2 id="the-best-atm-hsbc">The Best ATM: HSBC</h2>
<p>At the moment, HSBC has no extra fees and serves mostly 100 TL bills with some
50 and 20 TL.</p>

<p>In February 2020, QNB used to allow large transactions, no fees, and serving
only 100 TL bills, but this is no longer the case as of June 2020.</p>

<p>Depending on the ATM, they may try to apply DCC, so when the DCC menu comes
up, make sure to click <strong>Istemiyorum</strong> (it was on the left side), which means:
“I do not want.” Make sure you say no to DCC. DCC is very bad (Google it).</p>

<p>See the table below for a relative comparison.</p>

<h2 id="atm-comparisons">ATM Comparisons</h2>
<p>Credit for this table goes to <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Turkey/comments/cute4k/a_guide_to_turkish_atms_if_you_are_using_a_card/">some anonymous user on
Reddit</a>, who I’m actually,
very truly grateful for taking the time to write and do this exploration. As of
February 2020, I can verify that at least some of these were true, as I tried
about five ATMs in central Sisli.</p>

<p>If you have any updates or additions to this table, please add them below.</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Bank</th>
      <th>Non-DCC Fee</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>HSBC</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Mixed bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>AKBANK</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 20 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>HalkBank</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 5 TL/10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>ZiraatBanksi</td>
      <td>None</td>
      <td>Only 10 TL bills</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>VakifBank</td>
      <td>Flat 10 lira fee</td>
      <td>I went to one and it was 4%.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>QNB Finansbank</td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Garanti</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Bankamatik</td>
      <td>2.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>YapiKredi</td>
      <td>3%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Denizbank</td>
      <td>3.5%</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h2 id="fees-on-the-card-side">Fees on the card side</h2>
<p>This is not really an advertisement, since I don’t really make money
from this blog.</p>

<p>In addition to the fees charged by the owning bank of the ATM, the owning bank
of the card might also have foreign transaction fees. I use Charles Schwab (for
my god-bless USA of bank account), which has no fees. It also waives ATM fees,
but I’ve actually never been sure if that works for international bank fees such as
the ones above.</p>

<p>If for whatever reason this inspires you to sign up for Schwab, I have <a href="http://www.schwab.com/public/schwab/nn/refer-prospect.html?refrid=REFERY23JXD3D">this
referral
link</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
